<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ntoll.org</title><link>https://ntoll.org/</link><description>Everything I say is false...</description><atom:link href="https://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:ntoll@ntoll.org"&gt;Nicholas H.Tollervey&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 16:54:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A Social Media Hermit</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/social-media-hermit/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have deleted my Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I no longer use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social media isn't fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are better ways to connect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retaining my account feels hypocritical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, that's all there is to it (and it feels good).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter encourages infantile, reactionary and shallow discourse. What do you
expect from a technology that enforces a 280 character limit and trains us to
read in bite size chunks? Twitter may as well enforce &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak"&gt;other arbitrary
limitations&lt;/a&gt;, for example the exclusive
use of monosyllabic words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want no part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If folks genuinely want to connect with me, they'll be in touch (as I will be
with them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/social-media-hermit/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 07:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Being Together</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/on-being-together/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Some raw thoughts I've written down solely to help me clarify my thinking.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being together with people I love and who love me in return is a source of
great joy and solace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet being with people can also lead to distress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many, I've encountered rejection and resulting feelings of loneliness,
I've been the target of ignorant nastiness, and some make it clear I am of no
value while others happily place unreasonable burdens upon me. My own
experiences are but a small selection from the menu of unwelcome situations
that could be, and often are, meted out to people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dealing with complicated experiences and finding a way to work through
challenging encounters often feels painful and can lead to a sense of failure
or hopelessness. But I believe this process is also an opportunity for growth,
albeit through small, difficult, and often misplaced, steps. Allowing
complicated feelings, pain and failure to manifest is certainly better than the
alternative: sweeping things out of sight means the distress is never
addressed, explored or dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, being together requires conscious work and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good stuff can take as much effort as the bad. To be loving, compassionate,
tolerant and forgiving towards others requires great strength of character. The
bad stuff shows we are all flawed sensitive beings whose strength often fails
us. We have an endless capacity to hurt and be hurt by each other. This is
especially true if we don't allow ourselves the time and energy to reflect upon
and consciously adjust our behaviour towards each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, some simply don't care for others or for such self reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, narcissists (by definition) lack empathy or compassion and only
make an effort in relationships if they see a benefit to themselves. This is a
tragic form of ignorance, for they will never know the joy of relationships
shared with loved ones who reciprocate emotional investment and mutual care.
For them, being together is an exercise in self aggrandisement, domination or
profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origins of such self-centredness are complicated. Ironically, introspection
and self-reflection - the very traits such people fail to exercise - would help
address and overcome such origins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe everyone has a unique and valuable journey through life, even if
their current location or direction of travel is deeply problematic.
Recognising this applies to a narcissist or other difficult individual takes
(the afore mentioned) strength of character. But it means it is possible to be
together without getting crushed by the weight of their ego or toxic behaviour.
Sadly, sometimes this is simply not possible and you have to cut your losses
and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often wonder how to respond to the difficulties that arise from being
together with others. I continue to believe that being together is often a
privilege and a source of happiness and growth. Yet some of my recent
collaborations have also been a source of great pain (interactions with aspects
of the Python community
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/compassion/"&gt;spring to mind&lt;/a&gt;). As a result, my
feelings about being together have changed significantly over the past
couple of years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to be all about promoting "the community" as a way of being together.
An immediate problem is "the community" is an amorphous blob of a term that
folks never pin down. This is a significant cause of many problems as
misunderstanding is rife. In any case, I naively contributed and volunteered my
code, time, effort and money. In short, I tried very hard to be a positive part
of "something". For the past 12 years or so, this "something" was the Python
programming community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, there are two common contrasting ways folks describe or
think about the notion of "community": top-down (meaning the community is
managed) and bottom-up (where the community emerges through participation). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always been reticent about top-down bureaucratic, formal and
hierarchical notions of community. Often they are well meaning yet ineffectual
(or sometimes even damaging) self defeating processes. They can also easily
turn into toxic dumpster fires full of malice (politics and power plays being
well known examples of contributing factors to such a sorry state of affairs).
Finally, they tend to gain a momentum that makes it easy to squash and ignore
rather than cherish and nourish individuals and creative innovation. While
my experience of the "formal" Python community has mostly been extraordinarily
positive, there has been enough not-so-good-stuff that I've chosen to step
away. I can only but wish the Python community well, but it's a ship in which I
no longer sail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don't want to find myself in a chaotic bottom-up community either.
While these are ad hoc, improvised and informal, there is still a hierarchy,
along with impositions of power and other negative political machinations.
These are lived out through hidden communication channels, gossip or because
the loudest or most charismatic folks hold the floor. People are either "in"
or "out" of the circle of these "movers and shakers".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least more formal communities appear to be up front about hierarchy, the
exercise of power, the scope and relations of roles and how one assumes
positions therein..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't help but feel that something is missing when we view communities as
such formal structures. Communities are collections of individual people and,
perhaps, the missing element to make sense of being together is an explicit
focus on the "character" of participants. Just how do individuals reflect and
choose to behave when being together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm reminded of &lt;a href="https://www.lewissociety.org/innerring/"&gt;this rather interesting essay&lt;/a&gt;,
by C.S.Lewis. I first read it when I was a music undergraduate and found it via
my Christian room-mate. Lewis describes an "Inner Ring", something akin to the
circle of "movers and shakers" vying for influence, power and prestige that I
describe above. The part of the essay that most speaks to me comes at the very
end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"And if in your spare time you consort simply with the people you like, you
will again find that you have come unawares to a real inside: that you are
indeed snug and safe at the centre of something which, seen from without,
would look exactly like an Inner Ring. But the difference is that the secrecy
is accidental, and its exclusiveness a by-product, and no one was led thither
by the lure of the esoteric: for it is only four or five people who like one
another meeting to do things that they like. This is friendship. Aristotle
placed it among the virtues. It causes perhaps half of all the happiness in
the world, and no Inner Ring can ever have it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaching back in time to feel like my 18 year old undergraduate self, I want to
be with folks who are open to compassionate, collaborative, cooperative
ways of working but without any extra problematic notions of "community" (as
described above). I simply want to bring myself, and welcome others who want to
join me, in a place where there's recognition, a connection, frisson or
creative energy from which we can mutually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, I am inviting friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendship requires trust, honesty, tolerance, compassion and forgiveness...
all those things that depend upon strength of character. Putting in such effort
for others is the antipode of the machinations needed to become one of the "in"
crowd or a member of the organisational elite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here's the thing... the tech world has its fair share of folks who forget or
don't understand what I believe makes a place positive, friendly and safe when
being with each other. Such folks see collaboration in terms of gaining
prestige and power. This is the stuff of narcissistic day dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an organised community such behaviour is addressed by a code of conduct (and
the Python community spend a lot of time and energy acting on this with varying
degrees of success, from [alas] hollow virtue signalling through to very
effective networks of support centred on extraordinarily kind and caring
individuals). Conversely, informal communities tend to lack this sort of
public or explicit "framework" often with detrimental results (folks are able
to capitalize, abuse or manipulate the informal "hidden" networks and
relationships to selfish or unpleasant ends with no clear way to call them
out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My focus on self-reflection and things within my own control explains why I've
found myself writing a sort of poetic personal code I call
"&lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/being_together"&gt;on being together&lt;/a&gt;".
I'll make it a part of all my future coding projects (and encountering
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Xe/creators-code"&gt;Xe's Creator's Code&lt;/a&gt;
inspired this effort). It's very much a work in progress and has become an
expression of what you can expect from me and what I hope from you should we
find ourselves "being together" in a place to collaborate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
When being together, especially if things go wrong,&lt;br&gt;
we acknowledge and work through differences.&lt;br&gt;
In so doing, we transform and enlarge each other.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
To nurture our mutual growth,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    this is a place of&lt;br&gt;
        learning, understanding, and sharing;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    this is a place to&lt;br&gt;
        affirm tolerance and compassion;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    this is a place for&lt;br&gt;
        collaborative creativity.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
All the aspects of yourself you choose to bring to this place&lt;br&gt;
are welcome here.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Reciprocate! Welcome, embrace and learn from others&lt;br&gt;
(even in the face of apparent hostility or misunderstanding).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
To act against this spirit invites ostracism,&lt;br&gt;
a loss that diminishes us all.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Thank you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/on-being-together/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 16:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Twisty Passages at EuroPython 2020 </title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/twisty-passages-at-europython/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ep2020.europython.eu/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; took place last month and the
raw video footage of the talks has just been published online. EuroPython has
always been one of my favourite conferences and is a special place for me:
it's where I gave my first ever programming talk back in 2010. It's also one of
the most culturally cosmopolitan coding conferences and was the world's
first community organised Python software conference. I always come away
feeling enriched by EuroPython.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, as always, to the volunteer organisers who work so hard to bring about
this remarkable event. Such thanks are especially well deserved in 2020 since
it was held online due to the spread of the COVID-19 virus. The potential for
technical mishaps and problems was huge, yet the friendly and supportive team
behind the conference ensured a slick and engaging event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, there were many great talks with a particular highlight for me being
a fascinating explanation of building "artistic artefacts" (computer generated
pictures in the style of human painters) with
&lt;a href="https://ep2020.europython.eu/talks/BSeL2FG-painting-with-gans-challenges-and-technicalities-of-neural-style-transfer/"&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I sorely missed the corridor track - when you walk around the physical
conference venue and bump into an old buddy, find yourself striking up a
conversation with a friendly co-attendee in the coffee queue, or join a huddle
of welcoming folks discussing something interesting. The corridor track is
where the community comes alive. I'll have more to say about this in a
moment...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to make two contributions to this year's conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was a wonderful opportunity to bring some music to the conference. My
friend and EuroPython's own force of nature,
&lt;a href="https://www.malemburg.com/marc-andre-lemburg"&gt;Marc-André&lt;/a&gt; got in touch
to say that they were looking for musical contributions to a "jam session". I
have, on several occasions, inflicted my love of tubas on Marc-André so
he knew I used to be a professional classical musician. I can only assume his 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hzJZObBSU7E"&gt;Germanic inclination for oompah-bands&lt;/a&gt;
was at the back of his mind when he reached out. I responded that tuba music is
"rather niche" at the best of times, let alone as part of a "jam session".
Nevertheless, I agreed to contribute something, "perhaps a piece of classical
piano music?" (since I'd been playing lots of piano during lock-down here in
the UK).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I went for some
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Brahms"&gt;Brahms&lt;/a&gt; ~ an
&lt;a href="https://www.mfiles.co.uk/scores/brahms-intermezzo-op118-no2.pdf"&gt;Intermezzo&lt;/a&gt;
written "as a token of friendship" for his friend, the concert pianist and
composer &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clara_Schumann"&gt;Clara Schumann&lt;/a&gt;. It's
my musical token of friendship towards everyone at EuroPython.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/V2nCyL0hZko" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second contribution was
&lt;a href="https://ep2020.europython.eu/talks/AGaSaW8-how-to-run-a-corridor-track-in-a-remote-conference-with-python/"&gt;a presentation&lt;/a&gt;.
The slides I prepared, including the links to all the resources I mention
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/static/presentations/textsmith_ep2020/index.html#/"&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation is an exploration of how one might recreate a remote corridor
track via the internet. I think it speaks for itself (honestly, go watch it, I
had a lot of fun preparing and presenting it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0FC5T396NVk" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary is that I feel deeply uncomfortable about the way friendships,
conversation and community are mediated in a technical context at this moment
in time. This is something we should be especially concerned about given how
much of our interactions have taken place online during these times of virus
related lock-down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offer a quick explanation of what I find so uncomfortable about the current
state of the art and look into the history of computing for other, more humane,
respectful (of users) and creative means of communication via computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I describe how I'm using Python to recreate a programmable
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MUD"&gt;MUD&lt;/a&gt; (a multi-user, real time text based
virtual world) based upon ideas first explored in the late 1970s and which I
encountered in both the 1980s (while at school) and in the mid-1990s (when I
was at university). Such creations were famous for their mazes of twisty
passages that players could explore and inhabit together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've never heard of MUDs before, here's
&lt;a href="https://mud.co.uk/richard/"&gt;Richard Bartle&lt;/a&gt; (one of the authors of the
original MUD and author of the
&lt;a href="https://mud.co.uk/dvw/"&gt;bible for virtual worlds&lt;/a&gt;) describing an old
technology for talking directly to the imagination...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Zctp972y_Eg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I love feedback, comments and constructive criticism offered in good
faith. Assuming the lock-downs have eased, next year's EuroPython will be in
Dublin, Éire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love Ireland. Can't wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you at next year's EuroPython!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/twisty-passages-at-europython/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2020 Changes</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/2020-changes/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've spent today updating everything to do with ntoll.org. Many
thanks to my buddy &lt;a href="https://kushaldas.in/"&gt;Kushal Das&lt;/a&gt; for the invaluable
advice on various technical matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what I've done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The website is run using &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; ~ a Python based
   static site generator. It was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; easy to migrate away from my previous
   hand-coded solution made with a custom
   &lt;a href="https://palletsprojects.com/p/flask/"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; script and HTML.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's hosted on &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; which is both free
   and makes it very easy to manage code and deployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've switched email hosting to &lt;a href="https://www.fastmail.com/"&gt;Fastmail&lt;/a&gt;, who 
   made the whole migration process extraordinarily easy. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've archived the code for the old website for "safe keeping", even though
   all the content has moved over to the new site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of things have changed in addition to my own technical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just finished a very busy period of freelance work with two clients -
the &lt;a href="https://freedom.press/"&gt;Freedom of the Press Foundation&lt;/a&gt; for whom I
contributed Python code to an
&lt;a href="https://securedrop.org/"&gt;application for journalists&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://digital.nhs.uk/"&gt;NHSDigital&lt;/a&gt; for whom I fulfilled the remote role of a
code mentor / developer coach (like an agile coach, but much more technical).
I was collaborating with a team of Java developers who were learning Python and
Django while building APIs for internal customers and users. I also provided
Python training, which was very rewarding since I love teaching and the
NHSDigital folks were already technically very strong and lots of fun. Both
teams were exceptionally talented and friendly. I had a blast and made lots of
new friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In just over a week I'll be starting a new gig with the
&lt;a href="https://mojdigital.blog.gov.uk/"&gt;Ministry of Justice&lt;/a&gt; as a senior Python
engineer. I'm &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; looking forward to this since the work is useful,
interesting and challenging. I'm looking forward to learning from my new
colleagues and making contributions to our collective effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for all my other projects (for instance
&lt;a href="https://codegrades.com/"&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://codewith.mu/"&gt;Mu&lt;/a&gt;)..?
Ironically, I believe I'll have more rhythm to my day and so my work on these
projects will continue in my own time, but at a more predictable pace. Watch
this space. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the current Corona virus pandemic is affecting life in rather
unforeseen ways: my daughter and older son have had their summer exams
cancelled. Apparently, their results will be based upon their predicted grades.
It means my daughter is going to read Mathematics at university with a
scholarship (dependent on her achieving her target grades, which she will in
light of the current situation) and my son will have the grades needed to go
onto study Physics, Maths, Music and Design Technology at "A" level (his
current plan is to read engineering at university). My youngest son continues
school lessons, completed at home via an online platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've also had to purchase some home-studio equipment (mics, pre-amp, monitor
speakers, midi keyboard and related audio software). Mary, my wife, uses this
to teach her many instrumental students remotely via video calls. It soon
became apparent that laptop or mobile phone mics are not great for cello
or piano teaching. Happily, the new equipment is proving to be a great success
and Mary is able to continue teaching most students without disruption and from
the comfort of our own music room:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Our home studio" src="https://ntoll.org/images/studio.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have the equipment available to produce my own (Python)
training materials and the kids are having a great time mixing all sorts of
different types of music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's hoping you stay safe and remain healthy during this challenging time.
Since most of us are in lock-down, don't hesitate to get in touch if you fancy
a chat..! Social distancing rules don't mean you have to be anti-social.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/2020-changes/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sponsorship</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The majority of the code I write is given away for free for the benefit of
others. This is unsustainable so I often think about how such voluntary work
could be supported. One solution is related to my
&lt;a href="http://codegrades.com/"&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; idea. But this is a slow
burn project that has involved, and continues to demand, a huge amount of
time, effort and money before I'll have anything to show for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another solution is simply to ask folks for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been a musician, I'm used to this feeling. I used to busk with some
buddies as a way of trying to make ends meet. However, as my grandmother once
pointed out, it's a form of begging. In one sense, this is a tragedy: begging
is a last resort because nothing else you do is of value. You're forced to
rely on the compassion and generosity of others. Yet in another sense it's like
the activity of a mendicant asking for alms for their service or contributions
to society. In any case, no matter how you "spin" it, it's a precarious
situation to find oneself in ~ be you a musician or free software developer
(and I'm both!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are some kind hearted individuals and (even rarer) companies or
organisations who are happy to help support such work, most think, "meh, I'll
just use the software" (without so much as a thank you). Even worse (and I have
personal experience of this) some folks will pass off such voluntary work as
their own and reap the rewards for such a lie. This is why I actually earn
money-to-live by writing software as a freelance developer (it gives me the
flexibility I need to work on my own coding projects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it was with some interest that I noticed GitHub had created what
they describe as account sponsorship. "Sponsorship" is an interesting word
to use because it makes the begging / mendicant aspect of the situation more
palatable. It also cheerfully suggests that the free/open-source software world
is full of generous hearted folks or organisations just waiting to give back to
the selfless volunteers who make all this code available via their GitHub
account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, a fiction. It's also normalising begging as a solution
to funding free software volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I'm open minded and willing to give anything a go, especially if it
means it'll cover my costs. So I've signed up and now &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can give me
money for my efforts. As of the time of writing, and after tweeting about this
to my 3,000+ followers, this is what my account looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/github_sponsors.png" style="border: 1px solid #ccc;"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can't help but think that in six months time, it'll still look the same.
But at least I can say I gave it a go. Despite my misgivings, I feel it
important to give ideas a chance to flower and I'm trying very hard (yet
failing) to view this as a mendicant rather than beggar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you've ever found my work or activities useful, beneficial or
supportive, please consider helping me sustain my efforts. You can do so by
visiting my "&lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/ntoll"&gt;sponsorship&lt;/a&gt;"
page to find out more about what I do and how to give "alms". The summary is
that I focus on education: I develop software that helps folks learn the
skills and knowledge they need to imagine, develop and program the stuff they
want. If you believe this is important work, sponsor me with a monthly
contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, and many thanks to the small number of you who have already
done this, you can send me a virtual hug-as-a-book by buying me
something from my &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/hz/wishlist/ls/3B63FUSVDIJJS"&gt;Amazon wish list&lt;/a&gt;
(none of the items are particularly expensive). Small gestures, such as gifting
books or music with a supportive message, can actually mean a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll report back in a few months to let you know how I get on. I have to
admit, I don't hold out much hope. Best knuckle down on CodeGrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well... what are you waiting for..? Go on... get your wallets out. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Honestly, I quite understand if you don't. I have the same misgivings
you're probably having after reading the sentence above. Such a feeling is the
nub of what I want to demonstrate in this blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 08:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CircuitPython 2020</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/blinka-computer.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My buddy &lt;a href="http://tannewt.org/"&gt;Scott&lt;/a&gt;, one of the wonderful
people at &lt;a href="https://adafruit.com/"&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, recently asked folks
in the wider CircuitPython community to
&lt;a href="https://blog.adafruit.com/2020/01/01/what-do-you-want-from-circuitpython-in-2020-circuitpython2020-circuitpython/"&gt;share their thoughts&lt;/a&gt;
about what they'd like to see for the project and community during 2020. This
is my contribution to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three aspects to my hopes for CircuitPython in 2020:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Things I hope will continue,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Developments I hope to happen,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;"Moon on a stick" wishes for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to start by reaffirming my belief that Adafruit, and those
involved with CircuitPython in particular, do inspiring stuff when it
comes to fostering an open, welcoming, supportive and collaborative tech
community. This is an extraordinary achievement. My own experience in the
wider Python community is that it takes a huge amount of effort, patience,
compassion and thoughtfulness to grow and sustain such a
"&lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2008/06/scenius-or-comm/"&gt;scenius&lt;/a&gt;"
(and, sadly, this can be destroyed very quickly by only a few bad actors). So
my wish for continuation in 2020 is that everyone involved in the
CircuitPython community grasp opportunities to enlarge positive aspects of
ourselves such as mutual appreciation, the sharing of tools and techniques,
latent network effects, and a spirit of tolerance, compassion and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I hope happens this year is a broadening of CircuitPython's horizons.
My passion for tech can be summed up by a quote from David Allen, the producer
on the original BBC micro from the 1980s -- my first computer. He
&lt;a href="https://www.nesta.org.uk/report/the-legacy-of-bbc-micro/"&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt;
that, "[t]he aim was to democratise computing. We didn't want people to be
controlled by it, but to control it." CircuitPython feels to me like it sits
very much in the hobbyist / enthusiast "segment" of users who already know
something of programming. I'd love CircuitPython to make inroads into
beginner related education. This probably involves a focus on
learning what teachers would like from a coding platform, honest appraisals of
how beginner coders (no matter their age or background) find their first steps
with CircuitPython and Adafruit boards, as well as making the results of such
findings accessible to all. This final point is important. Learning to code
shouldn't just be an option for English speaking, able bodied folk from a
cultural background that means examples and cultural assumptions are
easily understood. I hope you agree that education should be an inclusive
endeavour, and this takes concerted and conscientious effort. I hope the
CircuitPython community find the time and space to invest in the (never
finished) work such a focus entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/moon_stick.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My "moon on a stick" is a CircuitPython based mobile phone with a touch
screen and a simple
(&lt;a href="https://pypercard.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;PyperCard&lt;/a&gt; like?)
Python UI that's easily hackable. Think
of it as the open, easy-to-assemble, relatively cheap and "hack friendly"
version of something like the
&lt;a href="https://www.thelightphone.com/"&gt;Light Phone&lt;/a&gt; with all the
schematics and design assets (e.g. files for 3d printing the case) available
under open source licenses so folks can go mod-crazy. Now wouldn't that
be a turn up for the books..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll finish by wishing everyone in the CircuitPython a flourishing and
happy new year. Here's to wonderful things in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's go..!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Classical Playlist of Love</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When my Canadian buddies &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndreaMcInnes21"&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://snarky.ca/"&gt;Brett&lt;/a&gt; visited the UK in
the summer, we visited the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Albert_Hall"&gt;Royal Albert Hall&lt;/a&gt; to hear a classical music
concert that was part of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Proms"&gt;the Proms&lt;/a&gt; -- the world's largest
classical music festival. I think they must have enjoyed themselves because
they recently got in touch asking me to suggest a playlist of
classical music. What follows is my response along with videos of performances
of the pieces I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than put together a playlist of apparently random
choices, I decided it would be interesting to assemble a set of pieces
related to a particular feeling. In this case, I chose love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because love is complicated, tragic, happy, joyful, funny, raunchy and many
more aspects too numerous to list here. The western classical
tradition has around 900 years of musical reactions, settings and descriptions
of love -- plenty of opportunity to reveal a breadth and depth of music. So,
I'm going to associate each piece with some aspect of love, provide
a short commentary and embedded a video of a performance of
the selected piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to my sharing videos of performances. Ideally,
you'd listen to these pieces in person at a concert. Only in such a live
situation can you really experience the fleeting moment of the performance,
executed by highly trained musicians and feel that sense of being in a
particular unique moment, together with all the others in attendance. The
videos are a less than perfect replacement, yet still have the potential to
move you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For convenience I've put them into a
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yjz2TvC2TT4&amp;amp;list=PLzCYc445IVNTPApt_F6PkGCRRPNfG-JmA"&gt;playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is classical music, it may sound strange to modern ears not
familiar with styles and mannerisms from hundreds of years ago or it uses sung
or instrumental techniques that sound odd because they're not used much in
contemporary popular music. If classical music isn't your thing, consider
this an invitation to explore a new musical world -- a world that rewards
repeated engagement, an open mind and long term listening. This is music that
makes demands of the listener, but will reveal depths one cannot even imagine
until you experience them for yourself. For those of you who are already
immersed in classical music you'll find none of my choices particularly
challenging. In fact, you may even roll your eyes and think, "oh, not that old
chestnut again". Please remember, this is an introductory playlist, but know
that I'm open to suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sincerely hope you are moved by the pieces I've selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tender Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gustav Mahler - Adagietto from Symphony No. 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical representation of Mahler's love for his wife Alma. Their
friend Wilem Engelberg recollects, "In place of a letter, he sent her this in
manuscript form, not adding a further word. She understood and wrote to him
telling him to come!!! They both told me this."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alma later revealed Gustav left her the following poem with the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In which way I love you, my sunbeam,&lt;br&gt;
I cannot tell you with words.&lt;br&gt;
Only my longing, my love and my bliss&lt;br&gt;
can I with anguish declare.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/P8LZ43LA2nY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tragic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky - Fantasy Overture to Romeo and Juliet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tchaikovsky was well acquainted with tragic love: he was a gay man in 19th
century Russia (a time and place full of prejudice towards someone such as
himself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such tragedy and pain as well as an overflowing sense of passion are
skilfully captured in this piece or "musical impressions" loosely assembled to
follow the story of Romeo and Juliet. Listen out for the overwhelming "love
theme" which has become a musical cliché for inevitably doomed lovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3x69wuewkJM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Romantic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergei Rachmaninoff - Piano Concerto No.2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachmaninoff, another Russian, is widely considered one of the greatest
pianists of all time, as well as one of the greatest composers for the
piano. This piano concerto is full of yearning melodies, gushing outpourings of
emotion, tender moments and joyful exuberance. Just like falling in love!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was effectively used in the David Lean romance from 1945, "Brief
Encounters", thus cementing it as a "romantic" classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rEGOihjqO9w" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Denied&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puccini - O Mio Babbino Caro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aria, from Puccini's opera "Gianni Schicchi", comes at the moment where
the daughter of Gianni tells him that she's fallen in love, wants to get
married, and if he won't let her go to her true love, she'll throw herself off
the Ponte Vecchio bridge in Florence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you imagine this sounds like a musical tantrum in the making, get ready
with the hankies and prepare for something absolutely not tantrum like at
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soprano singer in the video, Montserrat Caballé, is simply stunning. Her
charisma, presence, musicianship and vocal control is awe inspiring. Yes, she's
the one who sang with Freddie Mercury on his single "Barcelona".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RxZSP1Dc78Q" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Platonic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms - Intermezzo Op. 118 No. 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms wrote this beautiful piece for his friend Clara Schumann (Clara is
another musician considered one of the greatest pianists of all time and a
wonderful composer in her own right). I describe it as "Platonic" because Clara
was married to Brahms's mentor and friend Robert Schumann, who eventually
succumbed to mental health issues. Brahms and Clara were undoubtedly close and
shared a deep love for each other, but it was only ever a love between dear
friends. Imagine how you'd feel if you had been gifted such a piece of
music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78OO5v0lNtI" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fantastical Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berlioz - Symphonie Fantastique&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is sex, drugs and classical music with an added dose of musical story
telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is of the concert Andrea, Brett and I attended. I won't
say any more, since the performers do a fantastic job of explaining what's
going on. It's quite a spectacle (and watch out for the mirror balls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/t1sEI0JoZ8M" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Transformed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg - Verklärte Nacht&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg wrote this piece to closely follow the structure of the poem upon
which it is based, to the extent that the different sections in the musical
score map directly to lines in the poem. The poem, by Richard Dehmel, whose
title is translated as "Transfigured Night", tells of two lovers walking in the
woods. The woman opens up about a terrible burden she carries. Her lover is
full of compassion, love and support which transforms her burden into a shared
aspect of their life together. I'm being necessarily vague here so I don't
spoil the poem for you... just read it as
&lt;a href="https://allpoetry.com/Transfigured-Night-(Verklrte-Nacht)"&gt;translated here&lt;/a&gt;
and then listen to the piece. My favourite lines (and part of the piece)
are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just see how brightly the universe is gleaming!&lt;br&gt;
There’s a glow around everything;&lt;br&gt;
You are floating with me on a cold ocean,&lt;br&gt;
But a special warmth flickers&lt;br&gt;
From you into me, from me into you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the music sounds as if it's gleaming..! One other thing you
may hear, the violin (a high instrument) is prominent in the sections
representing the woman speaking, whereas the cello (a low instrument) is
prominent in the sections representing the man speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yzSaOWPBFqA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love's Dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fauré - Après un rêve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply a song about a dream of the poet's beloved. The words of the
poem (and their English translation) can be found &lt;a href="https://www.oxfordlieder.co.uk/song/15"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FlT1QhK4Wto" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Erotic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner - Prelude and Liebestod from 'Tristan Und Isolde'&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I start with this one..? This is erotic music. I don't mean humping
or "having a shag". Rather, it's a musical version of a passionate embrace
(between the protagonists, Tristan and Isolde).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In music theory we use the term "climax" to describe the point at which all
the tension in the music is released. There's a reason we call it a climax.
This piece has a famously ecstatic climax that takes a while to build, after
lots of tender pauses, gradually intensifying musical moments, soaring strings
and throbbing horns (no pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm sure you'll hear what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/W8EQcMurhAI" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Orgasmic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orff - Dulcissime (from Carmina Burana)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just watch and listen. No further explanation needed.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/BFq8vH7tPxs" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mendelssohn - Wedding March from A Midsummer Night's Dream&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You'll hear this in pretty much every church wedding you ever attend - and
quite rightly, it's very uplifting, celebratory and joyful music. Just what you
need for such an occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rIM5cWB2wmM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Moment of Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaughan Williams - Silent Noon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dante Gabriel Rossetti's poem "Silent Noon" recollects an intimate shared
moment of love that was both fleeting and intense. Vaughan Williams music
beautifully complements the nostalgic, thoughtful and timeless nature of the
moment in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Your hands lie open in the long fresh grass,--&lt;br&gt;
The finger-points look through like rosy blooms:&lt;br&gt;
Your eyes smile peace. The pasture gleams and glooms&lt;br&gt;
'Neath billowing skies that scatter and amass.&lt;br&gt;
All round our nest, far as the eye can pass,&lt;br&gt;
Are golden kingcup-fields with silver edge&lt;br&gt;
Where the cow-parsley skirts the hawthorn-hedge.&lt;br&gt;
'Tis visible silence, still as the hour-glass.&lt;br&gt;
Deep in the sun-searched growths the dragon-fly&lt;br&gt;
Hangs like a blue thread loosened from the sky:--&lt;br&gt;
So this wing'd hour is dropt to us from above.&lt;br&gt;
Oh! clasp we to our hearts, for deathless dower,&lt;br&gt;
This close-companioned inarticulate hour&lt;br&gt;
When twofold silence was the song of love.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rvl4Qo-z_KM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love's Yearning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck - Che farò senza Euridice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of Orfeo and Euridice is popular among composers. The hero,
Orpheus, is a master musician who can tame nature with his music. His beloved
Euridice dies and is taken to the Greek underworld. Missing his lover,
Orpheus travels into the underworld and charms Hades, the god of the
dead, with his music. As a result, Hades promises that Euridice can live and
return to the world of the living so long as Orpheus doesn't look back to see
if she follows him on the way home. Inevitably, Orpheus looks back and Euridice
is, once again, struck dead. It's at this point in the opera that we hear the
following aria for counter-tenor (the highest natural voice for a man to
sing). The title means, "What shall I do without Euridice?".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What will I do without Euridice&lt;br&gt;
Where will I go without my wonderful one.&lt;br&gt;
Euridice, oh God, answer&lt;br&gt;
I am entirely your loyal one.&lt;br&gt;
Euridice! Ah, it doesn´t give me&lt;br&gt;
any help, any hope&lt;br&gt;
neither this world, neither heaven.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll leave you to work out what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0mEKeaXST2s" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love's Pain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strozzi - Che si può fare&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Strozzi was a remarkable woman. Born in Venice in 1619, she was one
of the most well known musicians of her age. It is claimed she had more music
in print than any other composer of the era. This success was of her own doing
since she had no support from the usual sources of the church or nobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that if Bridget Jones were from Baroque era Venice, she'd be
listening to this instead of Céline Dion's "All By Myself".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What can I do?&lt;br&gt;
The stars have no pity and work against me;&lt;br&gt;
If heaven will give me no gesture&lt;br&gt;
Of peace for my pain,&lt;br&gt;
What can I do?&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
What can I say?&lt;br&gt;
The heavens are raining disasters on me;&lt;br&gt;
If Love will not grant me a moment of breath,&lt;br&gt;
to relieve all my suffering,&lt;br&gt;
What can I say?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1F458aC_FUM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smetana - Vltava (The Moldau) from Má vlast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the musical antidote to nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Czech composer Smetana uses music to represent the river Moldau as it
runs through his country in a celebration of the landscape, activity, folk
music, dance and industry of the people of the Czech republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works well as a musical metaphor, starting with the trickle of notes
from the opening flutes and building up to a flowing melody surrounded by
melodic eddys and currents in the strings. The river music keeps returning
throughout the piece as different musical interludes interject to describe
some aspect of where the river flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/l6kqu2mk-Kw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Nature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Pastoral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is an old friend of mine. Forget the Disney version from the
animated film "Fantasia" -- this is Beethoven musically representing a visit to
the country and the emotional impact that has on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the latter part of the work he paints a picture of a country dance
interrupted by a storm which he concludes with a hymn to nature. Beethoven
wasn't conventionally religious, but this is a certainly a spiritual reaction
to nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iQGm0H9l9I4" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Humanity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Choral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven's 9th is full of different emotions and a real journey of the soul
in musical form. But the part I want to particularly highlight is the finale,
the "Ode to Joy".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven was famously misanthropic and that's how the finale starts with
the rather annoyed sounding cellos and double basses. But once the "joy" theme
is found the instruments try their hardest to make something of it. Yet
Beethoven's genius is to interrupt the finale at this point, and start again
with human voices. Schiller's words are a celebration of brotherhood,
togetherness and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it really does have the line, "here's a giant kiss for all" sung by the
massed choir. Thank you Ludwig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/-suf9BL9xRA?start=2663" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Parental Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shostakovich - Piano Concerto No.2 (Second Movement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dimitri Shostakovich wrote this concerto for his son Maxim. Maxim used it as
an audition piece for music conservatoire when he was a teenager. This second
movement is both sad yet hopeful, as a parent lets go and reflects on the child
leaving and growing into adulthood. The music full of love and sadness. Perhaps
if the orchestra is Dimitri, then Maxim is the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TPqMvoR2Buo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Ending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strauss - "Im Abendrot" from Four Last Songs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical and poetic meditation on two lovers coming to the end of
their long life together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Through sorrow and joy&lt;br&gt;
we have gone hand in hand;&lt;br&gt;
we are both at rest from our wanderings&lt;br&gt;
now above the quiet land.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Around us, the valleys bow,&lt;br&gt;
the air already darkens.&lt;br&gt;
Only two larks soar&lt;br&gt;
musingly into the haze.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Come close, and let them flutter,&lt;br&gt;
soon it will be time to sleep -&lt;br&gt;
so that we don't get lost&lt;br&gt;
in this solitude.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
O vast, tranquil peace,&lt;br&gt;
so deep in the afterglow!&lt;br&gt;
How weary we are of wandering--&lt;br&gt;
Is this perhaps death?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Giaf3qSqDHM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar - Cello Concerto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife, Mary, once played this in a concerto competition (and won).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar wrote the piece soon after his wife, Alice, passed away. The cello is,
of course, Alice and the music Elgar creates reflects all the different
feelings he has now that she is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This very old performance, by Jacqueline du Pré on cello and Daniel
Barenboim conducting, is poignant. They were married but Jackie's playing
succumbed to multiple sclerosis soon after this recording was made. The MS
eventually killed her around a decade or so later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OPhkZW_jwc0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Testing CircuitPython Modules</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://micropython.org/"&gt;MicroPython&lt;/a&gt;, a project by my
buddy &lt;a href="http://dpgeorge.net/"&gt;Damien George&lt;/a&gt;, is a
complete reimplementation of the Python programming language for
microcontrollers and embedded systems. Put simply, it's Python for extremely
small computers (and I once
&lt;a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920056515.do"&gt;wrote a book about it&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;a href="https://circuitpython.org/"&gt;CircuitPython&lt;/a&gt;, a friendly fork of
MicroPython, is sponsored by the fantastic folks
at &lt;a href="https://adafruit.com/"&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, a company who make playful and
easy-to-use "hackable" technology while promoting a welcoming, friendly and
diverse community of makers. They are led by legendary founder and electrical
engineer extraordinaire, &lt;a href="http://www.ladyada.net/"&gt;Limor "ladyada" Fried&lt;/a&gt;.
CircuitPython is MicroPython for Adafruit's line of boards and with a
consistent API for accessing the numerous bits of cool hardware you can use
with such devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was privileged to recently complete a block of work for Adafruit: I've
written a CircuitPython module called &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; that makes it
easy for
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth"&gt;Bluetooth&lt;/a&gt; enabled
Adafruit boards to communicate with each other. The API is
a simplified version of the work myself and a number of other volunteers did on
the
&lt;a href="https://microbit-micropython.readthedocs.io/en/v1.0.1/radio.html"&gt;equivalent functionality&lt;/a&gt;
for the BBC micro:bit (&lt;a href="https://microbit-micropython.readthedocs.io/en/v1.0.1/tutorials/radio.html"&gt;here's a tutorial I wrote for the micro:bit
radio&lt;/a&gt;, to make electronic "fireflies" blink at each other over
Bluetooth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new Adafruit module, sending a message is as simple as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()
r.send("Hello")
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving requires a loop (to allow the device to keep checking for
messages), but is equally as simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()

while True:
    message = r.receive()
    if message:
        # Do something useful with the message.
        print(message)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best model for thinking about this module is that of kids'
walkie-talkies. Each
radio is tuned to a certain channel upon which it broadcasts and receives.
If you send a message, anyone else listening in on that channel and within
range will receive it. You'll also receive messages broadcast on that
channel from others within range. 
This is an ideal network topology because it's both familiar
yet capable since other, more specialised, network topologies can be built on
top of it. There is potential for users to grow from a simple "walkie-talkie"
model of networking to something more sophisticated and of their own
devising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/walkie-talkie.jpg" alt="Kids on walkie-talkies"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The channels in the module are numbered between 0-255 and can be set when
creating a &lt;code&gt;Radio&lt;/code&gt; object (the default channel number is 42 in
honour of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Adams"&gt;Douglas Adams&lt;/a&gt;, who
saw so much humane potential in new technology yet mischievously warned of the
polluting effect of technology for technology's sake via the inept
work of the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technology_in_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Sirius_Cybernetics_Corporation"&gt;Sirius Cybernetics Corporation&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio(channel=123)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can change channel at any time via the &lt;code&gt;Radio&lt;/code&gt;
object's &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; method (continuing the example above):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;r.configure(channel=7)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in addition to sending strings of characters it's also possible to
send and receive arbitrary bytes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()
r.send_bytes(b"Hello")
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving bytes gives you the full context of the message expressed as a
Python tuple consisting of three values: the raw bytes, the RSSI reading (i.e.
strength of the signal, from 0 [max] to -255 [min]), and a timestamp
representing the number (and fraction of) seconds since the device powered up,
as demonstrated in the following REPL based example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from adafruit_radio import Radio
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r = Radio()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r.receive_full()
(b'Hello', -40, 3245.155408037)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's it! You can find the code in &lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/Adafruit_CircuitPython_Radio"&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.
Special mention and thanks must be made to Adafruit's
&lt;a href="http://tannewt.org/"&gt;Scott Shawcroft&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://danhalbert.org/"&gt;Dan Halbert&lt;/a&gt; who
wrote the Bluetooth API I used. Because of their
work I was able to create my module with less than a hundred lines of Python
(at time of writing). Thanks chaps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this context, I'm going to explain why and how I created a
comprehensive test suite for the &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd summarise my approach to testing as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Testing is fundamental for creating and maintaining well designed
    software. My experience is that it tends to produce code that is both
    simple and easy to understand because nobody wants to write complicated
    tests to exercise equally complicated code. The process of exercising code
    through tests forces a developer to think carefully about how their code
    is written while having the added benefit of demonstrating it works as
    expected. Simplicity and ease of understanding are
    desirable properties because such code is easier to read, correct and
    maintain and also indicates the author's own clarity of thought (a good
    sign). I also believe it helpful and friendly to write code that's easy
    for others to read and understand (I often imagine my code will be read by
    an intelligent beginner coder, because it forces me to explain and address
    my own assumptions about my code).&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;I personally don't practice strict test-driven development, where one
    writes tests before writing the implementation. I prefer to explore,
    improvise, extemporise and play at first. I often try various different
    approaches to the task in hand and regularly re-draft. I'll often seek
    advice and comments from collaborators, colleagues and potential users of
    my code as soon as possible. Therefore, my highest priority when I start a
    new project is making my code simple enough so that it is very easy to
    change. Often this step in the coding process is called a "spike".&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Only when a project settles on a certain architecture, implementation
    or foundation of code do I add tests. I think of this as a sort of
    "hardening" process. When I'm happy with an approach I'll often re-draft
    the exploratory code I've already written, alongside writing tests to
    exercise that specific piece of code. I aim for, and often achieve, 100%
    test coverage (every line of my code is exercised in some way by a test).
    This process allows me to get a feel for how my API works from the point of
    view of a fellow coder encountering it for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;The hardening has another effect: I've baked in an expectation for how
    the code should behave via the tests. I also make sure my tests are
    commented in such a way that a meaningful intention behind the test is
    revealed. They're also a useful source of information for future users
    and/or maintainers of my code. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, they
    help manage change.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;No useful software is ever finished simply because the universe changes
    (and so must software). Despite our best efforts, software is often
    complicated and it's easy to forget something or not realise how a change
    in one part of the
    code may break another apparently unrelated part. Having a suite of
    tests to check all the aspects of a codebase helps future maintainers make
    changes with confidence.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Being pragmatic, I sometimes don't follow the playful explorations
    outlined above. If I'm dealing with a well defined or mature protocol
    (for example), I'll quickly settle on an approach, usually based upon
    research into how other folks have solved the same problem, and proceed by
    writing tests based upon the protocol in order to measure the completeness,
    accuracy and progress of my resulting implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem for developers writing for CircuitPython is that such code is
usually to be run on microcontrollers with certain hardware capabilities. Yet
such code is invariably written on conventional computers running operating
systems such as Windows, OSX or Linux. The only way to know your code works is
to try it on the target device. This is, to say the least, laborious compared
to having the benefits of running an extensive test suite in a matter of
seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having written my small and simple &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; module I
found myself missing the benefits of a comprehensive test suite. After asking
around, I found most Python modules for CircuitPython don't have a test suite
and there hadn't been much (if any) exploration for how to address this. Scott
suggested I add what I thought best in terms of testing to my module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted my solution to meet the following requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It works with existing Python testing tools so non-specialist Python
    developers feel at home and can bring their existing skills to
    CircuitPython with little effort.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;It runs on a conventional computer, because that's where developers do
    the majority of their work. (I'm constantly running and re-running my
    test-suite as I make changes to code.)&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;It handles the problem of using CircuitPython-only modules in a
    test-suite run on a conventional computer with standard Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to focus on using an existing, well known and mature Python
testing tool called &lt;a href="http://pytest.org/en/latest/"&gt;PyTest&lt;/a&gt; (the
creation of another friend of mine, the extraordinarily prolific and very
thoughtful &lt;a href="https://holgerkrekel.net/"&gt;Holger Krekel&lt;/a&gt;). The
advantage of using PyTest is that it has a large number of plug-ins that are
both useful and familiar to a large number of Python programmers. One such
plug-in I use a lot is the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest-cov"&gt;Pytest coverage tool&lt;/a&gt;,
which makes it easy to spot areas of a code base that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; 
exercised by a test suite. PyTest also has a well defined mechanisms to extend
it to work in specialist testing situations (such as our own CircuitPython
based context).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I was concerned, using PyTest met the first two of my self-imposed
requirements. I was left with the final problem of dealing with CircuitPython
only modules that wouldn't work on a conventional computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I need to introduce the concept of "mocking" in a test suite
(as in "mocked up" rather than poking fun). Mocking is a way to replace parts
of your system under test with "mocked up" objects and then make assertions
about how such objects have been used. Thanks to another friend of mine (the
huge hearted, funny and rather hairy
&lt;a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/"&gt;Michael Foord&lt;/a&gt;), mocking is built
right into Python's standard library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My idea was simple: automatically mock away those parts of CircuitPython
that don't work on a conventional computer. Such objects give the developer a
way to check and ensure the module under test is working as expected with
CircuitPython. It's even possible to specify how such mock objects should
behave under certain conditions (such as when they may be the source of some
sort of data which the module under test will use). However, this aspect of
mocking should be used with great care -- more on which later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a developer creates a &lt;code&gt;conftest.py&lt;/code&gt; file in their test suite
PyTest will import it before running any of the test code and use various
functions found therein to configure the test suite. For example, if PyTest
finds a function called &lt;code&gt;pytest_runtest_setup&lt;/code&gt; in the
&lt;code&gt;conftest.py&lt;/code&gt; file, then this function will always be called
immediately prior to any test function. Just what we need!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/Adafruit_CircuitPython_Radio/blob/master/tests/conftest.py"&gt;&lt;code&gt;conftest.py file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
is very short and simply mocks away named aspects of CircuitPython which cannot
be run on a conventional computer immediately before any test is run, via the
aforementioned &lt;code&gt;pytest_runtest_setup&lt;/code&gt; convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means I can write conventional looking PyTest based unit tests like the
following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def test_radio_receive_full_no_messages(radio):
    """
    If no messages are detected by receive_full then it returns None.
    """
    radio.ble.start_scan.return_value = []
    assert radio.receive_full() is None
    radio.ble.start_scan.assert_called_once_with(
        adafruit_radio.AdafruitRadio, minimum_rssi=-255, timeout=1
    )
    radio.ble.stop_scan.assert_called_once_with()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things you should know: &lt;code&gt;radio.ble&lt;/code&gt; is a mocked away part of
CircuitPython. As a result, on the first line of my test function, I've been
able to tell the mock that the result of calling the &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt;
method is an empty list. Then I can assert that the method I want to test (the
&lt;code&gt;radio.receive_full&lt;/code&gt; method returns &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt; in this
context. Furthermore, I'm able to check in the final two statements of the
function that the &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt; method was called with the expected
arguments, and that an additional &lt;code&gt;stop_scan&lt;/code&gt; method was called
too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I run the test suite, I see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pytest --cov-report term-missing --cov=adafruit_radio tests/
============================= test session starts ==============================
platform linux -- Python 3.7.5, pytest-5.3.0, py-1.8.0, pluggy-0.13.0
rootdir: /home/ntoll/src/adafruit_radio
plugins: cov-2.8.1
collected 12 items                                                             

tests/test_adafruit_radio.py ............                                [100%]

----------- coverage: platform linux, python 3.7.5-final-0 -----------
Name                Stmts   Miss  Cover   Missing
-------------------------------------------------
adafruit_radio.py      61      0   100%


============================== 12 passed in 0.09s ==============================
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note all the feedback about code coverage..! Neat, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mock object, by its very nature, is a mock-up of something else... it's
not the real thing..! So what happens when the real thing (that has been
mocked-up in the test suite) changes? For instance let's imagine that the
result of a call to &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt; is no longer an empty list, but
something else. The tests will still pass because the mocked-up object doesn't
reflect the real object, yet when the module under test is used on a real
device with the changed version of CircuitPython then it won't work
correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously not a good situation and why I mention mocks should be
used with great care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious solution is for the developer in charge of the test
suite to be careful and check API updates in the release notes of the modules
being mocked away. However, this becomes a burden if the test suite mocks away
a huge number of modules. It's also open to human error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to mitigate this problem, but because it's early days
I've not been able to investigate these potential solutions properly. The best
I can do at this point in time is shrug my shoulders, say things are under
construction and invite folks to dive in and help. Our community would
certainly be enriched by such collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I'm quite pleased with this first step in equipping
CircuitPython modules with comprehensive test suites. Yet there's still plenty
to do -- most notably, ways to address the problems mentioned with mocking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, comments, constructive criticism and ideas expressed in a
friendly, collaborative and supportive manner are most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over to you... :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 13:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PyWeek Retrospective</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/pyweek/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pyweek.org/"&gt;PyWeek&lt;/a&gt; is a simple idea: write a game,
using the Python programming language, from scratch, on a given theme, within a
week. Take part as either an individual or a member of a team entry. At the end
of the week play, feedback and score each others' entries. After which, an
individual and team are crowned respective champions for their category of
entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have taken part in three different iterations of PyWeek. Each one has
been extraordinarily good fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first PyWeek was as an individual entry. The theme was "two worlds", so
I imagined a paper based battle between the worlds of blue biros and red biros
(it felt like a good idea at the time...). I wanted to push the limits of my
&lt;a href="https://codewith.mu/"&gt;Mu code editor&lt;/a&gt; for beginner programmers and
&lt;a href="https://pygame-zero.readthedocs.io/en/stable/"&gt;PyGameZero&lt;/a&gt; (a
gaming framework for beginner programmers integrated into Mu, developed by my
buddy [and organiser of PyWeek] &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/pyweek/" http:&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Dan Pope).
The end result was a side-scrolling chase game called
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/paperchase"&gt;PaperChase&lt;/a&gt;. This video shows
me testing the game with my (then) thirteen year old son... you'll quickly
get the idea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/z_wGpJubVwI" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next entry was as part of a team. I'd been helping author and
journalist
&lt;a href="https://andrewsmithauthor.com/"&gt;Andrew Smith&lt;/a&gt; to
&lt;a href="https://www.1843magazine.com/features/code-to-joy"&gt;take his
first steps into coding&lt;/a&gt;. Making a game seemed like a fun vehicle for
further learning. The theme was "flow" and so we devised a simple
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frogger"&gt;Frogger&lt;/a&gt; clone
where you avoided traffic flow whilst being chased by lumbering zombies.
I did the code and Andrew did the sound and music. The end result
(&lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/traffic_flowmageddon"&gt;Trafficflowmageddon&lt;/a&gt;)
is, I feel, quite cute... as zombie relate games go...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/08mvNmhOVG4" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we come to the most recent PyWeek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, Andrew and I teamed up. We chatted before hand about the sort
of game we might want to make. Since we both have a love of the written word we
decided to go with a text-based (rather than graphical) game -- the theory
being it would play to our "strengths" with the written word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, this was (by far and away) my favourite PyWeek so far. Here's
why...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphical games show, text based games describe. Graphical games have an
added cost of "asset" development (the graphical stuff shown on the screen)
whereas text based games only need typed characters. Graphical games tend to
focus on hand/eye skill to progress gameplay, whereas textual games necessarily
put narrative, meaning and intent at the centre of their process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, these are broad generalisations. But what I want to get to is
the idea of a player engaging with a game imaginatively, emotionally and
intellectually via the medium of words. If done properly, the depth of
engagement is potentially greater. I'm not saying one can't be engaged in such
a way with graphical games, rather that textual games are perhaps a medium
which more easily lend themselves to this end. It's similar to the difference
between a book and a film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear, I'm not saying one is better than the other, these are
very different ways to tell a story or play a game, but I can't help but feel a
"reader" has to do more (and the reward is therefore greater) than a
"viewer".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that text-based games are, in a sense, more egalitarian and
accessible. Again, to continue the book/film similarity, while no mean feat,
writing a book is within the realms of a single author armed with just a pen
and paper, whereas making a film requires a cast of collaborators and
specialists, equipment, facilities, locations and deep pockets. For similar
reasons, the generation and manipulation of textual game content is far simpler
and affordable than for graphical games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what sort of games are textual?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy! &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colossal_Cave_Adventure"&gt;Adventure games&lt;/a&gt;!
If you're interested in finding out more about this style of text-based game
you should watch &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o15itQ_EhRo"&gt;GET LAMP&lt;/a&gt;,
a fascinating documentary about the genre. Alternatively, if you want to try
playing an example of such a game, I've embedded one of my favourites below
(just click on it and type some commands). It's based on Douglas Adams'
"Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy" (the game itself was co-authored by
Adams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container" style="border: 1px #ccc solid !important;"&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://iplayif.com/?story=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.douglasadams.com%2Fcreations%2Fhhgg.z3"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's where it gets interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such games don't have to be single player, solo efforts. While this is a fun
way to play, things get far more interesting if you can play with others. This
is not a new idea and I remember playing such games (commonly called
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MUD"&gt;MUD&lt;/a&gt; "Multi-User Dungeons") via
surreptitious use of my school's single 1200 baud modem when the teacher wasn't
looking. These were often Tolkien-esque fantasy themed virtual worlds where
players could wander about exploring, socialising and cooperating to achieve
some in-game outcome (usually a quest of some sort). Later, when I was at
university in the mid-1990s, I began using a type of multi-user textual world
called a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOO"&gt;MOO&lt;/a&gt; (Multi-user Object
Oriented). The wonderful thing about MOO based textual worlds is that they are
programmable by users (I first got to grips with object-orientation via
learning to program MOO). In a sense the MOO is both the game and a platform
for creating textual games collaboratively. It was this sense of a creative
textual virtual world that Andrew and I wanted to recreate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Et voilà, "TextSmith" was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme for this most recent PyWeek was announced as "six". This
fitted our idea for an interactive textual platform. It could contain six
different literary worlds which players collaboratively create, inhabit and
explore together. The six literary worlds we "seeded" in our game were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jane Austen: Recreate Netherfield, go to a ball, affect regency period
    manners and etiquette.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Poetic Passions: Everything is a poem, haiku or rhymes, speak in
    riddles or chat in rhyming couplets.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Hardboiled Detectives: It was about eleven o'clock in the morning, with
    the sun not shining. The client asked, "Well, will you take the case or
    not, bud?"&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;J.R.R.Fantasy: Orcs! Elves! Wizards! Bleak locations! Ancient mystery!
    Quests! (And impenetrable prose.)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;SciFi and Future Worlds: As the service droids efficiently cleaned up
    the remains of the ship's captain, I wondered how long it would take to
    make planet-fall on the alien world of Zaonce.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Parry Hotter: Inspired by everyone's favourite boy wizard, but in such
    a way that Warner Brothers don't go after us for copyright infringement.
    :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming the game was a lot of fun. I managed to build everything mostly
from scratch (except for the web based front-end which uses the
&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/pgjones/quart"&gt;Quart&lt;/a&gt; web microframework).
Sadly, most of it was unfinished, broken and clunkily implemented. The
important thing is that it has &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt;. Below is a screenshot of
an early version of the game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/textsmith.png" alt="The TextSmith client."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, despite the unfinished and rather shonky nature of the end result,
we placed 4th in the team category..! Our highest result..! The
&lt;a href="https://pyweek.org/e/CodeToJoy/ratings/"&gt;feedback&lt;/a&gt;
from fellow PyWeekers was encouraging too and, as a result, I've decided to
continue to develop TextSmith. In the immediate term this will involve plugging
in the almost-finished scripting language I created and knock off some of the
hard edges. More importantly, once this aspect of the "platform" settles down,
I'm looking forward to creating and exploring interactive literary worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, programming, creating and playing with TextSmith has been a very
rich seam of reflection in terms of both technical and playful contexts. I've
had lots of fun thinking about the architecture and implementation of such a
platform while also doing a philosophical deep-dive into what on earth is going
on when "players" connect to, create within and interact with such a
platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows where this may lead..?&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/pyweek/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Make a Joyful Noise</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/joyful-noise/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have a new tuba!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If my mention of a tuba is a surprise (it
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/remembering-john"&gt;shouldn't&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/vaughan-williams-tuba-concerto-programme-notes"&gt;be&lt;/a&gt;),
check out this short student-film, by my buddy
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cluttercup"&gt;Jane&lt;/a&gt;, which explains all:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/YlS9lpybYxo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new tuba isn't a replacement for my current instrument (which I got when
I was sixteen years old). Rather, the instruments complement each other. What's
the difference? If my current tuba is a professional "all rounder", my new
instrument is a sort of "heavy duty" tuba for big orchestral pieces (most of my
current playing is orchestral).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tuba works by amplifying the buzzing sound I make with my lips
into a mouthpiece. I change notes by tensing or relaxing my lips (so the
buzzing sound gets higher or lower) which gives me a limited series of notes
that are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overtone"&gt;overtones&lt;/a&gt; to the
"fundamental" (lowest) note produced by blowing down the length of the tube of
the instrument. I use valves to add tubing to the length of the instrument to
fill in the notes between the overtones so I can play all the notes I need
(i.e. a chromatic scale).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's interesting is how the two instruments are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My original instrument is pitched in Eb (E flat) -- which means the
instrument's fundamental note is the Eb more than an octave below the bass
clef (i.e. very low). My new instrument is pitched in C, so its fundamental
note is &lt;em&gt;even lower&lt;/em&gt;, thus making it an instrument more suited to lower
sounding music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The valves on each instrument are different. I have "piston" valves on my
original instrument. These are spring loaded and when pressed fully down add
additional lengths of tubing to the instrument. The photograph below is of the
inside of the valve so you can see the holes in the piston used to connect 
the different pipes, depending on the valve's position (up or down).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/piston_valve.jpg" alt="The inside of a piston valve."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new instrument uses "rotary" valves. These, as the diagram below shows,
rotate to connect additional lengths of tubing (the passage of air is indicated
by the hatched area). A sort of lever is used to actuate each valve. They're
generally much quieter and more reliable than piston valves (less moving parts
to make clanking sounds) although they can be slower to "engage".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/rotary_valve.jpg" alt="A diagramatic view of a rotary valve."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture below shows the rotary valves on my new tuba. Notice the
levers I press with my fingers to engage the valves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/rotary_valves.jpg" alt="Rotary valves on my new tuba."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both tubas look "tuba shaped" my original tuba points to the right
(as the player is looking at the instrument) whereas my new instrument points
to the left. This simply means I have to hold them differently and there's not
really any change in sound. You can see this difference in the picture
below (the new tuba is on the right):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/two_tubas.jpg" alt="My two tubas."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final major difference is in the number of valves each instrument has.
My original instrument has four "compensating" valves which allow me to get a
full chromatic scale. The new instrument has five "non-compensating" valves:
the first four work like my original instrument and allow me to play a full
chromatic scale, but the fifth valve is used to help tune the very lowest
notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does the new tuba need a special extra "tuning" valve and what on earth
am I talking about when I say "compensating"..? This, dear reader, is where
maths, acoustics, logic and music come together in a spectacular fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new tuba is approximately 524.9 cm in length without any valves engaged.
This produces the note, "C". The first valve adds enough pipe to lower the
pitch by a tone, giving me a "Bb" (B flat) which requires the total length of
tube to be 589.2 cm. Simple arithmetic tells us the total length of the tube
added by using the first valve is therefore 64.3 cm (the "open" length of the
instrument with the added tube should give the correct length to play a tone
lower). The second valve drops the pitch by a semitone to the note "B" which
requires a total length of 556.1 cm. Similarly, the third valve lowers the
pitch by one and a half tones, giving me an "A" which requires the total length
of tube to be 624.2 cm. Again, the simple arithmetic tells me that the length
of tube added by the second valve is 31.2 cm while the length added by the
third valve is 99.3 cm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's where it gets interesting. If I want to play the note "G" I need to
make the length of the instrument 700.6 cm. Given the note "G" is two and a
half tones below "C" I could take the tone provided by the first valve and
one and a half tones of the third valve and use them together. It means the
resulting length of additional pipe is 64.3 cm (the first valve) + 99.3 cm 
(the third valve) giving me a total of 163.6 cm. However, the open length of
the instrument (524.9 cm) with the additional lengths of pipe (163.6) brings
the total length to 688.5 cm, which isn't the 700.6 cm needed to play the
note in tune!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to use my fourth valve, which adds 175.7 cm to the length
of the instrument, thus making it in tune. However, when I need to use my
fourth valve in combination with my other three valves I still encounter the
same sort of "wrong length of pipe" problem I describe above. I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt;
use combinations of valves in order to get all the notes I need in the
chromatic scale. So what can I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the fifth valve on my new tuba comes into play. It has a
special tuning slide I can adjust "in real time" as I play, thus allowing me
to tune the fifth valve as and when I need it. It can also be tuned in such a
way that it "compensates" (remember that word) for the missing lengths of
tubing when I use the other valves together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leaves us with the problem of keeping my current tuba (with only four
valves) in tune. Thankfully, this instrument has "compensating" valves which
work in a rather ingenious manner. The schematic representation of my current
tuba is shown below. The mouthpiece is on the left with the bell on the right
and between are the four valves and associated tubing (not to scale). None of
the valves are engaged so the column of air blown through the instrument goes
directly through without any "detours" (as shown by the pipe filled in with
blue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/compensating_open.png" alt="Compensating system, no valves pressed."&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I press the first and third valves down the expected two extra lengths
of tubing are added, as shown by the two loops of pipe filled with blue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/compensating_13.png" alt="Compensating system, valves 1 and 3 pressed."&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's where it gets really clever. When the fourth valve is pressed down,
not only is the expected additional length of tube added to the length of the
instrument, but this tube is also diverted back through the other three valves
which have additional "compensating" tubes to bring the instrument in tune:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/compensating_134.png" alt="Compensating system, valves 1, 3 and 4 pressed."&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, essentially, a logical &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; expressed as pipe-work. If
the first and fourth valves are pressed then add some new "compensating" length
of pipe. Clever huh..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of this system is the air does two "circuits" around the
instrument (once through the first three valves, and then again if the fourth
valve is pressed so the compensating pipes can come into effect). This makes
the instrument harder to blow (since there are more bends to blow through).
My new instrument feels like there is less to push against when I'm
playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given all the technical tuba-related geekery described above I want
to end on an artistic note...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These instruments are beautiful to look at and playing them is a joy. It's
hard to explain to folks who have never performed music what an amazing
privilege it is. I get to play beautifully designed and precision engineered
instruments as part of an orchestra, band or smaller ensemble. By playing with
my fellow musicians to an audience I'm taking part in a unique social activity.
No matter the mood or difficulty of the piece I'm playing, I love the sense of
non-verbal communication I have with my fellow musicians and collectively with
the audience. I love that I am a part of something creative, challenging,
expressive, collaborative and most definitely greater than the sum of its
parts. That the audience appreciate these efforts is a lovely positive
side effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is always "joyful noise". :-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/joyful-noise/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>