<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ntoll.org</title><link>https://ntoll.org/</link><description>Everything I say is false...</description><atom:link href="https://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:ntoll@ntoll.org"&gt;Nicholas H.Tollervey&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 13:40:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PyCon Ghana 2022</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/ghana2022%20/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;It was an extraordinary privilege to be one of the keynote speakers at this
year's &lt;a href="https://gh.pycon.org/"&gt;PyCon Ghana&lt;/a&gt;. I was also very lucky to have the
support of my employer (&lt;a href="https://anaconda.com/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt;) who covered the
costs associated with the trip for myself and my colleague,
&lt;a href="https://cheuk.dev/"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this was my first trip to Ghana (actually, it was my first trip to
Africa), this was not my first Ghanaian interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't begin to describe how important and nourishing the stimulating
interactions I've had with Ghana based friends Mannie and Michael have been.
Two years ago we were introduced by our mutual friend Conrad Ho, and since then
have met every month, in video calls, to discuss Python in education. The work
done by the Ghanaian Python community to engage in educational activities is
truly inspiring, and you can find out more
&lt;a href="https://www.pythonghana.org/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That both Mannie and Michael are part of the PyCon Ghana organising team, and
this year's focus was on Python in education give a clue as to how I got
invited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/accra.jpg" alt="A view from our accommodation"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The view of Accra from our accommodation.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an eventful flight to Accra, both Cheuk and I went exploring during our
first full day. Adjacent to our accommodation was Oxford Street, containing
lots of shops, banks and other useful things we needed to visit. My immediate
impression was very positive... the Ghanaian folk we met were all friendly
and welcoming. "Good morning", "Hello", "Welcome to Ghana" and other such
greetings were common as we walked through the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also met the PyCon Ghana organisers at the venue. Having been involved with
community organising for well over a decade, I looked on in sympathy and (where
possible) got stuck in trying to help get everything set up. Like most aspects
of the Python community, PyCon Ghana is run by volunteers, and I'd like to
acknowledge their strength of character, friendliness and can-do attitude, led
by their chair, Francis. I saw first hand, that the Ghanaian Python community
is in good hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I was ill on Thursday's tutorial day. My son had shared his cold with
me and it meant I had to stay home instead of attend Cheuk's amazing
&lt;a href="https://humbledata.org/"&gt;humble data&lt;/a&gt; workshop. But the enforced day of rest
meant I was ready for Friday and Saturday at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was honoured to meet &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nii_Quaynor"&gt;Nii Quaynor&lt;/a&gt;
a Ghanaian gentleman who is often described as the father of the African
internet and an inductee to the &lt;a href="https://www.internethalloffame.org/"&gt;Internet Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt;.
Nii eloquently spoke with considerable experience and authority of the
challenges and opportunities for working with governmental and international
agencies. I hope folks were paying attention since the Python community
in Ghana could be a significant contributor and collaborator in the technical
growth of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also many other interesting talks, panels and workshops happening at
the event which made it feel like a typical Python conference found anywhere in
the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first proper contribution to the conference was to run a two day workshop
on MicroPython on the micro:bit for young people. I have to say this was an
absolute joy and, assisted by Anthony and Joanna, we were also joined by
a collection of teachers, tech folk and IoT curious. The vibe was friendly and
the young people brought lots of energy and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a video, shot on the second day while folks were building a project with
their micro:bit, to give a flavour of what went on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TBsl7WvQELM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the &lt;a href="https://microbit.org/"&gt;MicroBit Foundation&lt;/a&gt; for supporting
PyCon Ghana via the donation of 20 devices for participants to use and then
keep. Every device found a safe home, with many asking where they can be
obtained in Ghana..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My keynote, on the subject of Python in Education, went well and as usual, I
especially enjoyed answering the questions at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was especially pleased to channel my "inner teacher" by (half jokingly)
setting the conference some homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pointed out that somewhere will become known as a place of African technical
innovation. Somewhere will be lauded as having the most accessible and
creative coding education programme in Africa. Somewhere will famously
contribute a uniquely African story to our global technical community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked, "why not you..?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My homework task to the audience was to discover and become their own unique,
colourful and extraordinary community. They already have a small but strong,
vibrant and close knit nucleus from which to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope, in ten years time,
to visit Ghana again and have some of today's community say to me, "see what
we did, and look where we're going...", and for me to be amazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/ghana.jpg" alt="Ghanaian friends."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ghanaian friends.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of the conference was its friendliness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the breaks I
spoke to many different people, from all over Africa, and drew energy from
their passion, enthusiasm and openness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also enjoyed the warmth of their
conversation and willingness to share games with me... I especially appreciated
learning how to play &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oware"&gt;Oware&lt;/a&gt; from PyCon
Ghana organiser, Hillary. I enjoyed it so much I managed to buy a board in a
market in Accra and have taught my kids and wife how to play..! It's a big hit
in our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/accra_beach.jpg" alt="The amazing view of a beach from the old presidential residence."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The amazing view of a beach from the old presidential residence.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my final day, the day after the conference, we hung out with the conference
organisers and visited tourist sites in Accra. It was wonderful to see
non-Pythonic aspects of Ghana... its cultural spaces, historic monuments, the
university and glimpse some of its natural beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the course of my stay, I saw the twi word "akwaaba" in many places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I asked what it meant I was told it was a sort of very hospitable form of
"welcome".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Akwaaba" is a pretty good word to describe my experience of PyCon Ghana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long may the Ghanaian Python community flourish and I look forward to 2032. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/ghana2022%20/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 13:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Code Reviews</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/code-reviews/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As I've &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/pastures-new/"&gt;mentioned elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, I've just started a new
role at &lt;a href="https://anaconda.com/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week after joining I was asked to contribute an article to an internal
newsletter called "Consider This!". The format is simple: write something
thoughtful on a subject of interest to folks within the company, and, at the
end, curate a list of questions to prompt further thought and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was invited to explore what I considered important aspects of great code
reviews. Thanks to Anaconda, the article is reproduced below. Additional thanks
to my colleagues Elise and Dan who provided invaluable and stimulating feedback
to significantly improve my first draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="section_break"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask a room of engineers what makes a great code review, and you’ll have as many
different opinions as there are engineers. Yet, in my experience, common themes
and archetypes emerge from the gloriously colourful and diverse descriptions of
a great code review. This article aims to explore what they might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, a code review is exactly what it says: asking another to review
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why might one do this? Often the simple answer is, “because I have to”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code hosting sites, like GitHub, make it easy for code reviews to be part of
the development process through concepts like pull requests (PRs for short).
Simply make a change to the code, bundle your changes into a PR, submit it and
wait for feedback from maintainers or colleagues. Sometimes you have to submit
code for review because of corporate governance, your employer or the open
source project to which you’re contributing may have an existing review process
for all contributions. Or it may simply be habit or herd instinct to follow
so-called “best practices”... folks do code reviews because everyone else does
code reviews and so they’re living up to expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A code review could be an assessment to overcome, where someone in authority
accepts or rejects your changes. It might involve checking your changes to
ensure you’ve followed stylistic and technical conventions for a project, like
a teacher correcting work with a red pen. Furthermore, opinions about the
approach taken, methodology used or even the intention behind the change might
be offered, like a critic describing a restaurant, film or concert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s another, more engaging reason to participate in code reviews: if
done well, your world as a coder is enlarged by the process, be that as a
reviewer or contributor. In so doing, engagement with the project is a process
of growth, and the quality of the codebase is improved to reflect the shared
goals, ideas and aesthetic of those bringing the project into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a code review is used as a means of exercising authority then it’s no better
than pandering to another’s ego. Many projects have stylistic and technical
conventions, and checking such things can be easily automated so contributors
are confident their changes meet such minimum requirements before ever
submitting their code for review. Finally, if a critique of the approach,
methodology or intent is offered as part of a code review, then it’s happening
too late; such things should be discussed before code is submitted for
inclusion in the project, perhaps in early drafts (so called “code spikes”) or
exploratory proofs-of-concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the contributor’s point of view, a code review is an opportunity to share
their work so others understand and see what they are offering. In other words,
a code review is an exercise in education as others encounter and explore new
aspects of the code base. From a reviewer’s point of view, a code review is an
opportunity to explore, internalise and offer constructive feedback of
another’s contribution. Once again, it’s an exercise in education as the
contributor is invited to explore their own work through the fresh eyes and
constructive commentary of the reviewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I deliberately used the word “enlarge” when I said a code review
enlarges the world of those who participate. Enlargement is not synonymous with
“fun”, “positive” or “easy”. The process of enlarging one’s view of the code
might feel uncomfortable (perhaps you’re trying to get your head around a
difficult or unfamiliar concept), negative (you feel frustrated with yet
another bug in a hard-to-fathom part of the project) or difficult (the task at
hand is complex and requires much effort simply to engage effectively).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, enlargement implies growth, understanding and progress, and I’m reminded
of the types of fun mountaineers use to categorise climbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A climb that is &lt;em&gt;type one fun&lt;/em&gt; is fun because it’s fun to do, &lt;em&gt;type two fun&lt;/em&gt;
is not fun at the time but fun to recollect afterwards because of the
achievement gained or lesson learned, and &lt;em&gt;type three fun&lt;/em&gt; is not fun at the
time, nor fun to recollect because you realise you never want to be in that
situation ever again. Given a receptive spirit of learning, a mountaineer’s
view of the world is enlarged through a mixture of both &lt;em&gt;positive and
affirmative&lt;/em&gt;, as well as &lt;em&gt;negative and difficult&lt;/em&gt;, experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how do we foster a spirit of enlargement in code reviews?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe mutual respect is key. Respect involves showing empathy, gratitude
and acknowledgement that, when difficulties arise, folks involved are acting
with the best of intentions. Another key factor is trust, an attribute of a
team that only comes through working together over time, making mistakes
together, and seeing evidence that folks support each other. I’d add that
compassion (an awareness of and sympathy for another’s feelings and situation,
mixed with a proactive desire to engage) is a great way to show support. When
things inevitably become difficult, then compassion for each other is a way to
embody mutual respect and build trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of code reviews, such attributes help our judgement to become
deeper, more refined and aware of the wider context of the project and its
participants. A code review is no longer just an arbitrary measurement of
“quality” (have you followed our code conventions?), but becomes an exercise
in mutual learning and improvement that encompasses both enjoyable and
challenging aspects of participating in a coding project. At the heart of this
process is a strangely humorous paradox, as demonstrated by this old joke:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STUDENT: O Guru, what is the secret of success?&lt;br&gt;
GURU: Good judgement.&lt;br&gt;
STUDENT: How do you get good judgement?&lt;br&gt;
GURU: Experience.&lt;br&gt;
STUDENT: How do you get experience?&lt;br&gt;
GURU: Bad judgement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when folks feel safe to exercise potentially bad judgement (through the
code they offer or the feedback they give), will they be able to gain
experience and learn good judgement. The code review is a place to pay
attention to each other’s contributions to facilitate mutual learning and
growth. This will, ultimately, improve the project as a whole, and help its
participants better engage with the tasks at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But”, I hear you ask, “what things should one do in a code review?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re expecting a “top ten interventions to make in a code review” type
post, you’re in the wrong place. In fact, such naive shopping lists
demonstrate a rather transactional and limited view of the process of a code
review, while completely missing the point I’m trying to make. I hope you
focus on embodying and passing on the sort of attributes that make a project
an enlarging place in which to contribute: mutual respect, trust and
compassion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we could learn by examining what other disciplines do when something
is offered and feedback is given. For example, such a process is at the heart
of musicians rehearsing (no matter the genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This short fragment shows Leonard Bernstein rehearsing an orchestra. Clearly
the triangle players are not playing to the high standard he expects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ebf6_7nHciw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to the relationship between the musicians
involved. How do Bernstein and the percussionists appear to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Folks might think Bernstein is condescending, sarcastic and not particularly
supportive. Others might see him as setting clear (and very high) expectations
through humour. Others might focus on Bernstein’s clear ignorance of triangle
playing and the resulting laughter from the percussionists. That we see the
same thing in different ways is itself an interesting and important outcome of
our diverse and multifaceted backgrounds (and it’s important to acknowledge and
recognise such differences).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important relationship, upon which I want us to focus, is that between
Bernstein and the musicians. Only when there's mutual respect, a feeling of
safety and trust can such potentially difficult conversations, involving the
giving and receiving of constructive criticism to fulfil some important end,
take place. How such discussions unfold will reflect the unique relationship
cultivated between the participants. So long as both parties share a bond of
trust and respect, and we recognise and respect such a bond &lt;em&gt;reflects their
unique relationship with each other&lt;/em&gt;, then we can engage with and learn from
the feedback and what the outcome tells us about the endeavour. In other words,
our world is enlarged by observing their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions to Explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How has your world been enlarged through a recent code review?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember a time when you received valuable feedback or an important lesson
  that enlarged your world; how was it revealed to you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your team’s approach to code reviews?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you and your collaborators cultivate a place of mutual respect, trust,
  and compassion?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put yourself in Bernstein’s shoes, what would you say to the percussionists?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagine you’re the percussionists, how would you respond to Bernstein’s
  feedback?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of a recent PR submitted for you to review. How did you help enlarge
  the world of the author? How was your world enlarged?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/code-reviews/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EuroPython 2022</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/europython-2022/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I had a wonderful time at &lt;a href="https://ep2022.europython.eu/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt;, last
week, in Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important aspect of the conference, for me personally, involved giving
my talk entitled "Music and Code". It was an opportunity for me to reveal and
explore how I feel about programming, teaching and learning and the place of
tech in our wider culture. I've wanted to give a talk like this for over ten
years, but only recently have I figured out how to express what I wanted to say
through music as a metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/4McW0mrONLo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important aspect of the conference was friendship and it was a huge
pleasure to be a small part of the organising team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I especially
want to highlight collaborating with &lt;a href="https://blog.europython.eu/humans-of-europython-vicky/"&gt;Vicky&lt;/a&gt;
(a remarkable friend who embodies so many of the wonderful aspects of our
Python community: a pro-active "can do" attitude, an inclusive and
compassionate outlook towards others, and a formidable determination to
thoughtfully do "the right thing" for the benefit of the whole community). The
two of us flapped and faffed to fulfil a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maker_culture"&gt;Maker&lt;/a&gt; space within EuroPython.
Given the amount of positive engagement from attendees, I hope this becomes a
regular feature of the conference. A case in point being the DIY robots
competing to solve a maze in the fastest time, organised by the energetic and
enthusiastic folks at the &lt;a href="http://niraspberryjam.com/"&gt;Northern Ireland Jam&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TGb4g-E70Fk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to mention &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/boyang-dou/"&gt;Raquel&lt;/a&gt;, who
chaired this year's EuroPython. Her clear leadership, &lt;em&gt;from the front&lt;/em&gt;, her
apparently infinite energy, &lt;em&gt;displayed through her considerable efforts&lt;/em&gt;, and
her humane connection with folks, &lt;em&gt;embodied by her patience, friendliness and
compassion&lt;/em&gt; are generous gifts she has shared with us all. I sincerely hope
she's taking some post-conference time off, and I want to thank her for
reaching out to me, all those months ago, to become a part of organising
EuroPython. And I have to say all my fellow organisers were an absolute joy to
work with. Their collective courtesy, hard work, enthusiasm and friendliness is
a very rare and special thing that I hope we can sustain, nourish and
cultivate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other group of friends deserves a mention - my fellow maintainers of
&lt;a href="https://codewith.mu/"&gt;the Mu code editor&lt;/a&gt;. It was a huge amount of fun for us
to be together in the same place for the first time ever. I was especially
delighted to meet &lt;a href="https://github.com/xbecas"&gt;Vasco&lt;/a&gt;, face to face, for the
first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final part of EuroPython were two days of "code sprints", where open-source
collaborators work together on their projects, meet to discuss technical and
other aspects of our collective work, and welcome new collaborators and friends
to our efforts. We, the maintainers of Mu, had a wonderful time focusing on
Mu related things, and collaborating with new contributors who have made
welcome enhancements to Mu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a picture of all the Mu maintainers at EuroPython:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/mu_maintainers.jpg" alt="The five core Mu maintainers" title="The five core Mu maintainers"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The five core Mu maintainers:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tjguk"&gt;Tim&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tmontes"&gt;Tiago&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/carlosperate"&gt;Carlos&lt;/a&gt;,
myself and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/xbecas"&gt;Vasco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I heard many wonderful talks, enjoyed the conversations with many
friends old and new in the famous corridor track and took part in some really
stimulating workshops (with my amazing daughter, who was attending her first
PyCon as a proper attendee with an interest in data science - she especially
enjoyed both
&lt;a href="https://djangogirls.org/en/dublin/"&gt;Django Girls&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://ep2022.europython.eu/humble-data"&gt;Humble Data&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love EuroPython's culturally cosmopolitan feeling, something that's hard to
recreate at a national PyCon. I love how folks keep coming back to EuroPython,
there are people who mean a lot to me, who I only ever see at this conference.
I also love EuroPython's peripatetic nature, as a community we are welcomed to
all sorts of fun places and have an opportunity to soak up the vibe of
different countries and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long may it last, and I hope to see you at next year's EuroPython.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/europython-2022/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 13:20:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pastures New</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/pastures-new/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been a freelance software engineer for almost 17 years. In that time, as
is usual for a freelancer, I have changed roles every 18 months to two years.
Often I took time off between gigs to work on personal projects, write, reflect
or learn something new. For instance, in 2008 I left my role as a senior .NET
developer for an investment bank in London to learn Python, then reset my
career as a junior Python coder three months later and never looked back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've relished my freedom and independence, and it has been a privilege to work
on a huge variety of projects for a diverse range of companies in many
different sectors. I have been enriched by my colleagues, made many wonderful
friends, and learned a huge amount from folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet change is in the air... Since January I've been in discussions with
&lt;a href="https://www.anaconda.com/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt; and from today (the Northern Hemisphere's
summer solstice no less!), I'm delighted to reveal I'll be joining them as
a principal engineer. Long may the sun shine on this endeavour. 🌞&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; big change for me and my family is that I'm an employee rather than
freelancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big factor in persuading me to step away from freelancing were the folks I
met in interviews and the company culture I encountered leading up to my offer
of employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important factor was the nature of the work I'll be doing. I can't go
into details, but I'm very excited to work with an exceptionally talented group
of folks, on something that I'll relish getting my teeth into. Importantly, it
is an opportunity for me to bring together and use skills from many different
aspects of my background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Anaconda understand what motivates folks passionate about creative
coding: I'll still be active as an open source contributor and will continue to
develop projects such as &lt;a href="https://codegrades.com/"&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; in my own time,
as has been the case so far.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's to new adventures.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/pastures-new/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Complete</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offa-all/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;For completeness, here's a list of all the Offa's Dyke related blog posts in
chronological order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-1/"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt; - Chepstow, pizza and first steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-2/"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt; - Monmouth to Pandy over rolling countryside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-3-4-5/"&gt;Days 3, 4 and 5&lt;/a&gt; - Things don't go to plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-6/"&gt;Day 6&lt;/a&gt; - The Centre for Alternative Technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-7-8-9/"&gt;Days 7, 8 and 9&lt;/a&gt; - Shropshire hills, Welsh lakes and castles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-final/"&gt;Days 10, 11 and 12&lt;/a&gt; - Improvising and going with the flow to our destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offa-all/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Days 10, 11 and 12:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-final/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We found our relaxing rhythm during the final few days of our holiday. Our lack
of a plan allowed us to follow our noses, and intuitively improvise an itinerary
during each day. As you'll see from the photos below, we spent a lot of time
focusing on four things: historic monuments, gardens, food and travel through
beautiful places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our tenth day started with breakfast in Ruthin, at Gail's coffee and tea rooms
on Upper Clwyd Street. Many of our stop overs have provided us with spectacular
food and drink, and the vegetarian full cooked breakfast at this modest and
out of the way cafe was up there with the best. Their friendly chef suggested
a few sights to see in Ruthin and furnished us with a map. And so our typical
modus operandi of chatting with locals and improvising on the spur of the
moment led us to the grounds of Ruthin castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/ruthin_castle_display.jpg" alt="Peacocks in the gardens of Ruthin Castle." title="Peacocks in the gardens of Ruthin Castle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Peacocks in the gardens of Ruthin Castle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chef at Gail's had explained the peacocks who live in the castle grounds
were a friendly bunch, and we were not disappointed to find several of them
displaying to the peahens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/ruthin_castle_gardens.jpg" alt="Ruthin Castle gardens." title="Ruthin Castle gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ruthin Castle gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle itself was undergoing renovation, since the original fortified
remains had been converted into a stately pile during the 19th century, and
were now used as a hotel of some sort. With the abundance of dramatic castles
in this part of the world, it was inevitable we'd find a few that had been
repurposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our chef at Gail's also suggested we visit the Ruthin Arts Centre, and we
spent an extended period of time wandering the relatively small but open plan
galleries. Both Mary and I particularly enjoyed the exhibition of
husband-and-wife artists
&lt;a href="https://paulineburbidge-quilts.com/"&gt;Pauline Burbridge&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://charlespoulsenartwork.co.uk/"&gt;Charlie Poulsen&lt;/a&gt;. We immersed ourselves
in the artworks and lost track of time... as we encountered the art in three
distinct phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow wandering around the exhibition as we let our intuition guide us as we
were drawn different pieces,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a sort of inquisitive "deep dive" as we read the prose attached to the
exhibitions and watched a couple of videos where the artists describe their
works, process and intents,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a recapitulation as we explore the exhibition one final time now that we're
more familiar with the pieces, the artists and the story being told.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/artwork.jpg" alt="A fragment from a Charlie Poulsen piece." title="A fragment from a Charlie Poulsen piece."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A fragment from a Charlie Poulsen piece.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a wonderful state of mind to inhabit and we both wished there had
been more of this to explore and encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having put us both in a thoughtful mood, and given the glorious weather, Mary
suggested we go visit &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodnant_Garden"&gt;Bodnant garden&lt;/a&gt;
to continue our pensive strolling. Since we had the car and we felt like
touring through North Wales, we instructed the sat-nav and slowly wound our way
to our destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/bodnant_gardens.jpg" alt="Bodnant gardens." title="Bodnant gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bodnant gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found ourselves in a large and
varied garden containing an abundance of benches on which we could both sit,
look, listen and soak up our surroundings. I think my favourite aspect of the
gardens were the woods containing paths and shallow brooks and many different
sorts of tree and woodland life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the art gallery, our slow meandering meant we encountered and
re-encountered aspects of the garden in a manner that encouraged a slow and
thoughtful attention to all the ways the garden stimulated our senses: the
colourful floral displays, smell of pine, sound of running water or warmth of
the sun touching our faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/bodnant_gardens_terrace.jpg" alt="Bodnant gardens terraces." title="Bodnant gardens terraces."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bodnant gardens terraces.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening we found ourselves staying at a community run inn that was
holding a quiz night. After an early dinner we joined the locals and had a
friendly evening answering questions about such diverse topics as the game of
Cluedo, Elton John's back catalogue, the plural noun for crows (it's a "murder"
of crows, in case you're wondering), and other out of the way trivia. The quiz
was both taken seriously, yet in a spirit of silliness, as many of the locals
made humorous commentary of the emerging themes in the questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, our modus operandi of chatting with locals and improvising on the
spur of the moment led us to something fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our penultimate day started with the realisation that it was our penultimate
day. So, we decided to make use of the car and go visit the seaside, since that
was the only type of terrain we'd not yet visited during our break. We chose to
head towards Porthmadoc since it would mean driving through the beautiful Welsh
mountain range called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowdonia"&gt;Snowdonia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey was, indeed a sight to behold as we made our way to the coast, yet
upon our arrival at Porthmadoc we both felt underwhelmed by the place.
Wondering what our options might be, and in the spirit of improvisation, we
spotted a castle on the coastline in the distance and pointed the car in that
general direction only to pick up signs for
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harlech_Castle"&gt;Harlech Castle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/harlech_castle.jpg" alt="Harlech castle." title="Harlech castle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Harlech castle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This well preserved ruin is an imposing sight so we imagined it would be very
busy with tourists, due to its prominence. Yet the village was relatively
empty and we easily got into the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only was the castle an amazing sight, but the views from it were
magnificent as we were able to take in a full panorama from the Irish sea to
the mountains of Snowdonia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/harlech_view.jpg" alt="The view of Snowdonia from Harlech." title="The view of Snowdonia from Harlech."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The view of Snowdonia from Harlech.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its good state of repair, it was possible to explore many different
parts of the castle. For instance, we walked up and down spiral staircases to
get to the battlements and then to the very highest tower. I'm OK with heights
but Mary (and several others) found the drop from the walls rather intimidating
and so we didn't spend &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; long up there. Luckily it was a bright sunny day
with little wind to speak of, otherwise I imagine the reaction of folks might
be very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/harlech_walls.jpg" alt="Walking the castle walls of Harlech." title="Walking the castle walls of Harlech."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Walking the castle walls of Harlech.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were having our lunch we noticed a cameraman and several people faffing
about and talking about "positioning", "shots" and "delivery". One of them, a
lady in sunglasses, spotted us watching the events unfold and came over to
explain what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out she and her colleague were professional story tellers
specialising in Welsh legends (particularly, the 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mabinogion"&gt;Mabinogion&lt;/a&gt;), and were at Harlech to
tell stories in both English and beginner level Welsh, to help keep this
beautifully musical language alive. The UK's &lt;a href="https://www.itv.com/"&gt;ITV news&lt;/a&gt;
had turned up to do a short feature on their work and were just filming a
talking head segment in front of the castle before filming the actual story
telling in the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't realise such bardic activity was going on, but both of us love
listening to a well told yarn, so quickly finished our lunch and headed back
over the bridge into the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside we found perhaps a hundred people sitting on benches, low walls and the
grass as our bespectacled friend started to tell us a story. I won't describe
stories she and her colleague told. Rather, I heartily encourage you to seek
out such folk and let them cast their magic. In our case, as they told their
tales in Harlech, the story tellers embodied and communicated the worlds they
described in a way that only an oral story teller can. The best special effects
happen as part of the story seen inside one's head, the interaction between the
story teller and their audience adds an extra dimension of connectivity to the
telling of tales that our screen laden world often lacks and, ultimately, our
stories are just that... connections between ourselves that deeply and
fundamentally move and speak to us through distances of time and space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the video segment broadcast by ITV, it is but a shadow cast by the
brilliance of their story telling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6Oo9uypliq8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must have spent hours in the castle, since we both mentioned exploring the
village of Harlech at the same time. Almost immediately we discovered a small
ice cream shop, selling home made produce made earlier in the day. This was some
of the best ice cream either of us have ever tasted, and the owner explained how
she hand made the produce fresh each day. Clearly this woman had a passion
for ice cream, and we could taste it in abundance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/mary_icecream.jpg" alt="Mary, with her amazing ice cream." title="Mary, with her amazing ice cream."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Mary, with her amazing ice cream.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just around the corner was an knick-knack shop in which I found a piano. On
the music stand was Debussy's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suite_bergamasque#3._Clair_de_lune"&gt;Clair de Lune&lt;/a&gt; (which I know),
so I rattled it off, after finding a very convenient candelabra to help free up
a hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/nicholas_piano.jpg" alt="Nicholas on the piano, but where is his ice cream?" title="Nicholas on the piano, but where is his ice cream?"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Nicholas on the piano, but where is his ice cream?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was lovely to play after more than a week away, and I even got a round of
applause!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon leaving Harlech we decided to take the long and winding road over
the mountains of Snowdonia, just to take in the views and make space for
enjoying a slow and gently winding journey together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/snowdonia.jpg" alt="Snowdonia." title="Snowdonia."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Snowdonia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the morning of our final day (today), we finished the last of many full
breakfasts and set off for Prestatyn to conclude our walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/offas_sign.jpg" alt="The sign to Chepstow." title="The sign to Chepstow."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The sign to Chepstow.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did we realise, almost a fortnight ago, how different our adventure
along Offa's Dyke would be, compared to what we had imagined or prepared for.
We certainly enjoyed walking the first third of the trail (almost 60 miles),
and we both reflected that the injuries and improvised change to a touring
holiday had taught us a lesson: go with the flow, and unexpected change is to
be embraced and welcomed if you're going to make something of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/offas_stone.jpg" alt="The stone marking the end of Offa's Dyke." title="The stone marking the end of Offa's Dyke."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The stone marking the end of Offa's Dyke.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, as I write this back at home in Towcester, both Mary and I feel
glad to have returned after our journey together. We're especially looking
forward to seeing our children again and giving them gifts we found on our way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think this won't be the last time Mary and I do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've had too much fun not to do it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/offas_selfie.jpg" alt="The two of us, at the end of our adventure." title="The two of us, at the end of our adventure."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The two of us, at the end of our adventure.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onwards!&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-final/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 13:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Days 7, 8 and 9:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-7-8-9/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Since we are supposed to be on a walking holiday, Mary and I decided to try
out a shorter walk, and one with which we were familiar, on day 7. We were in
Mary's part of the world (the beautiful Shropshire hills) and so we found
ourselves driving to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stiperstones"&gt;Stiperstones&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/stiperselfie.jpg" alt="The two of us walking along the ridge at Stiperstones." title="The two of us walking along the ridge at Stiperstones"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The two of us on the ridge at Stiperstones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived relatively early in the morning and easily found a parking space,
gingerly put on our boots and started to make our ascent. Given we were both
injured in some sense (me with my blisters and Mary with her knee) we went at a
slow and steady pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/stiperstones.jpg" alt="An outcrop at Stiperstones." title="An outcrop at Stiperstones"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;An outcrop at Stiperstones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the top of the ridge (one of the highest points in Shropshire), the
outcrops of quartzite rock make obvious waypoints for hiking. We found several
folks &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouldering"&gt;bouldering&lt;/a&gt; on the rock
formations and paused to watch them and take in the glorious views and drink in
the fresh clear air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/underfoot.jpg" alt="Conditions underfoot at Stiperstones." title="Conditions underfoot at Stiperstones"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Very poor conditions under foot at Stiperstones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conditions underfoot on many parts of the ridge are not good, and it's easy to
go over on one's ankle or painfully stub a toe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our slowness was thus more compounded by both the injuries and rough-shod rocks
strewn all over the paths. Yet we made progress and walked the full extent of
the ridge in glorious sunshine and accompanied by larks chirruping
away:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;q&gt;He rises and begins to round,&lt;br&gt;
He drops the silver chain of sound&lt;br&gt;
Of many links without a break,&lt;br&gt;
In chirrup, whistle, slur and shake,&lt;br&gt;
All intervolv’d and spreading wide,&lt;br&gt;
Like water-dimples down a tide&lt;br&gt;
Where ripple ripple overcurls&lt;br&gt;
And eddy into eddy whirls;&lt;/q&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://allpoetry.com/The-Lark-Ascending"&gt;The Lark Ascending&lt;/a&gt; ~ George Meredith&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All told we walked almost five miles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="map-day7" style="height: 400px"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon we visited the small town of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop's_Castle"&gt;Bishop's Castle&lt;/a&gt;,
having heard the high street contained a number of book shops and a
&lt;a href="https://poetrypharmacy.co.uk/"&gt;Poetry Pharmacy&lt;/a&gt;, which sounded like it was
just what we needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/bishops-castle.jpg" alt="Bishop's Castle high street." title="Bishop's Castle high street."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The high street at Bishop's Castle - including a poetry pharmacy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end we spent most of our time in the wonderful &lt;a href="https://www.hocmuseum.org.uk/"&gt;House on Crutches Museum&lt;/a&gt;
where I was able to examine some of the old brass instruments from the former
town band (not in a good state), and learn all about local
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morris_dance"&gt;Morris dancing&lt;/a&gt; troupes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poetry pharmacy was another highlight, although I was unable to find
anything to read that suited my mood. Perhaps, given that I usually have my
nose in a book, this holiday is also a holiday from reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening we stayed near &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welshpool"&gt;Welshpool&lt;/a&gt;
and found evidence of the local knitting circle's guerilla Easter decoration
operation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/welshpool.jpg" alt="Easter knitting in Welshpool." title="Easter knitting in Welshpool."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Easter knitting in Welshpool.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day started with a drive to lake Vyrnwy (you pronounce it,
"ver-in-wee"). The lake is man-made and to reach the car park involves crossing
this rather imposing dam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/vyrnwy-dam.jpg" alt="The dam at Lake Vyrnwy." title="The dam at Lake Vyrnwy."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The imposing dam at Lake Vyrnwy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We timed our arrival perfectly since the car park was empty and hardly anyone
appeared to be around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to walk around the lake until we found a quiet beach on which we
could sit, relax and simply ponder the world. It can't have taken more than 20
minutes to find such an isolated spot, and we spent over two hours just
chatting, relaxing or throwing skimmers into the lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the morning we were joined by various passers-by: a young
family, a Polish couple with their daughter, a group of students. Everyone was
friendly and happy to be by the lakeside and the opportunity for moments of
reflection that it offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/lake-vyrnwy.jpg" alt="Lake Vyrnwy." title="Lake Vyrnwy."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lake Vyrnwy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our walk back to the car we appeared to meet a bank holiday weekend tour for
the "young fellers with souped-up cars" motoring club. The sound of noisy
exhausts, the look of go-faster stripes and the thinness of sports tyres
(clearly, for country roads) were much in evidence. A massive traffic jam was
also in evidence as the posse (what is the correct plural noun?) of young men
in souped up cars, took on the overweight hairy bikers and caravan owners in a
three way battle for the junction leading to the dam. It wasn't a pretty sight
as helpful bikers attempted to direct the traffic, only to be ignored by one of
the other tribes (in the end, the old fellers just stood in the way of the
traffic to control the flow). Well, done to the hairy bikers for their public
service!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took our time getting back to the car, not wishing to be involved in the
traffic chaos, but in the end the blockages had been cleared and the route to
the dam was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended up driving to our overnight rest stop at &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanymynech"&gt;Llanymynech&lt;/a&gt;
and spent some time exploring the remains of the lime industry in the area.
This included a lovely walk in some woods reclaiming the area used for
processing and delivering treated lime into barges on the Shropshire Union
canal. Among the thickets we found a huge abandoned lime kiln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/lime-kilns.jpg" alt="Lime kilns in Llanymynech." title="Lime kilns in Llanymynech."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lime kilns in Llanymynech.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today started with a trip to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chirk_Castle"&gt;Chirk Castle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As members of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Trust"&gt;National Trust&lt;/a&gt;
we got in for free and spent the morning wandering the amazing gardens and
grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/chirk_castle.jpg" alt="Chirk Castle." title="Chirk Castle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Chirk Castle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gardens ranged from managed woodland to formal gardens with statues and
topiary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/chirk_formal_gardens.jpg" alt="Chirk gardens." title="Chirk gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Chirk gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the castle were displays depicting different aspects of the castle's
history, including the dungeon, the clockwork for the clock tower, the
servant's hall and a collection of knight's helmets. These final items made
me smile, as each helmet appears to bear a different expression, much like a
medieval metal emoji.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/helmet_emoji.jpg" alt="A selection of knight's helmets." title="A selection of knight's helmets."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A selection of knight's helmets.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon we visited the town of Llangollen. It being bank holiday
Monday, the small town was heaving with visitors (like us) and the tourist
traps were doing a swift trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A highlight was watching canoeists tackle the Dee river running through the
town (they had hung slalom gates over the river). This led us to the railway
station, run by volunteer enthusiasts, and we ended up escaping the scrum of
tourists by taking a trip up the valley in an open train to the village of
Berwyn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/llangollen.jpg" alt="The river Dee at Llangollen." title="The river Dee at Llangollen."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The river Dee at Llangollen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we enter the final stretch of our holiday, we're both starting to feel like
all this relaxing and touring is quite tiring. It means our holiday has done
its job: we're looking forward to throwing ourselves back into our usual day to
day routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
var map_day7 = L.map('map-day7').setView([51.505, -0.09], 13);
L.tileLayer('http://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png', {
  attribution: 'Map data &amp;copy; &lt;a href="http://www.osm.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;'
}).addTo(map_day7);
var gpx_day7 = "/static/files/gpx/stiperstones.gpx"; // URL to your GPX file or the GPX itself
new L.GPX(gpx_day7, {
  async: true,
  marker_options: {
    startIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-start.png',
    endIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-end.png',
    shadowUrl: '/static/images/pin-shadow.png'
  }
}).on('loaded', function(e) {
  map_day7.fitBounds(e.target.getBounds());
}).addTo(map_day7);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-7-8-9/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Day 6:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-6/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was our first proper "touring" day, and we made the most of our relative
(but not actual) closeness to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machynlleth"&gt;Machynlleth&lt;/a&gt;
to visit
the &lt;a href="https://cat.org.uk/"&gt;Centre for Alternative Technology&lt;/a&gt; (CAT) - an
inspiring organisation that specialises in sustainable living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first visited CAT back in 1995, it turned out to be a perfect day both
of us fondly remember. We have returned several times since and enjoyed
watching the site, educational work and influence of the CAT organisation 
flourish and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone fascinated with technology (and I'll informally define that as,
&lt;em&gt;crafting the world through creativity and coherent invention to better engage
and interact with it to some valuable aim or benefit&lt;/em&gt;), the "alternative" part
of the CAT name has always appealed to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a software engineer, a job most folks imagine is at the heart of "new" or
"hi"-tech. Yet I, and many of my colleagues, will tell you that "new"
and "hi"-tech is not necessarily the same as "good". The focus on "alternative"
appeals to the engineer in me: it means I'm not constrained to frame my
thinking via the tired stereotypes found in our culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of what I mean is the first thing you see upon arrival at CAT, a
water powered funicular railway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa6/water_powered_rail.jpg" alt="Arrival at the Centre for Alternative Technology involves ascending a mountain in a water powered funicular railway." title="Arrival at the Centre for Alternative Technology involves ascending a mountain in a water powered funicular railway."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Arrival at the Centre for Alternative Technology involves ascending a mountain in a water powered funicular railway.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly there is a lot of technology going on here, but it's not a computing
"tech" mode of transport like a Segway or self-driving car. If you
understand simple physics, it's easy to figure out how it works. That it runs
on water, an abundant resource in rainy Wales, means the energy cost of running
the system is very small and doesn't involve polluting the environment
(rather, it complements and integrates the ambient environmental conditions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa6/the_lake.jpg" alt="The lake at the top of the railway is the source of the water." title="The lake at the top of the railway is the source of the water."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The lake at the top of the railway is the source of the water.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this enlarged view of technology, beyond just the thing being imagined
or a "tech" mode of creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainability, impact and
the life-cycle of the "tech" is carefully considered. This is a very
different approach to "smaller, faster, cheaper" gizmos and apps inflicted upon
"consumers", created and made with a development process based on the mantra of
"&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1428/"&gt;move fast and break things&lt;/a&gt;",
whose aim is to maximise shareholder profit. Put simply, there is a
philosophical aspect to tech that is, in my experience, often missing or
actively discouraged in "tech" culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, we chose to take part in the guided tour because we wanted to see and
hear about the centre from our guide: someone intimate with the ethos and
practicalities of such an enlarged outlook to technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being
semi-regular visitors over the past 27 years or more, both Mary and I learned
so much from our guide, Joel, who patiently fielded questions and engaged our
group both with the story of CAT and the various things found therein (such as
modular &lt;a href="http://www.segalselfbuild.co.uk"&gt;Segal method&lt;/a&gt; buildings, or the
diverse number of energy solutions, such as the hydroelectric
generator shown below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa6/water_power.jpg" alt="The hydroelectric generator." title="The hydroelectric generator."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The flow of water from the top lake to the lake used by the railway drives the hydroelectric generator.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CAT is a very stimulating and eye-opening place, with much of the location taken over with
practical educational projects that both illustrate and explain the many
aspects of "alternative" technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, I enjoyed their approach to engaging with folks wishing to learn.
Rather than a "how to use" video or documentation that fills your head with
facts, we were left to experiment
and engage directly with "alternative" tech. For instance, the
wind-powered seat (shown below), beautifully illustrated how little wind is
needed to achieve some useful end (in this case, lift and lower a person).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa6/wind_powered_chair.jpg" alt="A wind powered chair that moves up and down." title="A wind powered chair that moves up and down."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A wind powered chair gently moves the occupant up and down.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you don't see in this photograph of me sitting on the chair, is the
relatively small windmill attached by a pulley system to the seat. I have to
say this was a pleasantly gentle and rather fun way to prove a point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture is also an important aspect of CAT, with many of the buildings
demonstrating interesting approaches to creating space for living, working and
enjoying life. Often unusual but sustainably sourced
materials are used (straw bale, or rammed earth for instance) and those aspects
of the building are thoughtfully brought to visitor's attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CAT is also a thriving educational organisation and, while we were wandering
the site, we noticed groups of students learning about "alternative" technology
in buildings built with such technology, created by the folks running the
educational programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rather like the directness of this approach. If I were
a student looking to engage with these things, who wouldn't want to learn in
such a way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa6/conference_centre.jpg" alt="The sustainably built conference and education centre." title="The sustainably built conference and education centre."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The sustainably designed and built conference and education centre.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, CAT isn't just about "alternative" tech, but also contains information
about alternative uses of "traditional" tech. For instance, as a
space-nut, I was fascinated by their interactive display on using small earth
observation satellites to gather data and monitor changes in the landscape.
Space bound technology is no longer just the preserve of large governmental
agencies like NASA, and the open data received can be put to all sorts of
interesting and important uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa6/earth_observation_sat.jpg" alt="A small earth observation satellite." title="A small earth observation satellite."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A small earth observation satellite.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're ever in mid-Wales, I heartily recommend CAT. Mary and I have always
had thought provoking visits.
Clearly CAT won't appeal to everyone, but nobody can ignore their hard work to
promote a much needed different perspective... an alternative vision of
"technology".&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-6/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2022 06:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Days 3, 4 and 5:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-3-4-5/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Our meal at the end of day 2 was lots of fun. As we walked into the
pub we met again the lady who had found Mary's phone on day 1, struck up a
conversation, and she joined us for a sociable evening of chatter over rustic
grub. It turned out Caroline was a teacher and so we had a fine old time
going over teacher talk. We shared classroom based triumphs and tragedies and
the usual moans and gripes about the state of the education "system"
that all teachers appear to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning, as expected, it was raining and the country was covered in
low rolling mist. Nevertheless we set off in good spirits and determined to
climb up onto the ridge for the views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did we know how different our situation would be by the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/setting_out.jpg" alt="Walking towards the Black Mountains." title="Walking towards the Black Mountains."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Walking towards the Black Mountains, in the rain.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of relatively swift miles tramping the rolling countryside to
Pandy, we started to ascend the edge of the Black Mountains. Since we were
laden with all our clobber this took a while: but our mantra was "slow and
steady does it". We could have stomped up, like I usually do, but we decided to
save ourselves for the 15 miles of walking over the ridge we would need to
complete to get us to Hay-on-Wye by the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sight to greet us upon completing our ascent was an ancient hill
fort from pre-Roman times. Even after 2500-3000 years, the dykes and ditches
that marked the boundaries of the fort were an imposing site, especially as
they loomed ominously out of the mist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/hill_fort.jpg" alt="The ramparts of a 2500 year old hill fort." title="The ramparts of a 2500 year old hill fort."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The ramparts of a 2500 year old hill fort.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, it was at this point, we resigned ourselves to the fact that the
weather would be against us for the day. There would be no beautiful views
over mountains or down into valleys for us. In fact, we could only see about 20
metres ahead of ourselves. Fortunately the path for the Offa's Dyke trail was
obvious, so we just had to trudge on (and on, and on).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to remain motivated when all around you is freezing fog. There's no
sense of progress and it's impossible to look back to see how far you've come,
or look ahead to a marker in the distance as a target to aim for. Yet sometimes
we would pass way-points that marked the tops of peaks, and this photo, taken
perhaps just before lunchtime, is a good indication of our conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/wet_conditions.jpg" alt="Wet conditions on the ridge." title="Wet conditions on the ridge."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Wet conditions on the ridge.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also felt quite alone: by lunch we hadn't met a soul. Yet we were not the
only ones tramping the hills that day. Huge piles of steaming dung alerted
us to the presence of others, just out of sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then suddenly, we came upon the group of wild horses grazing the grass.
They took a look at us, pondered for a few seconds why on earth two humans
would be up there with them, and then returned to the more pressing task of
grazing again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/wild_horses.jpg" alt="Wild horses." title="Wild horses."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Wild horses.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point mid-afternoon the conditions under-foot became much more boggy
and the path turned into a set of paving slabs. We joked that Offa must have
sourced them from the local garden centre...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/offas_paving_slabs.jpg" alt="Offa's paving slabs." title="Offa's paving slabs."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Offa's paving slabs.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;...but we were thankful that they helped us avoid tramping through the black
peaty mud. Perhaps this is how the mountains got their "black" name?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also started to realise that not all was well for either of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My feet and ankles ached and while Mary found it comfortable to walk up hills,
and over the levels, descending was very painful because of her right knee.
This got gradually worse throughout the day, to the point that it couldn't be
ignored, and we started to talk about what we might do about the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from this photo, we were determined to put a brave face on
things but I think we both realised things were not going as they should (we're
no longer spring chickens!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/afternoon_snack.jpg" alt="Drying off for an afternoon snack." title="Drying off for an afternoon snack."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Drying off for an afternoon snack.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, around mid-afternoon we met the first people of the day. Two fellow
walkers appeared out of the mist towards us, and we shared some encouraging
words. Yet just as we were commenting how deserted the ridge was, a young
man came from the same direction as us at a fast pace. He stopped to
say a quick "hello" only to realise his small back-pack had come undone. He
checked his things (nothing missing), re-adjusted his equipment and stomped off
in the direction of Hay -- a momentary mist-clad apparition accelerating into
fog. We parted company with the other couple and wished
them well, only to encounter a group of
&lt;a href="https://www.dofe.org/"&gt;Duke of Edinburgh&lt;/a&gt; participants (in the UK we have
something called the "Duke of Edinburgh Award" for teenagers, that encourages
them to explore and encounter nature and outward bound activities). We helped
them with some map reading and then, gazelle like, off they sprang into the
mist leaving us to ponder our ever slowing pace and the fact that, like London
buses, we had met nobody all day only for three different parties to turn up
within minutes of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/into_the_valley.jpg" alt="The mist lifted, and we could see the way down into the valley." title="The mist lifted, and we could see the way down into the valley."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The mist lifted, and we could see the way down into the valley.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we got to the end of the ridge, the mist lifted and we were able to finally
see some views. Yet these were not to last since we had to make our descent,
and it was here that things got very tricky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My poor Mary had to endure intolerable pain in her knee as we made our way
down the side of the mountain towards Hay-on-Wye. The first of several steep
descents should have only taken us perhaps 20 minutes but, in fact, took an
hour. We had several more descents to go until we reached our destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet we spied a line of cars parked in the distance, and this proved to be our
way out of the difficult and painful situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear the final couple of miles to Hay were all down hill with
difficult conditions under foot. My feet were a constant source of a dull ache,
and if I stopped walking the pain would become strong and resuming the walk
took lots of effort. Mary was clearly in a lot of pain with her knee, and so
our journey was no longer the happy, if tiring, adventure we had enjoyed up
until this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we approached the parked cars I tried a few local taxi companies, but nobody
picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking we may need to just press on, I spotted one of the cars was occupied.
I tapped on the window to find a man of a similar age to ourselves inside. He
told me he was there just to enjoy the view and to get out of the house for a
while. I explained our situation and he very kindly offered to drop us off in
Hay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a relief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except, he suddenly remembered, "by the way, I have COVID".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had driven to the beauty spot just to get out of the house since he had been
isolating for the past few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="map-day3" style="height: 400px"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a quick (socially distanced) chat about the potential logistics of the
situation and worked out a way for us to get a lift, but with him masked up
with the addition of a scarf around the lower part of his face, and us sitting
away from him with all the windows of the car open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to admit, we made the right decision because our speed due to the knee
situation was at a snail's pace and it would have taken several hours to cover
the final two miles into town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we had a fun chat with Carl (our impromptu driver) and I
think he enjoyed the sense of adventure the situation presented. We were
deposited right outside our guest house in Hay, got to our room and collapsed
into the shower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple of hours of rest we had stiffened up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I examined my feet and found they were covered in blisters and Mary's knee was,
to use her words, "shot to pieces".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear that our journey to walk Offa's Dyke was coming to an end and we
both felt sad and deeply frustrated by the situation. As Mary put it, "I feel
fine from the right knee up", and I was also in fine fettle from the ankles
up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet we could not continue given our different ailments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so, we decided to change plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over dinner in the &lt;a href="https://thegoodpubguide.co.uk/pub/118898/hr3+5df/blue+boar/"&gt;Blue Boar Inn&lt;/a&gt; (excellent food and beer),
we worked out what to do next. We'd booked places to stay along our route,
and we certainly didn't want to abandon our holiday, yet we clearly couldn't
walk to the extent that we would need to, and it was clear our current
situation required us to rest and recover before attempting any further
distance by foot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end we decided to transform our holiday from a
"by foot" affair to a touring holiday with a car on hand,
which leads us to day 4's adventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href="https://booktowntaxi.co.uk/"&gt;booked a taxi&lt;/a&gt; to pick us up at 9am the next
morning and take
us to Hereford station. From there we took a train to Shrewsbury and another
short taxi hop to the village where Mary grew up, her parent's house, and the
place where we'd parked our car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey was uneventful, the highlight being the local taxi driver from
Hay-on-Wye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within seconds of picking us up he had asked us about our
reason for being in the place and Mary reciprocated by asking what living in
such a beautiful place as Hay-on-Wye was like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Well", he ruefully started, "there's us, and then there's them."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing he had a captive audience for at least the next 45 minutes, he went on
to explain that Hay-on-Wye has a highly stratified population. By "us" he
meant those born and bred in the place scraping a living via a few relatively
menial jobs. By "them" he meant, "city folk who sell up, move here and lord it
all over the place like they're millionaires". This included the owners of
various "lifestyle" shops, coffee houses in the town, and artisanal crafty
places. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hadn't seen that much of Hay-on-Wye so didn't have any evidence to check his
appraisal of the situation. We were sympathetic to
his cause and he was clearly enjoying putting the world to rights. As he
dropped us off he even commented that he'd had a jolly old time getting things
off his chest. Clearly, we were good (captive) listeners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we picked up our car, we made our way back into Wales and our place of
rest for the next night: Kington. During the journey we realised we were
passing close by the village where Mary's widowed aunt (who we hadn't seen
since before the pandemic) had settled with her new partner. We called ahead
and made arrangements to drop our stuff off in Kington before joining our
relative for a lovely meal and evening of catching up. It was lovely to see
she was so settled and happy with her new partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning, after a good night's sleep and a lovely relaxed breakfast we
decided to drive back to Hay-on-Wye and look around... with both of us being
avid readers, the thought of all the book shops, for which Hay is so famous,
was a real draw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, within minutes of our arrival we could see yesterday's taxi driver was
onto something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hay-on-Wye &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; clearly a beautiful place, but had
transmogrified into a sort of unintentional parody of itself. We found shops
full of pointless crap, new age treatment centres that gave the place a smell
of cheap incense, and a faux farmer's market full of "artisans" selling yet
more nick-nak crap (there wasn't an actual farmer in sight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary's knee was also playing up again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite our very gentle pace we ended up in the chemist's shop to buy
a knee support to try to help with the pain. After following directions to the
local public toilets (so Mary could put on the strap under her trousers), our
poor opinion of Hay-on-Wye was cemented by finding the cost of taking a pee
was 30 pence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our experience of Hay is that it's a tourist trap of the worst kind,
with no actual investment in the local community. Just scratching the
surface indicated that most activities involved extracting money from naive
visitors with no sustainable local economy to speak of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We quickly escaped Hay-on-Wye and decided to follow our noses to &lt;a href="https://hergest.co.uk/"&gt;
Hergest Croft gardens&lt;/a&gt;. On the way Mary called the UK's
111 service (our NHS's first point of contact for non-emergency medical
situations). A callback with a physiotherapy nurse was duly arranged, and we
subsequently found ourselves walking in some magnificent spring gardens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/hergest_house.jpg" alt="The house in Hergest Croft gardens." title="The house in Hergest Croft gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The house in Hergest Croft gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are over 70 acres of different types of garden at Hergest Croft, and the
house had a wonderful cafe full of vegetarian food. Our slow and steady
wandering through this place was just the antidote we needed to the plastic
pastoral fakery of Hay-on-Wye and the travails of the previous days walking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/spring_flowers.jpg" alt="Spring flowers." title="Spring flowers."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Spring flowers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst exploring the rhubarb patch in the kitchen gardens the phone rang again
and Mary found a park bench to talk to the friendly nurse tasked with triaging
her knee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/in_the_garden.jpg" alt="In the kitchen garden." title="In the kitchen garden."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;In the kitchen garden.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cut a long story short, I'm currently typing this in the waiting area of 
Llandrindod Wells hospital's minor injuries unit while Mary is being seen by
a physiotherapy nurse. All told, it has taken around three hours from Mary's
first contact to her receiving treatment for her knee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa3/minor_injuries.jpg" alt="Minor injuries." title="Minor injuries."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Waiting in the minor injuries unit at Llandrindod Wells hospital.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We'll check into this evening's rest-stop and find a good pub for this
evening's meal. Tomorrow will be another day of gentle poddling &lt;em&gt;andante con
spirito&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like real life, our Offa's Dyke journey is turning up all sorts of
unforeseen and challenging situations... yet Mary and I continue to support and
encourage each other as we improvise and adapt to an unforeseen touring
holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My feet are feeling fine today, so perhaps -- assuming the nurse doesn't tell
Mary she needs a new knee (highly unlikely) -- we'll even get some more walking
in before we've finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A few hours later, in our B'n'B for the evening:&lt;/em&gt; After a series of tests,
it turns out that Mary's knee is not permanently injured, but just over-worked,
bruised and thus complaining. The nurse told her she needs to rest it for the
next three days or so, while still keeping it moving so it doesn't stiffen up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I guess we'll be playing it all by ear when it comes to rambling
Offa's Dyke (of which we've already walked almost 60 miles in three days).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get the feeling we're not done yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onwards!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
var map_day3 = L.map('map-day3').setView([51.505, -0.09], 13);
L.tileLayer('http://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png', {
  attribution: 'Map data &amp;copy; &lt;a href="http://www.osm.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;'
}).addTo(map_day3);
var gpx_day3 = "/static/files/gpx/OffasDyke_Day_03.gpx"; // URL to your GPX file or the GPX itself
new L.GPX(gpx_day3, {
  async: true,
  marker_options: {
    startIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-start.png',
    endIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-end.png',
    shadowUrl: '/static/images/pin-shadow.png'
  }
}).on('loaded', function(e) {
  map_day3.fitBounds(e.target.getBounds());
}).addTo(map_day3);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-3-4-5/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 17:20:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Day 2:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-2/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Music is a gift and it's a privilege to listen to highly skilled and
engaging musicians. We wondered what sort of music might be on at the
Queen's Head Inn yesterday evening, and we were pleasantly surprised by the
quality, versatility and mellow tones of the unnamed guitarist shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He played a selection of classic pop music, some of his own compositions and
plenty of folk music. At the end he was joined by two others, a mandolin player
(a mandolinian?) and a soprano saxophonist (who confirmed that the only
difference between a lawn mower and a saxophone, is the fingering). Actually,
joking aside, the sax player was quite virtuosic. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/music_night.jpg" alt="Music night at the Queen's Head Inn, Monmouth." title="Music night at the Queen's Head Inn, Monmouth."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Music night at the Queen's Head Inn, Monmouth.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had an unplanned and unexpectedly lovely evening just sitting back and
letting someone else perform a set of toe tapping music in such a friendly and
warm atmosphere (the locals were all pleased to make our acquaintance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a continental breakfast, at which Neil gave us advice about the next pub
at which to eat (and his advice about yesterday evening's Italian restaurant
was spot on), we packed our bags and headed for the high street to stock up
on picnic supplies. As a result, we were relatively late setting off from
Monmouth at 9:30am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, we arrived yesterday by the more welcoming direction of travel.
Because, here's a photo of the Welsh facing gate house / toll booth / fortified
bridge out of which Mary and I left the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/gatehouse.jpg" alt="Leaving Monmouth via the gate house bridge." title="Leaving Monmouth via the gate house bridge."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leaving Monmouth via the gate house bridge.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few miles out of Monmouth were some wooded hills. This, I thought to
myself, would be a repeat of yesterday's wonderful forest walking: at the foot
of the hill I heard a woodpecker and the birds were singing &lt;em&gt;fortissimo con
animato&lt;/em&gt;. Here's a recording of the ambient sounds of the woods at the foot of
the hills... including the odd tapping noise of the distant woodpecker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio controls&gt;
  &lt;source src="https://ntoll.org/static/files/woodpecker.mp3" type="audio/mpeg"&gt;
  Your browser does not support the audio tag.
&lt;/source&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also took this photo immediately after making the audio recording and have
decided to name this place "woodpecker grove".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/woodpecker_grove.jpg" alt="The grove in the woods with the woodpecker." title="The grove in the woods with the woodpecker."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The woodpecker grove.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the hills took a sharp turn in an upwards direction (as hills are wont
to do). It's not so much that the hills were huge, it was just that conditions
under foot were very bad and the path was exceptionally steep. Also, at this
point early in the walk, my boots and ankles had a disagreement and I'm afraid
I suffered the painful consequences. Honestly, how Mary put up with the
constant irritated chuntering coming from my direction, like the sound of a
grumpy steam locomotive, I will never know. But she did, and I was glad she
did, because that steep incline was a struggle for all the wrong reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, despite the pain, difficulty under foot and exceptional effort needed to
climb up the steep inclines, we eventually reached the top... as Mary kept
insisting we would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We met a family resting on the bench, who made encouraging sounds about it
being downhill all the way out of the forest from this point on. We suspected
they were being generous with their encouragement, especially given all the
"bloody backpack" type comments coming from my direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not, actually, the first time we had encouragement on our walk.
Yesterday evening, just as we were walking over the welcoming, less fortified
bridge into Monmouth, a woman drove past, wound down her window and shouted at
Mary, "you go girl!". At that point in the day, Mary probably had a grim look
of determination on her face as the hotel was in sight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, our downward route was a mixed experience. Mary's knees decided to
complain, yet we found ourselves surrounded by flowers, the forest and the
sounds of nature. Mary's knees also encouraged us to make many stops
to make a closer examination of the flora and fauna we might see. This common
dog violet being a prime example of Mary's knees' keen interest in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/flowers.jpg" alt="Flowers in the woods." title="Flowers in the woods."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Flowers in the woods (a common dog violet).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the ups and downs (literally) of exploring the wooded hills, we felt we
deserved elevenses. And so, once we found a suitable spot (perching on a bridge
over a stream) we soon made short work of some banana Soreen bars. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/elevenses.jpg" alt="Elevenses, sitting on a bridge over a stream." title="Elevenses, sitting on a bridge over a stream."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Elevenses, sitting on a bridge over a stream.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suitably fuelled up, we pressed on over the rolling countryside (or, as Neil at
the Queen's Head described it, gently undulating farmland) and made good
progress. Especially now that I had intervened in the argument between my boots
and ankles. A quick examination of the lacing situation caused me to reconsider
my options. I realised that the boots were simply too helpful in offering
unneeded support for my ankles. So I just ignored a bunch of hooks on my boots,
that seemed to be causing my discomfort, much to the relief of my ankles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lunchtime picnic was in the middle of a wonderfully tranquil orchard. We
sat down, took off our boots and just let ourselves relax into the grass. It was
lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/orchard.jpg" alt="Lunch time orchard." title="Lunch time orchard."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The orchard in which we had our lunch.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting up a head of steam after lunch took a bit of time, but we managed it.
We also encountered some hills that were less inclined to incline, if you see
what I mean. Actually, they were not too much of a challenge to walk and I,
true to form, fell into my habit of stomping &lt;em&gt;allegro con brio&lt;/em&gt; up such hills
as &lt;strong&gt;I found my rhythm&lt;/strong&gt;. Mary has had to deal with such an enthusiastic
response to hills for over 25 years, and can usually be found a little way
behind me insisting that I slow down and take in the views, dammit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This photo, is a case in point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/stomping.jpg" alt="Stomping." title="Stomping."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;When I see a hill, I tend to stomp my way up it, and Mary is VERY patient with me.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, we lamented the various aches and pains we were coming to know and
love. For both of us, mid-afternoon, these took the form of the first, dreaded,
blisters. Yet we pushed on through, despite an enforced detour due to an unsafe
bridge that took us off the Offa's Dyke route. This took us through
several flocks of unamused sheep and lambs. Mary reckons we added at least
another couple of miles to our (14.5 mile) route. I think that's the blisters
talking!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, we rejoined the route and could see our destination ahead with
tomorrow's challenge, the Brecon Beacons, on the horizon. It was at this point
we realised there had only been four kissing gates on today's route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa2/looking_at_the_view.jpg" alt="Looking over the rolling countryside to the Brecon Beacons." title="Looking over the rolling countryside to the Brecon Beacons."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking over the rolling countryside to the Brecon Beacons (tomorrow's challenge).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening, we have a meal booked at a recommended pub. In fact, it's the
only damn pub for miles and miles. Let's see if they've even heard of
vegetarians in this part of Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow will be a challenging day. It's going to rain, both of us have
blisters, and it's going to be tough walking up and over the Black
Mountains towards Hay on Wye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the name sounds ominous... surely the Black Mountains belong in Mordor..?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary put a positive spin on things: at least we get to try out our new
waterproof trousers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onwards!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="map-day2" style="height: 400px"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
var map_day2 = L.map('map-day2').setView([51.505, -0.09], 13);
L.tileLayer('http://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png', {
  attribution: 'Map data &amp;copy; &lt;a href="http://www.osm.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;'
}).addTo(map_day2);
var gpx_day2 = "/static/files/gpx/OffasDyke_Day_02_bespoke.gpx"; // URL to your GPX file or the GPX itself
new L.GPX(gpx_day2, {
  async: true,
  marker_options: {
    startIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-start.png',
    endIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-end.png',
    shadowUrl: '/static/images/pin-shadow.png'
  }
}).on('loaded', function(e) {
  map_day2.fitBounds(e.target.getBounds());
}).addTo(map_day2);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 19:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>