<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ntoll.org</title><link>https://ntoll.org/</link><description>Everything I say is false...</description><atom:link href="https://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:ntoll@ntoll.org"&gt;Nicholas H.Tollervey&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 20:36:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Day 1:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-1/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the previous blog post, we want to celebrate our 25th wedding
anniversary in style. Mary suggested we walk
&lt;a href="https://offasdyke.org.uk/"&gt;Offa's Dyke&lt;/a&gt; and I only went ahead and actually
booked it all for a twelve day hike. You see, as a devoted husband, I do as
I am told!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say we've been looking forward to this with some trepidation is an
understatement. Since early January we've been doing several long practice
walks to ensure our equipment behaves, we understand how to pace ourselves
and feel what long (20 mile or more) walks feel like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And today, the moment came for us to start our walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived by train at &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chepstow"&gt;Chepstow&lt;/a&gt;, and
booked into a guest house called, appropriately enough,
&lt;a href="https://thefirsthurdle.co.uk/"&gt;The First Hurdle&lt;/a&gt;. It happened to have an award
winning pizza parlour attached to it, so that was our evening meal sorted.
Afterwards we looked at the map and realised that we'd be walking the first
mile or so to the starting stone, only to have to retrace our steps to within
a short distance of the guest house. Given that day 1 was also the longest day
by quite some distance (19.5 miles) we thought we'd give ourselves a head start
and walk the first mile in the evening, thus saving us some time in the
morning. And so, as the dusk was falling we trekked south from Chepstow to
the starting stone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/starting_stone.jpg" alt="The stone in Chepstow, that marks the official start of the Offa's Dyke walk." title="The stone in Chepstow, that marks the official start of the Offa's Dyke walk."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The stone in Chepstow, that marks the official start of the Offa's Dyke walk.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were &lt;em&gt;very excited&lt;/em&gt; to find the stone, look across the Severn estuary and
take in that we were taking our first steps together on a very very long
journey, just as we had done so (metaphorically speaking) all those years ago
on the day of our wedding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/at_the_starting_stone.jpg" alt="Proof we made the start." title="Proof we made the start."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Mary and I besides the starting stone.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the morning, we were met at breakfast with a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Full_breakfast"&gt;full English&lt;/a&gt; (vegetarian) and
lots of coffee that seemed to do the trick and put the fire in our bellies. The
helpful waitress took this photo of us, just as we were about to set off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/setting_off.jpg" alt="Setting off from The First Hurdle." title="Setting off from The First Hurdle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Setting off from The First Hurdle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes dear reader, completely independently of each other we have purchased
pretty much the same GorTex jackets and trousers, so we definitely look like a
the middle aged "Mr. and Mrs." that we so clearly and unwittingly are. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have on my phone an &lt;a href="https://www.ordnancesurvey.co.uk/"&gt;Ordinance Survey&lt;/a&gt; app
into which I can load pre-planned &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GPS_Exchange_Format"&gt;GPX files&lt;/a&gt;
that define our route. I created our GPX routes back in January (based upon the
official "Offa's Dyke" guide - sadly Offa is no longer with us to sign such
books), and careful testing during our training sessions showed the OS app was
the clear winner for ease of use and simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we could have saved ourselves the trouble, because a squirrel like
ranger, with a love of acorns had clearly marked our route at every turn.
Actually, because the Offa's Dyke route is designated a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Trails"&gt;National Trail&lt;/a&gt;
(and there are several of these in the UK) an acorn logo is used to tell you you're
on such a long distance footpath, administered and maintained by
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_England"&gt;Natural England&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_Resources_Wales"&gt;Natural Resources Wales&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/follow_the_acorns.jpg" alt="Follow the acorn logo to stay on route." title="Follow the acorn logo to stay on route."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Follow the acorn logo to stay on the route.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unexpectedly common feature of our walk was the large number of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kissing_gate"&gt;kissing gates&lt;/a&gt;. I always thought
they were so named because, if you were walking with someone, the tradition
when passing through such gates, was to share a kiss. I've just looked at the
Wikipedia page (linked to above), and it appears I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;q&gt;The name comes from the gate merely "kissing" (touching) the inside of the enclosure.&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We counted 34 such gates, and we kissed at each one. I'm not going to tell Mary
that we've got our "kissing gate" story wrong, just to see if she actually
reads this blog post..! I think our reason is far better, and certainly more
appropriate given our 25th wedding anniversary. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/kissing_gate.jpg" alt="Lots of kissing gates." title="Lots of kissing gates."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The route contained lots of kissing gates (34 on today's leg, we tried them all).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather was wonderful. We had a crisp April day that was full of sunshine,
but not unbearable heat. Conditions under foot were good and we were treated to
all sorts of wonderful moments where we allowed ourselves to be in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mostly walked three types of terrain: wood, hills and river banks. I think
my favourite was the woodland walking (perhaps because I'm originally from
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sherwood_Forest"&gt;Sherwood Forest&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were treated to all sorts of sensory stimulation: the smell of wild garlic,
the fresh April breeze, the sound of the river Wye along whose banks we walked,
and, of course, a lot of birdsong. I made this recording in the woods at the
top of the cliffs that overlook Tintern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;audio controls&gt;
  &lt;source src="https://ntoll.org/static/files/bird.mp3" type="audio/mpeg"&gt;
  Your browser does not support the audio tag.
&lt;/source&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking of Tintern... for much of the walk we were following in the august
footsteps of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Wordsworth"&gt;William Wordsworth&lt;/a&gt;,
who wrote &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lines_Written_a_Few_Miles_above_Tintern_Abbey"&gt;Lines Written a Few Miles above Tintern Abbey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;q&gt;Five years have passed; five summers, with the length&lt;br&gt;
Of five long winters! and again I hear&lt;br&gt;
These waters, rolling from their mountain-springs&lt;br&gt;
With a sweet inland murmur. — Once again&lt;br&gt;
Do I behold these steep and lofty cliffs,&lt;br&gt;
Which on a wild secluded scene impress&lt;br&gt;
Thoughts of more deep seclusion; and connect&lt;br&gt;
The landscape with the quiet of the sky.&lt;br&gt;
The day is come when I again repose&lt;br&gt;
Here, under this dark sycamore, and view&lt;br&gt;
These plots of cottage-ground, these orchard-tufts,&lt;br&gt;
Which, at this season, with their unripe fruits,&lt;br&gt;
Among the woods and copses lose themselves,&lt;br&gt;
Nor, with their green and simple hue, disturb&lt;br&gt;
The wild green landscape. Once again I see&lt;br&gt;
These hedge-rows, hardly hedge-rows, little lines&lt;br&gt;
Of sportive wood run wild; these pastoral farms&lt;br&gt;
Green to the very door; and wreathes of smoke&lt;br&gt;
Sent up, in silence, from among the trees,&lt;br&gt;
With some uncertain notice, as might seem,&lt;br&gt;
Of vagrant dwellers in the houseless woods,&lt;br&gt;
Or of some hermit’s cave, where by his fire&lt;br&gt;
The hermit sits alone.&lt;/q&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are, a few miles above Tintern Abbey. We tramped the steep and lofty
cliff, saw plots of cottage ground in the villages below, and carefully found
our way through woods and copses as we travelled through the wild green
landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/above_tintern.jpg" alt="The two of us at the top of the cliff above Tintern Abbey (in the background)." title="The two of us at the top of the cliff above Tintern Abbey (in the background)."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The two of us at the top of the cliff above Tintern Abbey (in the background).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we descended into Brockweir we started having thoughts of food. Sadly, there
wasn't the hoped for pub, cafe or other means of nourishment. Brockweir hasn't
a lot going for it apart from the beautiful river Wye. The scenery more than
made up for the lack of food and drink!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was as we walked north along the river bank that today's "incident" took
place. At some point, and we're not sure where or how, Mary dropped her mobile
phone. We had got about 2 miles north of Brockweir when Mary discovered her
mobile was missing. At this point we put on the hand-brake, did a swift 180
turn and stomped in completely the wrong direction while regularly phoning
Mary's missing mobile to no avail. After perhaps 1.5 miles the phone was
answered by a friendly lady.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I described myself as, "a middle age chap, wearing
a TUBA t-shirt, with a heavy backpack and staff".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She replied that she was heading north and, at this point, I could see a lady
in the distance talking on a phone. So I mentioned I was furiously waving my
staff above my head and she replied,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh yes, I see you. I'll be there in 5 minutes."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happily, Mary was reunited with her phone, but not after adding 3 miles to our
total for the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I could say this was the only incident on day 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, our naivete about the culinary qualities of Brockweir meant we didn't have
anywhere to grab lunch. As a result, we drank all our water (which was rather
concerning) and cracked open emergency supply of chocolate Easter eggs. (Just
writing this down, makes me feel stupid, dear reader.) And so the last few
miles into Redbrook was more of a struggle than they should have been given
our empty tummies and the onset of thirst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, as with our journey through life, we both enjoyed ourselves during the
good times (for instance, walking in the woods), and supported and encouraged
each other when faced with a challenge. I can happily report both Mary and I,
on different occasions, helped the other overcome their moaning. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's Mary, descending into Redbrook with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monmouth"&gt;Monmouth&lt;/a&gt;
in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa1/into_wye_valley_and_monmouth.jpg" alt="Into the Wye valley and Monmouth." title="Into the Wye valley and Monmouth."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Into the Wye valley and on towards Monmouth.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, Redbrook had a pub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unhappily, we were too late for food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I think I consumed the world's best pint of bitter and packet of
salt and vinegar crisps whilst in that drinking establishment... or at least,
that's how it felt, and after 20 minutes of resting and enjoying our
repast, we creaked back into gear for the final push to Monmouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we arrived at the &lt;a href="https://queensheadmonmouth.co.uk/"&gt;Queen's Head Inn&lt;/a&gt; we
were cheerfully greeted by Neil, the publican, who made us feel very welcome
and recommended a fantastic Italian restaurant for our evening meal. I'm not
sure what the waiters made of us, but I think we set some sort of speed of
eating record in their restaurant, because we woofed down some amazing, fresh
and locally sourced Italian cuisine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this post, below us we hear live music from the bar, and Mary and I
will soon descend for a final drink, and listen to the music for a while before
a well deserved sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, here's a map of the route we covered today. We're not quite sure how
far we &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; walked, given the unplanned repeat of the river walk, but we
think we managed somewhere north of 22 miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="map-day1" style="height: 400px"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow we head to Llangattock Lingoed, which is, as far as we can tell,
completely in the middle of nowhere. As a result, we've spied a good bakery
in Monmouth and will stock up with provisions for tomorrow and the day
after (which will end in Hay-on-Wye).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onwards! :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
var map = L.map('map-day1').setView([51.505, -0.09], 13);
L.tileLayer('http://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png', {
  attribution: 'Map data &amp;copy; &lt;a href="http://www.osm.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;'
}).addTo(map);
var gpx = "/static/files/gpx/OffasDyke_Day_01.gpx"; // URL to your GPX file or the GPX itself
new L.GPX(gpx, {
  async: true,
  marker_options: {
    startIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-start.png',
    endIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-end.png',
    shadowUrl: '/static/images/pin-shadow.png'
  }
}).on('loaded', function(e) {
  map.fitBounds(e.target.getBounds());
}).addTo(map);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-1/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 19:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Wedding Anniversary Plans</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/25-anniversary-plans/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Mary and I will celebrate our 25th wedding anniversary on the 2nd of August
this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/wedding.jpg" alt="Our wedding, 2nd August 1997 at Bourton Manor, Shropshire." title="Our wedding, 2nd August 1997 at Bourton Manor, Shropshire."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Our wedding, 2nd August 1997 at Bourton Manor, Shropshire.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered Mary late on an autumnal Friday afternoon in the library of
the &lt;a href="https://www.rcm.ac.uk/library/"&gt;Royal College of Music&lt;/a&gt;. Mary and I were
the only two people in the
&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/maps/@51.4994838,-0.1770779,2a,75y,272.48h,94.45t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sV2M1OLSwpd3LHD0jlX1_MQ!2e0!7i13312!8i6656"&gt;Donaldson Room&lt;/a&gt;,
a study area with large oak desks, and she happened to be sat opposite me. I
think there was an immediate attraction because we kept surreptitiously looking
at each other. When I idly chewed my pen to try to hide that I was really
checking her out, she caught my eye and smiled at me. I involuntarily bit down
on my pen in panicked shyness (I'd been found out!) and split the pen lid while
also chipping the corner of my front tooth. I soon fled in embarrassment.
Later, I felt the roughness where my tooth had chipped and reflected that
it would be a permanent reminder of that pretty girl in the
library. For the rest of my life, when I felt the roughness on my tooth, I'd
ask myself "I wonder who she was?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn't take long for me to find out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following Wednesday, just after lunch, (yes, I have all the dates, times
and places recorded in my diary of the time) I returned to the Donaldson Room
with a buddy only to find Mary sat at a desk with her friend and fellow
cellist, Ellen. I sat down at the opposite end of their table (realising I'd
found the pretty girl again) and soon found they were not working on an
academic assignment, but goofing around playing the game of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hangman_(game)"&gt;hang man&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary had a unique tactic... whereas most people do something sensible like
start with the vowels or other common letters (to help figure out the skeleton
or shape of the word), Mary used the least expected letters. She started games
with "X", followed by "Q", then "W" or "Z".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this hilarious and, after watching her play for a few minutes,
couldn't resist to interrupt and say,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;    "You really have no idea how to play
hang man, do you?"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    "Oh yes I do. I'm just choosing to play it like
this", was her mock-offended response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We struck up a conversation, our friends (bored of our flirting) soon left us
in peace and we spent the afternoon chatting. We talked about all sorts:
science, philosophy, plants, gardens, music, books and many other things. All
too soon Mary noticed the time ~ it was 5pm and we had spent three hours in
deep joyful conversation. Time just flew by, but Mary was late for a rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll never forget how we parted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;    "I'm afraid I'm going to have to go to my rehearsal," she said, "but I'd much rather be talking with you."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the following weeks and months we got to know each other, talked a LOT and
eventually shared our true feelings for each other in the spring. It didn't
take much longer for us both to realise we'd found our life-long soulmate and
by the end of the year we were announcing our engagement. A couple of years
later, only a few weeks after Mary graduated from the RCM, we were married. She
was 22, I was 23 and we've been an "us" ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meeting Mary was the most important moment in my life. Living life's journey
with Mary has been my life's greatest privilege and full of wonderful moments -
the most important highlights being the arrival and growth of our three
beautiful children, Penelope, Sam and William.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/family_selfie.jpg" alt="A serious family selfie from 2018." title="A serious family selfie from 2018."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A serious family selfie from 2018.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To celebrate 25 years of sharing our journey through life together, Mary and I
have decided to make another (symbolic) journey together. We're going to walk
over 170 miles, during the Easter holidays, along
&lt;a href="https://www.nationaltrail.co.uk/en_GB/trails/offas-dyke-path/"&gt;Offa's Dyke&lt;/a&gt;,
a 1300 year old earthwork barrier created by Offa, king of the ancient
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercia"&gt;Anglo-Saxon kingdom of Mercia&lt;/a&gt;.
Nobody knows why the dyke was built, but the modern Welsh/English border
roughly follows its path and it passes through some of the most beautiful parts
of Wales and England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll start in the south and walk an average of 15 miles a day,
staying in bed-and-breakfasts or hotels along the way.
It being April we expect fresh showers,
but hope for sun to encourage spring flowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're not the first to have had the idea of an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Prologue"&gt;April journey&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whan that Aprille with his shoures soote,&lt;br&gt;
The droghte of March hath perced to the roote,&lt;br&gt;
And bathed every veyne in swich licóur&lt;br&gt;
Of which vertú engendred is the flour;&lt;br&gt;
Whan Zephirus eek with his swete breeth&lt;br&gt;
Inspired hath in every holt and heeth&lt;br&gt;
The tendre croppes, and the yonge sonne&lt;br&gt;
Hath in the Ram his halfe cours y-ronne,&lt;br&gt;
And smale foweles maken melodye,&lt;br&gt;
That slepen al the nyght with open ye,&lt;br&gt;
So priketh hem Natúre in hir corages,&lt;br&gt;
Thanne longen folk to goon on pilgrimages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We expect our adventure to take us 12 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the coming weekends we'll spend our time training by rambling similar
daily distances in the rolling Northamptonshire countryside that surrounds
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Towcester"&gt;Towcester&lt;/a&gt;. We'll also
blog each day of the journey as a memento of our progress - we both suspect our
adventure along Offa's Dyke will be something we'll want to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're at a loose end in the weekends before Easter, get in touch, come
visit and share a walk with us as we prepare... we forgot to mention
there are many wonderful pubs on our local rambles, and we'd love to share
their hospitality with any of our friends who happen to be passing by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy new year for 2022 and here's hoping you find fulfilment and flourish over
the coming 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/25-anniversary-plans/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 20:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Chicken chicken chicken</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/chicken/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A large part of my day job involves reading and writing what folks
optimistically call "technical documentation". It's usually about as much
fun as sticking forks in one's eyes, rubbing a cheese grater up and down one's
nose or reading the complete unabridged works of Ayn Rand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happily, there are examples of great technical documentation (the
&lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/3.2/"&gt;Django project&lt;/a&gt; immediately springs to
mind, and the wonderful folks at
&lt;a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/"&gt;Write the Docs&lt;/a&gt; do amazing work in this
space). But for every example of great documentation, there are many more
incomprehensible, incomplete or incoherent tomes where knowledge goes to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joking aside, quality is clearly a subjective judgement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to make innocuous claims like, "good technical writing is clear,
coherent and engaging; bad documentation is the opposite ~ complicated, chaotic
and opaque". Yet trying to pin down terms like "clear", "coherent" or
"engaging" is a slippery exercise and, ultimately, a matter of personal taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more nuanced approach would say diversity of voices and perspectives is
at play here, and &lt;em&gt;it's important to always keep this in mind&lt;/em&gt;. Every reader
and writer comes to documentation from their own unique point of view and lived
experience. That's why pointing out examples of allegedly poor documentation or
claiming there is a "one true way" to write it is unhelpful. It's disrespectful
of difference, arrogantly presumptuous and there are more supportive and open
minded ways to engage when (inevitable) difficulties arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, feedback that is constructive (offered from a desire to help),
compassionate (aware of another's feelings) and unambigous (specific and
actionable) can highlight
unintended misunderstanding&lt;sup id="chicken-sup"&gt;[&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/chicken/#chicken-edit"&gt;edit&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/sup&gt;. It acknowledges there is a difficulty of some
sort, but does so in a way that encourages writers to reflect, refine and
revise their work. It's also perfectly reasonable for the writer to decline to
change things: perhaps you are not the intended audience, they simply don't
have the time (many docs written for open source projects are created by
volunteers), or they disagree with you and stand by their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let many flowers bloom!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I'm honest, I love to read (even stuff I find difficult or disagreeable ~
like Ayn Rand). It is a connection with others, a source of creative
stimulation and an enlargement of my world. I read because I am curious to
reach out beyond myself and into the lives of others. I love the change and
growth this brings. I also love to write - it is an opportunity for self
reflection, a source of consolation, an invitation to connect, and a rewarding
skill to develop and practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why I write this blog: I enjoy the art of writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The artistry involved in writing is something to celebrate,
cherish and promote. Sadly, and far too often, a focus on form, structure or
process is held up as the best approach to writing technical documentation.
Artistry, taste or style are hardly mentioned, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most documentation looks like what most people think documentation should look
like. There are good reasons why documentation is often organised in the way
that it is, &lt;em&gt;but to follow these conventions is not enough&lt;/em&gt;. Going through the
motions in a structural sense or following a certain form or process is no
guarantee of "quality" (whatever that might mean).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wonderful and humorous example of this is Doug Zongker's "Chicken chicken
chicken".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally
&lt;a href="https://isotropic.org/papers/chicken.pdf"&gt;created in the form of an academic paper&lt;/a&gt;,
and then delivered in the form of a typical academic conference presentation,
Doug created two parodies that focus on process, form and structure at the
expense of meaningful content:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yL_-1d9OSdk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I love how the audience all sound like chickens because they're laughing so
hard.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doug's work got me wondering, would the "chicken" effect work for the tropes
and conventions of a software project? I'm pleased to report
&lt;a href="https://chicken.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;that it does&lt;/a&gt;. It even works
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/chckn/blob/chicken/chicken.py"&gt;for the source code&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/chckn"&gt;Git repository&lt;/a&gt; and the
&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/project/chckn/"&gt;packaging metadata&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "chicken" code highlights what a deeply problematic oversight this
focus on form, structure and process is for technical documentation. Imagine
if teaching the composition of poetry only dealt with structure, rhyme
or rhythm at the expense of meaning, metaphor, story-telling, pacing, symbolism
and expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'd end up with limericks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Chicken chicken chicken chicken,&lt;br&gt;
Chicken chicken chicken chicken,&lt;br&gt;
    Chicken chicken chick,&lt;br&gt;
    Chicken chicken chick,&lt;br&gt;
Chicken chicken chicken chicken.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why this interest in technical documentation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm in the midst of a writing marathon for some of my personal projects (Mu and
CodeGrades). I'm enjoying the opportunity to reflect upon, and work both inside
and outside, the usual conventions for technical documentation. I can't help
but wonder that process, form and structure are best thought of as the servants
of an authentic expression of thoughts, feelings and values through one's own
authorial voice to make a space for the reader to think, engage and learn. If I
am ever disatisfied with my output, it's usually because I've forgotten this
(and I just had to write this blog post to say so!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always with any of my work, I welcome constructive, compassionate and
unambiguous feedback. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="chicken-edit"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT (18th Nov 2021):&lt;/strong&gt; Thank you to the
person (who wishes
to remain anonymous) who reached out to point out that, "constructive,
compassionate and unambigous", are also slippery terms. I've added
clarifications in brackets and would especially like to point out that they
embodied the very best of constructive, compassionate and unambiguous
feedback in their correspondence with me. :-)
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/chicken/#chicken-sup"&gt;Return to text&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/chicken/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On a Scottish Island</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/scottish-island/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;My wife's family have the lease for a 19th century cottage on a small,
otherwise uninhabited, Scottish island. Every year, since Mary and I first
became an item, I have returned to the island for an off-the-grid retreat of
rest, recuperation and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to get onto the island: by boat during high tide, or by
walking over two miles of mudflats at low tide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_from_shore.jpg" alt="The island viewed from the mudflats" title="The island viewed from the mudflats"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The island viewed from the mudflats.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renovating the cottage is my in-law's retirement project and, from
time to time, we and other members of the extended family have helped in
various ways (most recently my family and I carried more than 2000 slate tiles
and other roofing material up the hill from the beach so the roof could be
fully restored by a couple of friendly local builders).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a small traditional whitewashed cottage with two bedrooms, a sitting room,
a kitchen and a bathroom. Running water is pumped into cisterns from an ancient
well, there is no electricity except that provided intermittently by a
generator and the bathroom is unplumbed with a compost toilet and wash basin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside the cottage an old barn is used for storage and contains a sheltered
outdoor room called the "Breeze Inn". In the garden are various home-made seats
around a campfire, a vegetable plot and, to one side, an improvised "hot tub"
made from a large ancient Victorian bath (what a wonderful view!). A fence
secures the property from the island's only other occupants: a herd of sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're free to roam and, while the island is not very big, it offers a
remarkable number of &lt;em&gt;things to do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_mudflats_looking_back.jpg" alt="Looking back towards the mainland from the mudflats" title="Looking back towards the mainland from the mudflats"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking back towards the mainland from the mudflats.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first &lt;em&gt;thing to do&lt;/em&gt;, as always, is to get to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we walked the mudflats and carried our clothes, sleeping bags and a
generous number of books in rucksacks. This has always felt to me like a ritual
of transformation: by crossing the mud we're leaving the real world and all its
interruptions, demands and busy-ness and arriving in a sanctuary of calm, a
refuge for reflection and an undisturbed natural space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking the mudflats allows me to exercise more than just my legs. My senses
are stimulated too. The short walk from the car park to the slipway is along a
verdant tree-lined dappled road. We're accompanied by the distant laughter of
gulls, the piping of oyster catchers and bubbling whistle of curlews. The air
is full of the smell of sweet honeysuckle with an undercurrent of the salty
twang of seaweed. Once barefoot on the mudflats, walking is a warm, wet,
rhythmic sensation that feels like a gentle massage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we sing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we just lose ourselves in silent reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels important to take in this liminal time: a threshold and transitory
in-between space for adjusting to and from island life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_sky_in_water_on_mudflats.jpg" alt="The sky reflected in the water on the mudflats" title="The sky reflected in the water on the mudflats"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The sky reflected in the water on the mudflats.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mudflats are not only (literally) a place of reflection, but also an active
and dynamic world. Birds swoop in to explore the gifts swept in by the tide and
we're not the only ones making journeys: if you look closely, winkles make
tracks over a lunar like landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knows where they're off to..?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_mudflat_journeys.jpg" alt="We're not the only ones journeying on the mudflats" title="We're not the only ones journeying on the mudflats"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;We're not the only ones journeying on the mudflats.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the mudflats is a long mussel bed called the "rack". Sliding into
sandals protects feet from the sharp rocks and mussels that crackle and pop 
when trodden on. To the west of the rack are some medieval fish pools
constructed by monks from a nearby abbey. Apparently they used the island as a
hermitage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the tide is in and the rack is submerged, we're isolated from the mainland
and alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_rack.jpg" alt="The partially submerged mussel bed called the rack" title="The partially submerged mussel bed called the rack"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The partially submerged mussel bed called the rack.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tide and other natural rhythms of the place soon influence the pace of
life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change of the tide is a barely perceptible but constant reminder
that, as Heraclitus would put it, "everything flows" (πάντα ῥεῖ). Yet, while
the tide is a rhythmic constant, each tide brings about a new world:
new flotsam and jetsam emerge from the waves, the sea itself changes colour,
tone and mood, and the shallow river on the mudflats changes course. Once again
Heraclitus provides a suitably watery aphorism, "on those who enter the same
rivers, ever different waters flow" (ποταμοῖσι τοῖσιν αὐτοῖσιν ἐμβαίνουσιν
ἕτερα καὶ ἕτερα ὕδατα ἐπιρρεῖ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a steady tempo of change in the external world leaves time and space to
feel and observe changes within, reflect and simply be with oneself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help with this process I switch off my mobile phone and don't wear a watch ~
preferring to synchronise myself with the world through the ambient events of
island life: passing boats, swimming in the sea, playing games, exploration of
the island, reading and, of course, the weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The island has a microclimate. It might be raining torrents on the mainland,
but the island is still bathed in sunshine. The sky is often a turbulent and
dramatic looking place and another source of steady rhythmic change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often we're richly rewarded simply by looking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_double_rainbow.jpg" alt="A double rainbow over the cottage" title="A double rainbow over the cottage"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A double rainbow over the cottage.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the sunrise and sunset always act as momentous cadences in the day.
Everything feels like it is paying attention during these marvellous
transitions. Memories of these times act as souvenirs to help recall the
feeling of being on the island (especially when frustrated by life back on the
mainland).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_sunset.jpg" alt="Sunset over the mainland" title="Sunset over the mainland"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sunset over the mainland.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of the hill, directly below the cottage is a sandy beach. We
often swim there when the sea makes it safe to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a prominent sign in the cottage's kitchen declares, "by the sea, all worries
wash away", and swimming in the sea is another way of immersing oneself in
nature. It's certainly very cold, but this soon passes and you become sensitive
to swells and waves while paying close attention to the depth or closeness of
jellyfish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it doesn't really matter how you occupy yourself on the island. As
my father-in-law commented, "only the seagulls are here to complain, so don't
worry". I'd add that seagulls always sound as if they're complaining, so it
becomes very easy to ignore them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_beach.jpg" alt="The beach" title="The beach"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The beach.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shore around the island is another source of stimulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many years, and allegedly within living memory, the island was used by
smugglers. There are many caves of various sizes and some of the larger ones
even have shelves cut into the rock. They also make wonderful hiding places for
games of hide-and-seek with younger members of the family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the caves are not just a hiding place for children. Birds, bats and even
the odd marten have been observed to emerge from their depths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_cave.jpg" alt="A view from one of the many caves" title="A view from one of the many caves"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A view from one of the many caves.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microcosms that are rock pools are another source of fascination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the time to observe them requires patience but is often rewarded. A
large lumbering human being who casts a shadow inevitably causes the creatures
in such pools to skedaddle. But quiet repose results in the gradual emergence
of the inhabitants and life resumes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a sort of people watching, but in the wholly alien world of plump red
anemones filtering whatever floats by, crabs scuttling around the place as if
they're late for an important office meeting, the ponderously peripatetic
quests of the many different sized winkles and the nervous darting of small
fish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I stand up and make my presence known, it's as if the inhabitants of the
pools are playing Grandmother's Footsteps (as we do back in the cottage
garden)... everything suddenly stops, statue like, as if nobody wants to be
noticed making a move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_rockpool.jpg" alt="A typical rock pool" title="A typical rock pool"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A typical rock pool.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rocky intertidal zone is also full of hidden treasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closer to the sea one finds all sorts of interesting smelling seaweed and I
often wonder (but always forget to try) if these fruits of the sea are edible
and suitable for cooking. When I once mentioned this to the elderly fisherman
who used to be the lighthouse keeper on the island, he told me the only use
he'd have for the seaweed was as compost for his garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocks and pebbles are an endless source of interest. Often it's fun to
play target practice and throw or skim stones. Other times one finds pebbles
that have been polished in such a way that an interesting shape or colour is
revealed. Sometimes we find strange flotsam or jetsam stuck in the rocks: wood
collected for the fire, a deflated football, bones from a sheep, an old trainer
or a dead gull are typical finds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flinty smell of the rocks, the sounds of birds and waves as well as the
need to retain balance while carefully jumping from rock to rock mean there's a
certain amount of relaxed stimulation and attention required to navigate this
zone of the island - itself a rather wonderful state of mind to inhabit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_rocks.jpg" alt="The rocky intertidal zone" title="The rocky intertidal zone"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The rocky intertidal zone.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be remiss of me not to mention the island's most surprising
inhabitant: an elephant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_elephant.jpg" alt="The elephant" title="The elephant"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The elephant.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be able to make out Mary at the end of the elephant's trunk, and I
hope you get a sense of the size and scale of this wonderful mossy mammoth.
Many a time has been spent imagining ourselves as Scottish mahouts (McHouts?)
journeying out of the sea on the back of such a craggy beast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elephant is also a favourite location for clues during many of the riddle
based treasure hunts we play with younger members of the family...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
My backside is washed twice a day,&lt;br&gt;
With my tail playing in the spray,&lt;br&gt;
  It's certainly not junk,&lt;br&gt;
  Hiding at the end of my trunk,&lt;br&gt;
Could it be a clue? Yes! Hooray!&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that our own children are older I'm pleased to say the island still retains
its magic for them. Projects, games and exploration are the order of the day.
It's a special place for all of us (which makes it all the more special,
because it is a shared specialness private to our family).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are on the island last week, along with our long suffering, faithful
and ever patient dog, Burt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/island_family.jpg" alt="Me and my family on the island" title="Me and my family on the island"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Me and my family on the island.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(All photographs were taken by the author in the week immediately prior to
the publication of this post.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/scottish-island/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Perception, Abstraction and Culture</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-5/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 5)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/"&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/"&gt;part 4&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Treachery_of_Images"&gt;The Treachery of Images&lt;/a&gt;
by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%C3%A9_Magritte"&gt;René Magritte&lt;/a&gt; is a
thought provoking visual brain twist. It shows a pipe, under which is written
in French, "this is not a pipe". Magritte is correct, it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a pipe, but
actually a painting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/treachery_of_images.jpg" alt="This is not a painting"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lacma.org/art/exhibition/magritte-and-contemporary-art-treachery-images" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - educational fair use.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, you're not currently looking at a painting ~ rather, you're
looking at a multitude of pixels, each one acting like a small tile in a huge
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_mosaic"&gt;mosaic&lt;/a&gt; containing millions of
tesserae, each tile being one of many millions of possible colours. If you were
to zoom into the image you'd see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="This is still not a painting" src="https://ntoll.org/images/treachery_of_zoom.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, you're not even looking at an assortment of tessellated pixels! Rather,
your screen actually consists of repeating cells, each in turn split
into red, green and blue (RGB) sections. If you used a magnifying glass
to look at your screen, you'd see something similar to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/treachery_of_pixels.jpg" alt="This is definitely not a painting"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:LCD_pixels_on_Acer_Extensa_5620Z_20090124.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - Licensed under &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en" target="_blank"&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upper half of the image contains blocks of the RGB cells arranged to
display the basic colours: red, green and blue. The lower half contains RGB
cells arranged into two blocks for white and black. By adjusting the amount
of constituent red, green and blue emitted in each individual RGB cell, many
millions of colours can be generated. If you step back from your screen,
squint your eyes and look at the blocks of colour you'll see this effect in
action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For completeness, here's a close-up of one of the individual RGB cells:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An RGB square pixel" src="https://ntoll.org/images/rgb_pixel.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are likely to be several hundred of these minute electrical components
per square-inch of the screen you're using to read this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our perception of what we encounter depends on its scale. Furthermore, what
we
encounter may not be what we see, as René Magritte forces us to acknowledge
with The Treachery of Images (we see a pipe when we're actually encountering a
painting, or pixels, or a screen, and so on). There is a
&lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/phenomenology/" target="_blank"&gt;phenomenological&lt;/a&gt;
aspect to our relationship to things: we can't help but add meaning coloured by
our unique experience of the world. We have a unique and personal
perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies to other encounters with the world too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our perception of time depends on a sense of scale or, perhaps more
accurately, tempo. Each of the following eight images shows a different
snapshot of a stick man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/running_frames.png" alt="Individual frames for a running stick figure animation"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://steemit.com/art/@magiccleatus/magiccleatus-animates-2d-running-stickman-an-animated-template" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - educational fair use.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet if we repeatedly and speedily place them on top of each other, we no longer
see eight individual images, but a single image &lt;strong&gt;in motion&lt;/strong&gt;. In fact, because
we can't help but add meaning, we see a stick man running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Running stick man animation" src="https://ntoll.org/images/running.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scale also effects other senses, such as our perception of sound. Consider the
following musical experiment:
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._9_(Beethoven)"&gt;Beethoven's mighty 9th Symphony&lt;/a&gt;
stretched to last twenty-four hours. By drastically slowing down the tempo (all
other aspects of the piece remaining the same ~ notes, instrumentation, and so
on), it becomes something completely different. It sounds like an ambient
musical experiment by the likes of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Eno"&gt;Brian Eno&lt;/a&gt; and our recognition of
melody, form or harmonic structure disintegrates - even though the original
melody, form and harmonic structures are still present. Such a temporal zoom,
as well as hiding aspects of the music, also reveals new details: I find myself
concentrating on the timbre of the instruments and enjoying the indistinct
transitions between pitches ~ it's like listening through fog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/?listType=playlist&amp;amp;list=PLpJJnhgdCvERiUvfCaVjD0TC8y45MErN5" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are these examples important..?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first post I challenged you to acquire new perspectives about seemingly
everyday things. I called these brain twists because they cause "aha" moments.
Such subjective shifts provide a new, and hopefully deeper, understanding of
what we're encountering or how we relate to something. The external world
remains as it was before, but it is we who have changed perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the previous examples show brain twists are something we do naturally,
even if we're not always aware we're performing such twists. These examples
were carefully chosen because they bring such &lt;em&gt;changes of perspective into
focus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put simply, I'm inviting you to shift &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; perspective about how &lt;em&gt;we change&lt;/em&gt;
perspective. Or, put another way, can you "brain twist" brain twists..?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our capacity to shift perspective due to scale is a fundamental reason &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;
computers appear to work. They work so fast at such a small scale that our
sense of time and space means we don't see our computer re-drawing a static
image on a flat screen made up of millions of RGB cells at a rate of around 64
images per second. Rather, we see this blog post consisting of words, images,
sound and video - things that are meaningful to us. The computer is working at
a completely different scale of time (3 billion instructions a second), space
(running on microscopic electrical components) and with an absence of meaning
(it's just physics relating to electrical circuits). Yet you understand the
words, appreciate the images and engage with the music in this blog post: you
bring your unique culturally informed and meaningful perspective to the human
scale of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the brain twist: such tricks of perspective due to scale &lt;em&gt;also apply to
thinking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider learning to ride a bike ~ it's a challenge because the learner has to
think about lots of different things at once. For instance, turning the pedals,
steering, keeping balance, posture, the brakes and coordinating all these
things together so the beginner cyclist moves safely in the right direction.
When we become proficient at cycling, this bundle of thinking simply becomes
"riding a bike". All the constituent aspects I describe above are subsumed into
a larger concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such diverse dexterous details, through careful practice and familiarity,
become a single named activity. In a sense, we have zoomed out in the scale of
our thinking. Such generalisations are useful as placeholders in further
thoughts... the building blocks of our generalised thinking are at a
&lt;em&gt;different scale&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, I could say "I'm just going to cycle to the shops, do you want me
to get anything for you?". The concept of &lt;em&gt;cycling to the shops&lt;/em&gt; is a place
holder for the rather complicated activity of riding a bike, but whose specific
details are not important for the meaning of the sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, in a computing sense, what we mean by "abstraction".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense of "abstraction", functional units that fulfil a certain role are
organised into larger, or are composed of yet smaller, functional units. Such
units are used together to achieve some valuable end when their relative scale
allows complementary usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because computers process billions of instructions a second, this hierarchy of
abstraction is hidden in the blink of an eye with the end result being
something comprehensible at our human scale (except when things go wrong and
the computer becomes incomprehensible or appears confused...  commonly known as
a bug).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often the skill of the programmer or engineer is to work out the arrangement
and coordination of such abstractions to achieve something meaningful at the
human scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wonderful visual example of such an arrangement and coordination of
abstraction is
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway's_Game_of_Life" target="_blank"&gt;Conway's Game of Life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Game of Life is an automata: rules that define a process for how certain
states of affairs transition to a new state (sound familiar?). In the case of
the Game of Life, the states of affairs describe a huge grid. Each square cell
in the grid can be alive (white) or dead (black). Another way to imagine the
Game of Life is as many parallel tapes lined up on a huge Turing machine with
some squares white (on) and others black (off).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only three rules to work out the next state of affairs, and they are
disarmingly simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any live cell with two or three live neighbours survives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any dead cell with three live neighbours becomes a live cell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All other live cells die in the next generation. Similarly, all other dead
   cells stay dead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels as if nothing of much interest could be made with such a game. But
consider the following Game of Life grid state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="tape life"&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By following the simple rules, the next state of affairs &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; look like
this (pick a white cell from the first grid, follow the rules in your head, and
work out if you agree with this second grid):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="tape life"&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this grid can transition to a further new state of affairs (notice
anything interesting? It's an upside-down version of the first grid, but moved
one cell to the left and one cell up):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="tape life"&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next state of affairs is, unsurprisingly, the same as the second state but
upside down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="tape life"&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A further outcome of such mirroring is that this final state &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; transition
back to the first state of affairs but moved by one cell to the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an arrangement and coordination of cells, combined with the rules of
the Game of Life, create a looping pattern of four steps that always moves in a
single direction until it bumps into another pattern of cells. It appears to
humans as if something is flying across the grid of squares (which is why this
pattern is called
&lt;a href="https://www.conwaylife.com/wiki/Spaceship" target="_blank"&gt;a
spaceship&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skilful combination and arrangement of such small groups of cells in the Game
of Life show how abstraction, scale and perspective interact. In the following
video, as the camera zooms out the tempo of change speeds up to reveal
structures within structures, and something rather amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ra14IjqXS1Y" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar stack of abstraction is required for you to read this blog post
on &lt;em&gt;your computer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My website is created using an easy-to-read-and-write programming language
called &lt;a href="https://python.org" target="_blank"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;. Python is,
itself, written in another programming language called
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C_(programming_language)" target="_blank"&gt;C&lt;/a&gt;.
C is less easy to read but still comprehensible to a trained software engineer.
Yet C has to be
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compiler" target="_blank"&gt;compiled&lt;/a&gt;
for it to work. When C code is compiled, the relatively understandable C code
is translated into instructions written in
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Assembly_language" target="_blank"&gt;assembly language&lt;/a&gt;,
that work in a way that is closer to how the circuitry of the computer works.
But we're not finished yet..! The assembly language is itself translated into
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Machine_code" target="_blank"&gt;machine code&lt;/a&gt;,
a representation of assembly language instructions as binary numbers. This is
the lowest level software engineers tend to go when it comes to zooming-in to
the computer. But the numeric machine code instructions physically stored on
the computer hardware are usually further refined into
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microcode" target="_blank"&gt;microcode&lt;/a&gt;
- a series of circuit-level instructions that describe how the hardware should
behave to complete the computation. Of course, someone will have organised and
designed the millions of transistors and other microscopic components that make
up the (&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/"&gt;Turing complete&lt;/a&gt;) hardware. This
is the level of computing at which electrical engineers, chip designers and,
ultimately, physicists can be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, I didn't have to write everything from scratch. Coders use
&lt;a href="https://pypi.org/" target="_blank"&gt;software libraries&lt;/a&gt; in the same
way a chef may re-use pre-existing recipes. Someone else will have figured out
how to do some valuable task and organised the steps needed to fulfil it into,
say, &lt;a href="https://arrr.readthedocs.io/en/latest/" target="_blank"&gt;a module
of re-usable Python code&lt;/a&gt;. Just like the bundle of thinking needed
to ride a bike becomes subsumed into the concept of cycling, I don't have to
know the implementation details, but can refer to the relevant re-usable code
when it is needed in my own program. Such re-use of existing instructions
happens in all the levels of the computing &lt;em&gt;stack&lt;/em&gt; I describe above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these levels of abstraction are required to get to this fragment of Python:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Hello World in Python" src="https://ntoll.org/images/hello_world.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I come to the end of this exploration of computing, I can't help but feel
there is one final brain twist ~ something missing or yet undiscovered about
our relationship with computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use a musical metaphor, I feel like I've explained why a piano works (the
tuning, acoustic properties, action of the keyboard and hammers) and shown why
this relates to musical theory. Yet I've said nothing about the art or
performance of music, the emotions we feel when we hear or play music, or
that music moves us at a fundamental and human level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are missing the "music" of computers (and we miss it at our peril).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wittgenstein best sums up my feeling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die Menschen, die immerfort ›warum‹ fragen, sind wie die Touristen, die, im
&lt;a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baedeker-Reisef%C3%BChrer"&gt;Bädeker&lt;/a&gt; lesend,
vor einem Gebäude stehen &amp;amp; durch das Lesen der Entstehungsgeschichte etc etc
daran gehindert werden, das Gebäude zu &lt;em&gt;sehen&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(People who are constantly asking 'why' are like tourists, who stand in front
of a building, reading &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baedeker"&gt;Baedeker&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;amp;
through reading about the history of the building's construction etc etc are
prevented from &lt;em&gt;seeing&lt;/em&gt; it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~ Ludwig Wittgenstein, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Culture_and_Value"&gt;Culture and Value&lt;/a&gt; (MS 124:93)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should, rightly, be amazed by the technical marvel of computers; but it
is all too easy to be overwhelmed by, and focus on, the apparent cleverness (or
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rube_Goldberg_machine" target="_blank"&gt;Rube Goldberg&lt;/a&gt;-iness)
of it all. Sadly, in so doing we miss the opportunity for an enlarged, more
creative and expressive encounter with computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers are not just machines for rapidly evaluating logical instructions.
They are a medium through which we share and express our values, culture,
social world and forms of life. They are only valuable because we are able to
create and express things of significance &lt;em&gt;through computers&lt;/em&gt;. Furthermore,
&lt;em&gt;the way we express things with computers&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;that we choose this form of
expression&lt;/em&gt; is also of cultural significance. Like other forms of creative 
endeavour, computers reflect those who make, inhabit and consume in such a
medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers shine when they enlarge us in an affirmative, fulfilling, humane,
creative and expressive way. Yet computing for the sake of computers, with no
regard for culture, is a diminished, inhumane and insular form of ignorance
and, sadly, I can't help but feel disappointed with how, in the mainstream, we
currently use and think of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media is anything but social... it's an efficient advertising laboratory
that turns humanity into lab rats caged in echo chambers of digitally digested
packets of small-mindedness. "Artificial intelligence", "machine learning",
"blockchain" and other such buzzwords are nerdy PR for the clever use of
computers to unsatisfactorily automate human activity (including our latent
prejudices). Computer games are mostly beautiful looking yet formulaic
variations on a theme, target driven and hardly allow a player to express
themselves. Our world is polluted by complicated and unpleasant computerised
gizmos: "intelligent" washing machines, programmable coffee makers, automatic
point-of-sale machines... most of which are banal or frustrating to use. And,
of course, no aspect of life is too small to be "solved" by an app available on
your mobile device (a perculiarly problematic outlook ~ it's as if we're all
broken and need technology to fix us).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a shallow, invasive and unfulfilling world of computing is perhaps
inevitable. It reflects our failure to think creatively while we focus on
automating things in the most trivial, complicated or inconvenient manner. Yet
highlighting such a problematic state of affairs is helpful, for then we can
compensate and re-balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I can't help but feel the missing part of our relationship with
computers is an emphasis on things like culture, contemplation and creativity ~
activities and aspects of our lives that are affirmative, healing, empowering,
raise up our existence or provoke useful reflection and personal growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final brain twist I have for you is to rise above a merely technical view
of computers. I hope you imagine, create and participate in a meaningful,
authentic and engaging culture expressed with and through computers. One in
which computers become a medium for
&lt;a href="https://democracyclub.org.uk/" target="_blank"&gt;affirmative&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://freedom.press/" target="_blank"&gt;liberating&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="http://inbflat.net/" target="_blank"&gt;expressive&lt;/a&gt;
activities that enlarge ourselves, our world and our place in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, let's &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/on-being-together"&gt;together&lt;/a&gt; compose the
oft-missing "music" of computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, we are &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/thought-in-motion/"&gt;only just getting started&lt;/a&gt; with
these strange instruments of automation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-5/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Automated Rule Following Machines</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 4)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/"&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-5/"&gt;part 5&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What follows isn't so much a brain twist, as an extended make-pretend that
points the way to what a computer is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a strange looking contraption sitting before you on a table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It consists of an exceptionally long reel-to-reel tape that passes through an
electro-mechanical device of some sort. The tape is subdivided into square
"frames". Some of the squares contain symbols, others are empty. As it
operates, the tape moves through the device both to the left or to the right,
like a badly behaved cinema projector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/turing_machine.jpg" alt="A Turing Machine"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Turing_Machine_Model_Davey_2012.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
  - Licensed under
  &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en" target="_blank"&gt;CC BY 3.0&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The "head" (where the tape passes through the device) covers exactly one
square's worth of the tape. There's a flash of light from the head when a new
square is completely contained therein. Sometimes this is followed by a
clicking sound. When the click is heard the symbol in the square is changed:
it's either different or completely rubbed out. Then the tape moves to the left
or right to a new square before continuing its strange flashing and clicking
operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the front of the machine is a little window. The window is labelled
"&lt;code&gt;STATE&lt;/code&gt;" and contains a number that changes when each square is "processed" by
the head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while the machine comes to a stop. The state window contains the number
0 (zero). By the head, on the tape, are a sequence of squares containing some
familiar looking symbols:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="tape"&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;H&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;O&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt; &lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;W&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;O&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;L&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two other objects are on the table. On one side of the contraption is a black
and white photograph of a thoughtful looking man with an old fashioned side
parting and &lt;em&gt;enigmatic&lt;/em&gt; smile, sitting in a sturdy deck chair. On the other is
a thick ring-bound pile of paper whose title you can just make out:
"Instructions".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions listed on the front page consist of just four rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the machine to state "1".&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read the symbol in the current frame on the tape.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given the current state of the machine and the symbol read from the
  current frame, look up what to do next. "What to do next" is defined by three
  transitions:

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Change to a new numbered state.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Replace or delete the symbol in the current frame.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Move the tape by some number of frames to the left or the right.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the new state is "0" then stop, otherwise resume from rule 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the many pages that follow is a single huge table entitled "What to do
next". It contains thousands of entries under the same five columns, and all
look something like these extracts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;CURRENT STATE&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;HEAD READ&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;➔&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;NEXT STATE&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;HEAD WRITE&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;MOVE TAPE&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;"A"&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;785&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;"5"&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1L&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;" "&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;657&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;"!"&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;86R&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;"#"&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;657&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;"!"&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;86R&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;...&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1023&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;"#"&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1020&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;" "&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;23R&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note, just above the table, explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each combination of the "CURRENT STATE" and "HEAD READ" values is unique.
There is one row for each possible combination. Identify the row that
corresponds to the current state of affairs. The new state of affairs is
defined by the "NEXT STATE", "HEAD WRITE" and "MOVE TAPE" values on the same
row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the first line of the extract means that if the machine is in state
&lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt; and the head reads the symbol &lt;em&gt;"A"&lt;/em&gt; then the next state is &lt;em&gt;785&lt;/em&gt;, the
symbol &lt;em&gt;"5"&lt;/em&gt; should be written to the current square, and the tape should
move &lt;em&gt;1 square to the left&lt;/em&gt;. The final line of the extract means that if the
machine is in state &lt;em&gt;1023&lt;/em&gt; and the head reads the symbol &lt;em&gt;"#"&lt;/em&gt; then the next
state is &lt;em&gt;1020&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;symbol should be deleted from the current square&lt;/em&gt; and
the tape should move &lt;em&gt;23 squares to the right&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is propositional logic..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a table of conditionals whose two premises (the "CURRENT STATE" and
"HEAD READ" values) are conjuncted (logical &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt;) to identify what the
resulting behaviour should be (the "NEXT STATE", "HEAD WRITE", and "MOVE TAPE"
values). &lt;code&gt;IF&lt;/code&gt; the state is &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; the value read by the head is &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;code&gt;THEN&lt;/code&gt; go to the specified &lt;em&gt;next state&lt;/em&gt;, write &lt;em&gt;such-and-such&lt;/em&gt; to the tape and
move the tape by &lt;em&gt;however many squares in a certain direction&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look carefully, hidden within the extract are also disjunctions (logical
&lt;code&gt;OR&lt;/code&gt;). The middle two lines (for state &lt;em&gt;516&lt;/em&gt;) have the same state and outcome,
but different symbols read from the head. This is the same as checking &lt;code&gt;IF&lt;/code&gt;
(the state is &lt;em&gt;516&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; the head reading is &lt;em&gt;empty&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;code&gt;OR&lt;/code&gt; (the state is &lt;em&gt;516&lt;/em&gt;
AND the head reading is &lt;em&gt;"#"&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;code&gt;THEN&lt;/code&gt; the next state is &lt;em&gt;657&lt;/em&gt;, write &lt;em&gt;"!"&lt;/em&gt; to
the tape and the tape should move &lt;em&gt;86 squares to the right&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is the purpose of this machine? What does it do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It follows the four rules, that start the instruction manual, to repeatedly
perform the logical steps defined in the "What to do next" table. The steps in
the table react to and change the state of the symbols on the tape in order
to arrive at a desired end result. What that end result is depends upon what's
on the tape when the machine is switched on and how the steps in the table
interact with that starting state and subsequent states of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, given a certain "what to do next" table, a starting state and
some input on the tape, it computes a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;strong&gt;a computer!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you had the instructions, a copy of the table, a physical tape, a pencil and
an eraser you might follow the rules from the start state (state &lt;em&gt;1&lt;/em&gt;) until the
end state (state &lt;em&gt;0&lt;/em&gt;) was achieved. But the machine would do it much faster and
wouldn't get tired, bored or make mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A cardboard computer" src="https://ntoll.org/images/cardboard_computer.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process might feel familiar: deliberately precise rules describe how,
given certain states of affairs, such and such things must happen. States of
affairs unambiguously describe how things are in the world. For example, "the
machine is in state 284 and the current square on the tape contains an &lt;code&gt;H&lt;/code&gt;".
When I say that such and such must happen, I mean clear and unambiguous
instructions describe how the machine proceeds given a certain state of
affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how I described the game of Snap &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1#rules_of_snap"&gt;in the first article&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that computing a result is not that different to playing a
children's game. Computing a result is the same as following a set of
instructions for changing states of affairs. Such unambiguous instructions
are called &lt;em&gt;algorithms&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the rules in the "what to do next" table are logical, they can be 
represented by the sorts of electrical circuitry described
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3"&gt;in the previous post&lt;/a&gt;. Such circuitry receives input
signals from the components in the head, and controls other components such as
the motors that control the tape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this machine to do anything meaningful, someone will have carefully
crafted the "what to do next" rules so the symbols on the tape when the machine
is switched on in state 1, are transformed into a completely-new-yet-useful
set of symbols when the machine achieves state 0. The algorithm is defined by
the "what to do next" rules written in the table and encoded in the
circuitry. The machine transitions from state 1 and what may be found on the
tape at that moment, via a huge number of intervening states, to state 0 and a
computed result written on the tape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/alan_turing.jpg" alt="Alan Turing"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Alan_Turing_az_1930-as_%C3%A9vekben.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
  - this image is in the
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain" target="_blank"&gt;public domain&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I've described is a Turing machine. Such an imaginary device was invented
by the British mathematician Alan Turing (the chap in the photograph). It turns
out that anything that can be computed by a set of instructions that manipulate
symbols (the algorithm), can be computed by a Turing machine. Anything that
works in a way that is equivalent to a Turing machine is described as Turing
complete because it, too, is able to compute outcomes from an algorithm. To be
Turing complete is to be a programmable computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turing
&lt;a href="https://londmathsoc.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1112/plms/s2-42.1.230" target="_blank"&gt;explained how computation works&lt;/a&gt;
by describing his machine. If you create something that can work like a Turing
machine then you have also created a computer. You don't have to prove your
computer is complete, because Turing already did that for you. This equivalence
of capability is &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we learn about Turing machines: they make it
clear what it is to be a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many variations on a Turing machine. The one I've described could be
simplified in a couple of ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The machine could use multiple tapes with multiple heads rather than a
   single tape and a single head. The information used to make a computation
   is available in concurrent squares on several tapes, rather than as a
   sequence of individual values on one single tape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The alphabet of symbols that could be written to or read from the tape
   need only consist of two symbols: one representing "on", and the other
   representing "off". Put simply, information is represented in a binary
   fashion as shown in the following illustration (white or "1" is on, black or
   "0" is off).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;table class="tape"&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td class="on"&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;
            &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these changes wouldn't make the machine any more powerful than the one
I've described, but they may make the machine easier to build and program. The
important property of the machine is its Turing completeness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computer you're using to read this article obviously works in a completely
different way to the seemingly ramshackle contraption I describe. While there
is no tape or head inside your computing device, there are transistors
etched into silicon chips that react to and change the state of values stored
in memory, billions of times a second. The chips connect to other parts of your
device via input/output pins. The other parts of your device, connected via
specialist hardware, might include things like a screen, keyboard, mouse,
speaker or microphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as a Turing machine iterates over the same cycle of reading from the head,
writing to the tape and transitioning to a new state, a silicon based chip,
synchronised by a clock, carries out a similar iterative cycle of work one
instruction after another. In fact, the clock speed of your machine's CPU tells
you how many instructions the chip will carry out each second (for instance, a
3Ghz chip will manage 3 billion instructions a second).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in how an actual chip behaves,
&lt;a href="http://www.visual6502.org/sim/varm/armgl.html" target="_blank"&gt;this
link takes you to a simulation of an ARM1 chip&lt;/a&gt; -- a forerunner to those
that run your mobile phone. Click on the "play" button
(&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/play.png" target="_blank" style="display: inline;vertical-align: middle;"&gt;)
to watch the chip "operate". It's possible to zoom in and out, move around,
speed up or slow down the clock and see how individual transistors are
connected to and interact with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a computer is simply something that is Turing complete, why is it that we're
able to use such devices to read and write words, hear music, draw pictures,
watch videos and all the other meaningful stuff for which we find computers so
useful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer relates to how we perceive things, our talent for abstraction and
our cultural context. The next and final post will explore these concepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 07:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Representation</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 3)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/"&gt;part 4&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-5/"&gt;part 5&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to imagine one thing representing another. We do this all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in the UK the Royal Standard always flies from buildings
containing the monarch. This flag is understood to represent the Queen's
presence and somebody ensures it is flown at the right moment from the
buildings she visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/royal_standard.jpg" alt="The Royal Standard over Buckingham Palace"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Buckingham_Palace_-_Royal_Standard.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
  - Licensed under
  &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en" target="_blank"&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a twist...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the Royal Standard, a light on top of a building's flag pole could
represent the Queen's presence. If it were on, she was present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice there are two possible states for the Queen (she's either present or
not), this is mirrored by the two possible states for the light (it is either
illuminated or not), and we are playing along in a sort of game that provides
meaning for such a representation (we understand that the Queen is present if
the light is illuminated, just like we do when we see the flying of the Royal
Standard). One thing (a light) is representing something else (the Queen's
presence).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a device could be built using the circuit shown in the diagram below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Simple switch circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/simple_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the top is the symbol representing a battery that supplies current for
the other components. Lines show how the battery and other components connect.
The circle containing a cross represents a bulb and the gap created by the line
veering off at an angle represents a switch. In the following photograph the
real-world components, shown next to their symbols, connect to form the
circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Electrical components" src="https://ntoll.org/images/components.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch can be in two possible states: on (creating a circuit so current
moves through the components, thus lighting the bulb) or off (where the circuit
is broken, stopping the current and extinguishing the bulb).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a royal brain twist for you: can you think of something else that deals
with only two possible states?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought, "propositional logic" then you deserve a knighthood!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two possible states of the circuit, as controlled by the switch, mirrors
the two possible states encountered in propositional logic: on/true and
off/false. We could play along with the logical game and say that the circuit
represents the truth value of the proposition, "the Queen is present".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another royal brain twist: it's also possible to make simple circuits
that mimic the logical operations found in propositional logic ("and", "or",
"not" and all the rest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By re-arranging the physical components of the circuit, from a logical point of
view, the illuminated bulb could represent the presence of both the Queen
and/or her hier, the Prince of Wales:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Queen is present &lt;em&gt;AND&lt;/em&gt; the Prince of Wales is present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Queen is present &lt;em&gt;OR&lt;/em&gt; the Prince of Wales is present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, propositional logic doesn't care about the meaning of the
propositions ("the Queen is present", "the Prince of Wales is present"), so
the circuits' behaviour could be generalised to represent "A and B" or
"A or B".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the diagram for the "and" circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="And circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/and_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two switches are labelled to show how they represent the propositions "A"
and "B". Because of the &lt;strong&gt;consecutive&lt;/strong&gt; arrangement of the switches, the states
of the switches and the resulting behaviour of the bulb match the truth table
for "and": if both switches are on, then the bulb is on (representing "true"),
otherwise, in all other combination of switch states, the bulb is off
(representing "false").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the diagram for the "or" circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Or circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/or_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, the &lt;strong&gt;parallel&lt;/strong&gt; arrangement of the switches causes the circuit
to mirror the truth table for the logical "or" operation. If only one (or both)
of the switches are on, then the bulb is on, otherwise, when both switches are
off, the bulb is off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circuit for "not" is slightly different and allows me to introduce a new
(but important) electrical component: the &lt;em&gt;transistor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transistors control flow of electrical current with three connections called
"gate", "source" and "drain". Electrical current flows between "source" and
"drain" only if current is also applied to the "gate" connection. Rather than
controlling the flow of current with a switch operated by a person, a
transistor is controlled by another electrical component via the "gate".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transistors work because they're made from two different types of silicon, a
material that only conducts electricity under certain conditions (which is why
it's called a semi-conductor). The silicon is mixed with certain impurities to
create p-type and n-type silicon. In the diagram below the
&lt;span style="color: #586796;"&gt;p-type silicon is shown in blue&lt;/span&gt;,
the &lt;span style="color: #b03030;"&gt;n-type silicon in red&lt;/span&gt;
and the gate connection in green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Transistor off" src="https://ntoll.org/images/transistor_off_as_diagram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar way to how "and" and "or" circuits behave as a result of the
physical arrangement of their components, the cleverness of transistors comes
about because of how the p-type and n-type parts are physically arranged. The
"source" terminal is connected to an n-type layer (in red, on the left of the
diagram), the "gate" (in green) to the p-type barrier layer (in blue) and
"drain" to another n-type layer (in red, on the right of the diagram).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In very simplistic terms, if a voltage is applied to p-type silicon via the
"gate" connection, it behaves like n-type silicon. When in this state it is no
longer an insulating barrier between the "source" and "drain" and electricity
can flow. This is shown in the diagram below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Transistor on" src="https://ntoll.org/images/transistor_on_as_diagram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transistors come in many shapes and sizes, but are most common as
extraordinarily small components etched onto silicon (i.e. microchips). The
image below was taken by an electron microscope and shows a transistor on a
microchip with the parts labelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/transistor_on_chip.png" alt="A Transistor on a microchip"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-is-the-transistor-so-crucial-to-computers-and-what-role-does-it-play-in-computing" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - educational fair use.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the "not" circuit: remember that electricity will always flow the
shortest way to "ground" (for instance via a lightning rod). The following
(very simplified) circuit diagram shows how a transistor and ground is used to
make something that behaves like a logical "not".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transistor is represented by a circle pierced by three lines. The source is
represented by the line entering the circle at the 1 o'clock position, the
drain by the line at the 5 o'clock position and the gate by the line at 9
o'clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Not circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/not_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the left, the button labelled "A", attached to the gate, is off
(representing false) so current is unable to pass through the transistor to
ground. As a result, the electrical current (in red) flows through the lamp to
illuminate it (representing true). On the right, the button is on (in green,
representing voltage applied to the transistor's gate). The current is able
to flow through the transistor from the source to the drain and then to
ground (so no current flows to the bulb to illuminate it). The red arrows make
it clear how the current flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the lamp is always in the opposite logical state to the switch and
the circuit mirrors the behaviour of a logical "not". If the switch is off,
the light is on and if the switch is on, the light is off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important brain twist is understanding that we can design physical systems
(i.e. electrical circuits) that &lt;em&gt;appear to behave as logical ones&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another seemingly contradictory brain twist is to &lt;em&gt;remove "logic" from any
explanation of the circuits&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a scientific point of view of the circuit, an observer can only describe
physical properties and behaviours in terms of electrical current, the
mechanical behaviour of switches, the incandescent properties of filament and
the electrochemical nature of batteries and transistors. You won't find any
formal rules of propositional logic here, nor meaning ascribed to physical
states of affairs. The scientific view of the circuit is the "how" of the
circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet if we agree the on/off states of the switches represent the true/false
values of propositions "A" and "B" and the on/off status of the light
represents a resulting logical outcome (true/false) then the behaviour of the
first circuit undoubtedly mirrors the truth table for "and". Remember, it's not
logic that makes the circuit behave in this way (it's actually physics!), but
because we play along in a game where physical states mirror and thus
accurately represent logical ones, then the circuit acquires an additional
layer of meaning in terms of the rules of logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the "why" of the logical circuit: a human is needed to understand what
the behaviour of a physical object apparently represents. Without the
meaningful human-ascribed behaviour there is just an object described by
physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another instance of this phenomenon: there is no physical law described
by science that explains why green means "go" and red means "stop" at traffic
lights - yet the traffic lights are very much a physical system that can be
described by science. If meaning is involved, then humans and their cultural
norms are needed to make sense of it to explain what it represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teleology (using meaningful purpose or design to explain phenomena) isn't a
part of the "how" of physics-based descriptions of the world - yet humans
commonly retrofit purpose or design to describe physical systems that exhibit
behaviour appearing to represent something meaningful, such as logical
operations or traffic lights. The brain twist is to realise where and when such
human interventions assign meaning to the physical world, such as in the case
of the logic circuits I've described.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine an arrangement of many transistor-based circuits (representing various
logical operations), chained together so the output of one circuit provides the
input to the next. This yet-more-complicated arrangement of logical circuits
defines the meaningful behaviour of a device. Such a device, like its
constituent logical circuits, connects to the outside world via inputs and
outputs and has a strange capability: to change its own state in order to store
and process information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next post will explore such a machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Movements of Thought</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/"&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/"&gt;part 4&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-5/"&gt;part 5&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as one can describe rules for a card game, it is possible to describe
rules for thinking: rules for movement of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the study of &lt;em&gt;Logic&lt;/em&gt;, and using these rules is called &lt;em&gt;reasoning&lt;/em&gt;.
Reasoning with logical rules allows others, who know such rules, to follow the
movements of thought that brought you to a certain conclusion. Furthermore,
because there are rules, it's possible to notice when they're ignored or used
incorrectly (when movements of thought don't make logical sense).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many types of logic, but the one we're going to examine is called
propositional (or sentential, or boolean) logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Propositional" and "sentential" are just descriptive names for a type of
logic that deals with forming sentences by combining propositions. In logic,
&lt;em&gt;propositions make assertions that are either true or false&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Boole" target="_blank"&gt;George
Boole&lt;/a&gt; (1815-1864), shown below, invented a system of mathematical algebra
that works like propositional logic (it also deals with values that are either
true or false) and so the term "boolean" is often used synonymously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/boole.png" alt="George Boole"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Portrait_of_George_Boole.png" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
  - this image is in the
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain" target="_blank"&gt;public domain&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a contrived example of a sentence in propositional logic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If it is sunny and I am wearing a thick coat, then I am hot."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to some important aspects of this sentence that
may not, at first, appear obvious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It contains two propositions called &lt;em&gt;premises&lt;/em&gt; ("it is sunny" and "I am
  wearing a thick coat"). Premises make assertions about &lt;em&gt;states of affairs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ends with a &lt;em&gt;conclusion&lt;/em&gt; ("I am hot"). A conclusion is a &lt;em&gt;proposition that
  depends upon the premises&lt;/em&gt; in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sentence is in the form of a &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;/em&gt; ("if [premises], then
  [conclusion]"). A conditional is a rule saying that if its premises are true
  then the conclusion &lt;strong&gt;must be true&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The premises are related to each other by a &lt;em&gt;logical operator&lt;/em&gt; called a
  &lt;em&gt;conjunction&lt;/em&gt; ("and"). This is another rule: if the related premises are
  evaluated together, &lt;strong&gt;collectively they are true only if all of them are
  true&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Propositional logic describes the rules of a "game" to construct sentences that
make logical sense. Playing by the rules of logic forces everyone to reach the
same inevitable conclusion: if we accept that the premises are true (it is
sunny and I am wearing a coat) propositional logic dictates the conclusion must
be true (I am hot). The object of propositional logic is to use the rules to
evaluate (work out) if a sentence is true or false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the brain twist: propositional logic doesn't care about meaning. The
important logical aspects of the example above don't concern my state in the
real world (which is why the sentence sounds slightly odd). &lt;em&gt;Propositional
logic only cares about truth and how propositions fit together&lt;/em&gt;. I could
revise the example to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If A and B then C."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter what &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt; stand for nor what they may mean -- from
the perspective of propositional logic all that matters is there are two
conjuncted premises (A and B) and a conclusion (C) expressed in a conditional
(if ... then ...). If one or both of the premises is false, then the
conclusion must also be false. Why? Because the logical rules pertaining to
conditionals and conjunctions (&lt;em&gt;and nothing else outside those rules&lt;/em&gt;) make it
that way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brain twist is divorcing yourself from meaning -- just concern yourself
with truth values of the propositions, the structure of the sentence and
following the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way the
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1#rules_of_snap"&gt;rules of Snap explain what
must happen&lt;/a&gt;, given card
related states of affairs, so the rules of propositional logic do the same with
propositions and sentences. The rules of Snap don't care what the specific
values of cards are, just that such values may match. Similarly, propositional
logic doesn't care what the specific meanings of the propositions may be, only
that such propositions connect in a sentence that can be evaluated with rules
dealing in just two possible states: &lt;strong&gt;true&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to express the rules that govern such logical operations
for connecting propositions is with a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth_table" target="_blank"&gt;truth
table&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's the definition of "and" (conjunction):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt; A | B | A and B
----------------
 F | F |    F
 F | T |    F
 T | F |    F
 T | T |    T
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you see how it works?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two columns represent propositions labelled "A" and "B". The third
column represents the outcome of the "and" operation, given the values of "A"
and "B" in the first two columns. Each possible combination of truth value for
"A" and "B" is enumerated as a row with the resulting truth value for the "and"
operation in the third column. It's a simple tabular way to express the rules
of propositional logic. If you had any doubt how "and" (conjunction) worked,
you'd find the definitive answer in this truth table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, take the first row: if propositions "A" and "B" are both false
(as expressed in the first two columns), then the outcome for this rule
(expressed in the third column) &lt;strong&gt;must be false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another truth table that defines the rule for the logical operation
called "or" (disjunction):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt; A | B | A or B
---------------
 F | F |   F
 F | T |   T
 T | F |   T
 T | T |   T
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's pretend that "A" is false but "B" is true. How would you evaluate the
truth value of "A or B"? Is it true or false?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that "A or B" is true. Why? Because the second row tells us so:
the "A" column is false, the "B" column is true so the result, expressed in the
third column, is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's one final truth table. It's a bit different to the other two since it
only works on a single proposition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt; A | not A
----------
 T |   F
 F |   T
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's easy to see what the "not" (negation) operation does to a proposition: it
flips its truth value so false becomes true, and true becomes false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these logical operations have familiar names ("and", "or" and "not")
that &lt;strong&gt;appear to relate to how they work&lt;/strong&gt;, it is the truth table
&lt;strong&gt;and only the truth table&lt;/strong&gt; that defines how they behave in
propositional logic, not any similarity to how we may use such words in
everyday English. There are further rules, expressed as truth tables, for
connecting propositions that you may wish to look into. They are
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exclusive_or" target="_blank"&gt;XOR&lt;/a&gt;
(eXclusive OR),
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheffer_stroke" target="_blank"&gt;NAND&lt;/a&gt;
(Not AND),
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_NOR" target="_blank"&gt;NOR&lt;/a&gt;
(Not OR) and
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_equality" target="_blank"&gt;XNOR&lt;/a&gt;
(eXclusive Not OR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logical puzzles become fun when you combine such logical operations to build
more complicated structures. Take for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A and B) or (C or not D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've put parentheses ("&lt;code&gt;(&lt;/code&gt;" and "&lt;code&gt;)&lt;/code&gt;") around propositions so you can see how they
relate to the logical operators (the &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;). If we pretend all
the propositions represented by letters are false, what is the overall truth
value of the sentence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find the answer we play the logical "game" in the same way we would with
Snap: we follow the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start by evaluating the operators within the parentheses. If we replace the
propositions "A" and "B" with their truth values (remember, all the
propositions are false), we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(false and false) or (C or not D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the rule set out in the truth table for "and", the propositions in the
first parentheses evaluate to false. Here's how the sentence looks as a
result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;false or (C or not D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the "or" in the remaining parentheses we should first evaluate the
"not" operator to find the truth value of the proposition on the right. If "D"
is false, then the truth table for "not" tells us that "not D" must evaluate to
true. Since "C" is false, the sentence looks like this when "C" and "not D" are
replaced by their truth values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;false or (false or true)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth table for "or", when applied to values in the remaining parentheses
tells us that if one of the propositions is true, then the "or" operation must
evaluate to true, giving us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;false or true&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-using this rule to evaluate the remaining "or" operation gives the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;true&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;only way&lt;/strong&gt; to solve such logical puzzles is by following the inevitable
steps dictated by the rules. That's &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; logic works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; does logic work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the same reason why the game of Snap works: we modify our behaviour to
follow unambiguous rules because we want to determine the truth of sentences in
propositional logic (the aim of playing this sort of logic game). Furthermore,
by pretending propositions represent states of affairs in the real world, we
can use logic to describe and, in a sense, encode aspects of the real world.
For instance, we could describe the rules of Snap &lt;em&gt;with logic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is logic useful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because logic clearly and unambiguously describes the relationships between
states of affairs (premises), and allows us to take action given a resulting
truth value. Consider, for example, this conditional statement: &lt;code&gt;IF&lt;/code&gt; the card
on top of stack A is an ace &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; the card on top of stack B is an ace, &lt;code&gt;THEN&lt;/code&gt;
shout "SNAP!". Logic describes the movement of thought needed to participate in
the card game (or any other useful structured activity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a final "brain twist" for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Logic provides an inevitable, almost mechanical framework for organising and
describing movements of thought then we should be able to build machines to
work with such seemingly mechanical logical rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that we can, and describing such machines is the next step in
describing why computers work!&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Computers Work: An Introduction to Following Rules</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 1)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/"&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-4/"&gt;part 4&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-5/"&gt;part 5&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first of five short blog posts exploring &lt;em&gt;why computers work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to present a friendly introductory overview for laypeople, from zero
to Turing machines, automata, abstraction and more. My aim is conciseness and
clarity, so I've necessarily missed out, glossed over and simplified things.
There are plenty of more advanced resources online should you wish to
investigate this subject further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I hope to stimulate your thinking about computers by creating
a place to explore ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy these articles and, as always, I love getting constructive
feedback &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/contact"&gt;via email&lt;/a&gt;. Unless otherwise stated, all images and
diagrams were created by the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="section_break"&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;αἰὼν παῖς ἐστι παίζων, πεσσεύων· παιδὸς ἡ βασιληίη.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The universe is a child's game. A child's kingdom.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~ &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heraclitus/"&gt;Heraclitus&lt;/a&gt; (Fragment B52)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers are ubiquitous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They touch all aspects of our lives, from mediating our social interactions to
modelling aspects of our culture and managing the everyday infrastructure of
society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, computers are interesting and, understandably, folks want to
know &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; the machines that automate and control so much of our world work.
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tpIctyqH29Q" target="_blank"&gt;This is
a typical response&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm going to take a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to explore &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; computers work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's the difference?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answers to "how?" questions tell us what method or steps make something happen.
In contrast, the answers to "why?" questions describe what makes something
possible ~ an opportunity to encounter a more fundamental perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the difference between a car mechanic who may understand &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; an engine
works (so they can fix broken engines), and a mechanical engineer who
understands the physics and chemistry relating to &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; engines work (so they
can improve the design of engines). Knowing how something works means your
frame of reference is &lt;em&gt;within the system&lt;/em&gt;, whereas if you understand why
something works you're not bound by existing products, solutions or cultural
practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, cultivating an understanding of why something is possible is
an invitation for playful creativity, fearless exploration and careful
refinement of alternatives to the current crop of answers to "how?". It is an
opportunity to enlarge and change our world ~ a form of intellectual
empowerment and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; is good, but understanding &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the scene suitably set, to start our journey, we'll learn all about...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Following Rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how to play the children's card game, Snap?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Bear with me, I promise it'll be worth it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a standard deck of cards, the aim is to win all the cards by &lt;em&gt;taking
turns to play&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's follow along as siblings Penelope (11), Sam (8) and Will (5) play a game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Penelope (for no other reason than she's the oldest) acts as dealer. She
shuffles the deck of cards so they're in a random order and deals them, face
down and in equal quantity, to each player until there are none left to deal.
This is the starting state from which all games of Snap begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam, the player to the left of the dealer, takes the first turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players take a turn by moving the top card from their face-down stack onto the
top of an adjacent stack of face-up cards, so the newly moved card is also
facing up. Since this is Sam's first turn, the face-up stack doesn't exist,
so a new stack is created with Sam's first face-up card taken from his pile of
face-down cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So ends Sam's turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/snap.jpg" alt="A game of Snap!"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Snap" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - From
  &lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com" target="_blank"&gt;WikiHow&lt;/a&gt; and licensed
  under
  &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/deed.en" target="_blank"&gt;CC BY-NC-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next player to the left, William, takes his turn in a similar fashion and
so the game continues from one player to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while Sam shouts "SNAP". He's noticed that two face-up cards on top of
different stacks have the same value (for example, two aces are visible on top
of Penelope and Will's stacks). Since he was first to shout "SNAP" he wins all
the cards in the matching stacks of cards. He gleefully scoops up all the cards
in the face-up stacks belonging to Penelope and Will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play continues to the left of the player who turned up the matching card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few moments later Penelope shouts "SNAP". But there is a problem: there are
no matching face-up cards! William points this out to Penelope and reminds her
she has to pay a forfeit by giving one card to each of the other players from
her face-down stack. Sam and Will get a card each and Penelope is two cards
down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the game Sam has the most cards. Will and Penelope have less
with only a few cards difference between the quantities in their face-down
stacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are hotting up and the three children become more excited: when two
matching face-up cards appear again all three of them shout "SNAP" at the same
time. Since nobody can claim to have shouted "SNAP" first, and to avoid
arguments, both the matching stacks are placed in the middle and added to the
"Snap pool". When "SNAP" is next called unambiguously and correctly, the winner
will get both the matching stacks and any cards in the "Snap pool". The stakes
have suddenly got higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things quieten down for a few rounds until Penelope runs out of face-down cards
to put onto her face-up stack. At this point she simply flips over her face-up
stack and it becomes her face-down stack. Play continues as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after a few more calls of "SNAP", Penelope finds that she's run out
of cards and so out of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam and Will play together until, through luck and fast reactions, Sam finds
himself with all the cards and he's declared the winner of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's how you play Snap..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="rules_of_snap"&gt;The rules illustrated in this deliberately precise story describe
&lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;, given certain states of affairs, such-and-such things must
happen. States of affairs unambiguously describe how things are in the world.
For example, "there are two stacks of face-up cards whose top cards are of
matching value". When I describe how such-and-such must happen, I mean clear
and unambiguous instructions describe &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; play proceeds given a
certain state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, this is &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the game of Snap is played.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is Snap played?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because, in addition to knowing the rules, we understand that playing the game
of Snap means modifying one's behaviour to follow these rules. If everyone
modifies their behaviour in accordance with the rules then folks can play
together. Obviously, we don't explain card games in such a formal manner to
very young children. But, as my description shows, children discover it's lots
of fun to informally learn and skilfully follow rules that bring about
exciting situations in games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing how to play Snap is analogous to knowing how computers work. Looking
beyond the rules of Snap to appreciate that human behaviour and enjoyment
motivates people to follow the rules of the game, shows us &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; Snap is
played. This insight may also inspire us to invent new games. Perhaps we become
inspired to explore further aspects of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milgram_experiment" target="_blank"&gt;human behaviour relating to following rules&lt;/a&gt;,
or we may even
&lt;a href="https://theoryoffun.com/" target="_blank"&gt;reflect upon the nature of play or games&lt;/a&gt;.
In any case, exploring &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; provides a
fascinating perspective from outside the system (of Snap, in this case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to achieve an analogous enlargement of perspective beyond &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;
computers work in order to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; computers work. Only by acquiring a
perspective outside current norms can we possibly hope to invent or improve
technology and explore the nature and use of such devices. The alternative is
churn and recycling of existing ideas within the current system ~ a situation
that stifles innovation or positive change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computing-related rules and states of affairs I'm going to describe are not
much more complicated than the game of Snap explained above. However, what
follows may include a few &lt;em&gt;brain twists&lt;/em&gt; where I expect you to use your
imagination to see things in a seemingly unusual or unintuitive way! I'm
challenging you to acquire a new perspective about seemingly everyday things.
The external world remains as it was before, but you will have changed. Your
newly acquired perspective reveals a deeper understanding of what you're
observing and why this makes computing possible. It's fun and can result in
rather pleasant "aha" moments (if you were a cartoon character, it's that
feeling you get when a lightbulb appears above your head).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next chapter in our story is a beautiful brain twist: to think about
thinking...&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 07:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Social Media Hermit</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/social-media-hermit/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have deleted my Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I no longer use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social media isn't fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are better ways to connect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retaining my account feels hypocritical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, that's all there is to it (and it feels good).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter encourages infantile, reactionary and shallow discourse. What do you
expect from a technology that enforces a 280 character limit and trains us to
read in bite size chunks? Twitter may as well enforce &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak"&gt;other arbitrary
limitations&lt;/a&gt;, for example the exclusive
use of monosyllabic words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want no part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If folks genuinely want to connect with me, they'll be in touch (as I will be
with them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/social-media-hermit/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 07:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>