<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ntoll.org</title><link>https://ntoll.org/</link><description>Everything I say is false...</description><atom:link href="https://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:ntoll@ntoll.org"&gt;Nicholas H.Tollervey&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 07:01:09 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Representation</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 3)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to imagine one thing representing another. We do this all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in the UK the Royal Standard always flies from buildings
containing the monarch. This flag is understood to represent the Queen's
presence and somebody ensures it is flown at the right moment from the
buildings she visits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/royal_standard.jpg" alt="The Royal Standard over Buckingham Palace"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Buckingham_Palace_-_Royal_Standard.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
  - Licensed under
  &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en" target="_blank"&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a twist...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the Royal Standard, a light on top of a building's flag pole could
represent the Queen's presence. If it were on, she was present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice there are two possible states for the Queen (she's either present or
not), this is mirrored by the two possible states for the light (it is either
illuminated or not), and we are playing along in a sort of game that provides
meaning for such a representation (we understand that the Queen is present if
the light is illuminated, just like we do when we see the flying of the Royal
Standard). One thing (a light) is representing something else (the Queen's
presence).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a device could be built using the circuit shown in the diagram below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Simple switch circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/simple_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the top is the symbol representing a battery that supplies current for
the other components. Lines show how the battery and other components connect.
The circle containing a cross represents a bulb and the gap created by the line
veering off at an angle represents a switch. In the following photograph the
real-world components, shown next to their symbols, connect to form the
circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Electrical components" src="https://ntoll.org/images/components.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The switch can be in two possible states: on (creating a circuit so current
moves through the components, thus lighting the bulb) or off (where the circuit
is broken, stopping the current and extinguishing the bulb).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a royal brain twist for you: can you think of something else that deals
with only two possible states?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought, "propositional logic" then you deserve a knighthood!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two possible states of the circuit, as controlled by the switch, mirrors
the two possible states encountered in propositional logic: on/true and
off/false. We could play along with the logical game and say that the circuit
represents the truth value of the proposition, "the Queen is present".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another royal brain twist: it's also possible to make simple circuits
that mimic the logical operations found in propositional logic ("and", "or",
"not" and all the rest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By re-arranging the physical components of the circuit, from a logical point of
view, the illuminated bulb could represent the presence of both the Queen
and/or her hier, the Prince of Wales:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Queen is present &lt;em&gt;AND&lt;/em&gt; the Prince of Wales is present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Queen is present &lt;em&gt;OR&lt;/em&gt; the Prince of Wales is present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, propositional logic doesn't care about the meaning of the
propositions ("the Queen is present", "the Prince of Wales is present"), so
the circuits' behaviour could be generalised to represent "A and B" or
"A or B".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the diagram for the "and" circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="And circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/and_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two switches are labelled to show how they represent the propositions "A"
and "B". Because of the &lt;strong&gt;consecutive&lt;/strong&gt; arrangement of the switches, the states
of the switches and the resulting behaviour of the bulb match the truth table
for "and": if both switches are on, then the bulb is on (representing "true"),
otherwise, in all other combination of switch states, the bulb is off
(representing "false").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the diagram for the "or" circuit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Or circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/or_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, the &lt;strong&gt;parallel&lt;/strong&gt; arrangement of the switches causes the circuit
to mirror the truth table for the logical "or" operation. If only one (or both)
of the switches are on, then the bulb is on, otherwise, when both switches are
off, the bulb is off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circuit for "not" is slightly different and allows me to introduce a new
(but important) electrical component: the &lt;em&gt;transistor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transistors control flow of electrical current with three connections called
"gate", "source" and "drain". Electrical current flows between "source" and
"drain" only if current is also applied to the "gate" connection. Rather than
controlling the flow of current with a switch operated by a person, a
transistor is controlled by another electrical component via the "gate".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transistors work because they're made from two different types of silicon, a
material that only conducts electricity under certain conditions (which is why
it's called a semi-conductor). The silicon is mixed with certain impurities to
create p-type and n-type silicon. In the diagram below the
&lt;span style="color: #586796;"&gt;p-type silicon is shown in blue&lt;/span&gt;,
the &lt;span style="color: #b03030;"&gt;n-type silicon in red&lt;/span&gt;
and the gate connection in green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Transistor off" src="https://ntoll.org/images/transistor_off_as_diagram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a similar way to how "and" and "or" circuits behave as a result of the
physical arrangement of their components, the cleverness of transistors comes
about because of how the p-type and n-type parts are physically arranged. The
"source" terminal is connected to an n-type layer (in red, on the left of the
diagram), the "gate" (in green) to the p-type barrier layer (in blue) and
"drain" to another n-type layer (in red, on the right of the diagram).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In very simplistic terms, if a voltage is applied to p-type silicon via the
"gate" connection, it behaves like n-type silicon. When in this state it is no
longer an insulating barrier between the "source" and "drain" and electricity
can flow. This is shown in the diagram below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Transistor on" src="https://ntoll.org/images/transistor_on_as_diagram.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transistors come in many shapes and sizes, but are most common as
extraordinarily small components etched onto silicon (i.e. microchips). The
image below was taken by an electron microscope and shows a transistor on a
microchip with the parts labelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/transistor_on_chip.png" alt="A Transistor on a microchip"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.quora.com/Why-is-the-transistor-so-crucial-to-computers-and-what-role-does-it-play-in-computing" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - educational fair use.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the "not" circuit: remember that electricity will always flow the
shortest way to "ground" (for instance via a lightning rod). The following
(very simplified) circuit diagram shows how a transistor and ground is used to
make something that behaves like a logical "not".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transistor is represented by a circle pierced by three lines. The source is
represented by the line entering the circle at the 1 o'clock position, the
drain by the line at the 5 o'clock position and the gate by the line at 9
o'clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Not circuit" src="https://ntoll.org/images/not_circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the left, the button labelled "A", attached to the gate, is off
(representing false) so current is unable to pass through the transistor to
ground. As a result, the electrical current (in red) flows through the lamp to
illuminate it (representing true). On the right, the button is on (in green,
representing voltage applied to the transistor's gate). The current is able
to flow through the transistor from the source to the drain and then to
ground (so no current flows to the bulb to illuminate it). The red arrows make
it clear how the current flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the lamp is always in the opposite logical state to the switch and
the circuit mirrors the behaviour of a logical "not". If the switch is off,
the light is on and if the switch is on, the light is off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important brain twist is understanding that we can design physical systems
(i.e. electrical circuits) that &lt;em&gt;appear to behave as logical ones&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another seemingly contradictory brain twist is to &lt;em&gt;remove "logic" from any
explanation of the circuits&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a scientific point of view of the circuit, an observer can only describe
physical properties and behaviours in terms of electrical current, the
mechanical behaviour of switches, the incandescent properties of filament and
the electrochemical nature of batteries and transistors. You won't find any
formal rules of propositional logic here, nor meaning ascribed to physical
states of affairs. The scientific view of the circuit is the "how" of the
circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet if we agree the on/off states of the switches represent the true/false
values of propositions "A" and "B" and the on/off status of the light
represents a resulting logical outcome (true/false) then the behaviour of the
first circuit undoubtedly mirrors the truth table for "and". Remember, it's not
logic that makes the circuit behave in this way (it's actually physics!), but
because we play along in a game where physical states mirror and thus
accurately represent logical ones, then the circuit acquires an additional
layer of meaning in terms of the rules of logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the "why" of the logical circuit: a human is needed to understand what
the behaviour of a physical object apparently represents. Without the
meaningful human-ascribed behaviour there is just an object described by
physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another instance of this phenomenon: there is no physical law described
by science that explains why green means "go" and red means "stop" at traffic
lights - yet the traffic lights are very much a physical system that can be
described by science. If meaning is involved, then humans and their cultural
norms are needed to make sense of it to explain what it represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teleology (using meaningful purpose or design to explain phenomena) isn't a
part of the "how" of physics-based descriptions of the world - yet humans
commonly retrofit purpose or design to describe physical systems that exhibit
behaviour appearing to represent something meaningful, such as logical
operations or traffic lights. The brain twist is to realise where and when such
human interventions assign meaning to the physical world, such as in the case
of the logic circuits I've described.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine an arrangement of many transistor-based circuits (representing various
logical operations), chained together so the output of one circuit provides the
input to the next. This yet-more-complicated arrangement of logical circuits
defines the meaningful behaviour of a device. Such a device, like its
constituent logical circuits, connects to the outside world via inputs and
outputs and has a strange capability: to change its own state in order to store
and process information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next post will explore such a machine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-3/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Movements of Thought</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as one can describe rules for a card game, it is possible to describe
rules for thinking: rules for movement of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the study of &lt;em&gt;Logic&lt;/em&gt;, and using these rules is called &lt;em&gt;reasoning&lt;/em&gt;.
Reasoning with logical rules allows others, who know such rules, to follow the
movements of thought that brought you to a certain conclusion. Furthermore,
because there are rules, it's possible to notice when they're ignored or used
incorrectly (when movements of thought don't make logical sense).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many types of logic, but the one we're going to examine is called
propositional (or sentential, or boolean) logic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Propositional" and "sentential" are just descriptive names for a type of
logic that deals with forming sentences by combining propositions. In logic,
&lt;em&gt;propositions make assertions that are either true or false&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Boole" target="_blank"&gt;George
Boole&lt;/a&gt; (1815-1864), shown below, invented a system of mathematical algebra
that works like propositional logic (it also deals with values that are either
true or false) and so the term "boolean" is often used synonymously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/boole.png" alt="George Boole"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Portrait_of_George_Boole.png" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
  - this image is in the
  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_domain" target="_blank"&gt;public domain&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a contrived example of a sentence in propositional logic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If it is sunny and I am wearing a thick coat, then I am hot."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to some important aspects of this sentence that
may not, at first, appear obvious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It contains two propositions called &lt;em&gt;premises&lt;/em&gt; ("it is sunny" and "I am
  wearing a thick coat"). Premises make assertions about &lt;em&gt;states of affairs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It ends with a &lt;em&gt;conclusion&lt;/em&gt; ("I am hot"). A conclusion is a &lt;em&gt;proposition that
  depends upon the premises&lt;/em&gt; in some way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sentence is in the form of a &lt;em&gt;conditional&lt;/em&gt; ("if [premises], then
  [conclusion]"). A conditional is a rule saying that if its premises are true
  then the conclusion &lt;strong&gt;must be true&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The premises are related to each other by a &lt;em&gt;logical operator&lt;/em&gt; called a
  &lt;em&gt;conjunction&lt;/em&gt; ("and"). This is another rule: if the related premises are
  evaluated together, &lt;strong&gt;collectively they are true only if all of them are
  true&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Propositional logic describes the rules of a "game" to construct sentences that
make logical sense. Playing by the rules of logic forces everyone to reach the
same inevitable conclusion: if we accept that the premises are true (it is
sunny and I am wearing a coat) propositional logic dictates the conclusion must
be true (I am hot). The object of propositional logic is to use the rules to
evaluate (work out) if a sentence is true or false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the brain twist: propositional logic doesn't care about meaning. The
important logical aspects of the example above don't concern my state in the
real world (which is why the sentence sounds slightly odd). &lt;em&gt;Propositional
logic only cares about truth and how propositions fit together&lt;/em&gt;. I could
revise the example to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If A and B then C."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter what &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt; stand for nor what they may mean -- from
the perspective of propositional logic all that matters is there are two
conjuncted premises (A and B) and a conclusion (C) expressed in a conditional
(if ... then ...). If one or both of the premises is false, then the
conclusion must also be false. Why? Because the logical rules pertaining to
conditionals and conjunctions (&lt;em&gt;and nothing else outside those rules&lt;/em&gt;) make it
that way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brain twist is divorcing yourself from meaning -- just concern yourself
with truth values of the propositions, the structure of the sentence and
following the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way the
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1#rules_of_snap"&gt;rules of Snap explain what
must happen&lt;/a&gt;, given card
related states of affairs, so the rules of propositional logic do the same with
propositions and sentences. The rules of Snap don't care what the specific
values of cards are, just that such values may match. Similarly, propositional
logic doesn't care what the specific meanings of the propositions may be, only
that such propositions connect in a sentence that can be evaluated with rules
dealing in just two possible states: &lt;strong&gt;true&lt;/strong&gt; and
&lt;strong&gt;false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to express the rules that govern such logical operations
for connecting propositions is with a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth_table" target="_blank"&gt;truth
table&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's the definition of "and" (conjunction):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt; A | B | A and B
----------------
 F | F |    F
 F | T |    F
 T | F |    F
 T | T |    T
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Can you see how it works?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two columns represent propositions labelled "A" and "B". The third
column represents the outcome of the "and" operation, given the values of "A"
and "B" in the first two columns. Each possible combination of truth value for
"A" and "B" is enumerated as a row with the resulting truth value for the "and"
operation in the third column. It's a simple tabular way to express the rules
of propositional logic. If you had any doubt how "and" (conjunction) worked,
you'd find the definitive answer in this truth table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, take the first row: if propositions "A" and "B" are both false
(as expressed in the first two columns), then the outcome for this rule
(expressed in the third column) &lt;strong&gt;must be false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another truth table that defines the rule for the logical operation
called "or" (disjunction):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt; A | B | A or B
---------------
 F | F |   F
 F | T |   T
 T | F |   T
 T | T |   T
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's pretend that "A" is false but "B" is true. How would you evaluate the
truth value of "A or B"? Is it true or false?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that "A or B" is true. Why? Because the second row tells us so:
the "A" column is false, the "B" column is true so the result, expressed in the
third column, is true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's one final truth table. It's a bit different to the other two since it
only works on a single proposition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt; A | not A
----------
 T |   F
 F |   T
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It's easy to see what the "not" (negation) operation does to a proposition: it
flips its truth value so false becomes true, and true becomes false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these logical operations have familiar names ("and", "or" and "not")
that &lt;strong&gt;appear to relate to how they work&lt;/strong&gt;, it is the truth table
&lt;strong&gt;and only the truth table&lt;/strong&gt; that defines how they behave in
propositional logic, not any similarity to how we may use such words in
everyday English. There are further rules, expressed as truth tables, for
connecting propositions that you may wish to look into. They are
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exclusive_or" target="_blank"&gt;XOR&lt;/a&gt;
(eXclusive OR),
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheffer_stroke" target="_blank"&gt;NAND&lt;/a&gt;
(Not AND),
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_NOR" target="_blank"&gt;NOR&lt;/a&gt;
(Not OR) and
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_equality" target="_blank"&gt;XNOR&lt;/a&gt;
(eXclusive Not OR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logical puzzles become fun when you combine such logical operations to build
more complicated structures. Take for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A and B) or (C or not D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've put parentheses ("&lt;code&gt;(&lt;/code&gt;" and "&lt;code&gt;)&lt;/code&gt;") around propositions so you can see how they
relate to the logical operators (the &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;). If we pretend all
the propositions represented by letters are false, what is the overall truth
value of the sentence?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find the answer we play the logical "game" in the same way we would with
Snap: we follow the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start by evaluating the operators within the parentheses. If we replace the
propositions "A" and "B" with their truth values (remember, all the
propositions are false), we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(false and false) or (C or not D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the rule set out in the truth table for "and", the propositions in the
first parentheses evaluate to false. Here's how the sentence looks as a
result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;false or (C or not D)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To evaluate the "or" in the remaining parentheses we should first evaluate the
"not" operator to find the truth value of the proposition on the right. If "D"
is false, then the truth table for "not" tells us that "not D" must evaluate to
true. Since "C" is false, the sentence looks like this when "C" and "not D" are
replaced by their truth values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;false or (false or true)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth table for "or", when applied to values in the remaining parentheses
tells us that if one of the propositions is true, then the "or" operation must
evaluate to true, giving us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;false or true&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-using this rule to evaluate the remaining "or" operation gives the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;true&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;only way&lt;/strong&gt; to solve such logical puzzles is by following the inevitable
steps dictated by the rules. That's &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; logic works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; does logic work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the same reason why the game of Snap works: we modify our behaviour to
follow unambiguous rules because we want to determine the truth of sentences in
propositional logic (the aim of playing this sort of logic game). Furthermore,
by pretending propositions represent states of affairs in the real world, we
can use logic to describe and, in a sense, encode aspects of the real world.
For instance, we could describe the rules of Snap &lt;em&gt;with logic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is logic useful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because logic clearly and unambiguously describes the relationships between
states of affairs (premises), and allows us to take action given a resulting
truth value. Consider, for example, this conditional statement: &lt;code&gt;IF&lt;/code&gt; the card
on top of stack A is an ace &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; the card on top of stack B is an ace, &lt;code&gt;THEN&lt;/code&gt;
shout "SNAP!". Logic describes the movement of thought needed to participate in
the card game (or any other useful structured activity).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a final "brain twist" for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Logic provides an inevitable, almost mechanical framework for organising and
describing movements of thought then we should be able to build machines to
work with such seemingly mechanical logical rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that we can, and describing such machines is the next step in
describing why computers work!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Computers Work: An Introduction to Following Rules</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;style&gt;
.section_break {
    border: none;
    border-bottom: 1px solid black;
    width: 50%;
    color: #333;
    overflow: visible;
    text-align: center;
    height: 5px;
}

.section_break:after {
    background: #fff;
    content: '§';
    padding: 0 4px;
    position: relative;
    top: -13px;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why Computers Work (part 1)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first of five short blog posts exploring &lt;em&gt;why computers work&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to present a friendly introductory overview for laypeople, from zero
to Turing machines, automata, abstraction and more. My aim is conciseness and
clarity, so I've necessarily missed out, glossed over and simplified things.
There are plenty of more advanced resources online should you wish to
investigate this subject further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I hope to stimulate your thinking about computers by creating
a place to explore ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoy these articles and, as always, I love getting constructive
feedback &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/contact"&gt;via email&lt;/a&gt;. Unless otherwise stated, all images and
diagrams were created by the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="section_break"&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;αἰὼν παῖς ἐστι παίζων, πεσσεύων· παιδὸς ἡ βασιληίη.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The universe is a child's game. A child's kingdom.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~ &lt;a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/heraclitus/"&gt;Heraclitus&lt;/a&gt; (Fragment B52)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers are ubiquitous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They touch all aspects of our lives, from mediating our social interactions to
modelling aspects of our culture and managing the everyday infrastructure of
society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, computers are interesting and, understandably, folks want to
know &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; the machines that automate and control so much of our world work.
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tpIctyqH29Q" target="_blank"&gt;This is
a typical response&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm going to take a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to explore &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; computers work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's the difference?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answers to "how?" questions tell us what method or steps make something happen.
In contrast, the answers to "why?" questions describe what makes something
possible ~ an opportunity to encounter a more fundamental perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the difference between a car mechanic who may understand &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; an engine
works (so they can fix broken engines), and a mechanical engineer who
understands the physics and chemistry relating to &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; engines work (so they
can improve the design of engines). Knowing how something works means your
frame of reference is &lt;em&gt;within the system&lt;/em&gt;, whereas if you understand why
something works you're not bound by existing products, solutions or cultural
practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, cultivating an understanding of why something is possible is
an invitation for playful creativity, fearless exploration and careful
refinement of alternatives to the current crop of answers to "how?". It is an
opportunity to enlarge and change our world ~ a form of intellectual
empowerment and growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; is good, but understanding &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the scene suitably set, to start our journey, we'll learn all about...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Following Rules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how to play the children's card game, Snap?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Bear with me, I promise it'll be worth it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a standard deck of cards, the aim is to win all the cards by &lt;em&gt;taking
turns to play&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's follow along as siblings Penelope (11), Sam (8) and Will (5) play a game:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Penelope (for no other reason than she's the oldest) acts as dealer. She
shuffles the deck of cards so they're in a random order and deals them, face
down and in equal quantity, to each player until there are none left to deal.
This is the starting state from which all games of Snap begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam, the player to the left of the dealer, takes the first turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players take a turn by moving the top card from their face-down stack onto the
top of an adjacent stack of face-up cards, so the newly moved card is also
facing up. Since this is Sam's first turn, the face-up stack doesn't exist,
so a new stack is created with Sam's first face-up card taken from his pile of
face-down cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So ends Sam's turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/snap.jpg" alt="A game of Snap!"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Play-Snap" target="_blank"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; - From
  &lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com" target="_blank"&gt;WikiHow&lt;/a&gt; and licensed
  under
  &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/deed.en" target="_blank"&gt;CC BY-NC-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next player to the left, William, takes his turn in a similar fashion and
so the game continues from one player to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while Sam shouts "SNAP". He's noticed that two face-up cards on top of
different stacks have the same value (for example, two aces are visible on top
of Penelope and Will's stacks). Since he was first to shout "SNAP" he wins all
the cards in the matching stacks of cards. He gleefully scoops up all the cards
in the face-up stacks belonging to Penelope and Will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play continues to the left of the player who turned up the matching card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few moments later Penelope shouts "SNAP". But there is a problem: there are
no matching face-up cards! William points this out to Penelope and reminds her
she has to pay a forfeit by giving one card to each of the other players from
her face-down stack. Sam and Will get a card each and Penelope is two cards
down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the game Sam has the most cards. Will and Penelope have less
with only a few cards difference between the quantities in their face-down
stacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are hotting up and the three children become more excited: when two
matching face-up cards appear again all three of them shout "SNAP" at the same
time. Since nobody can claim to have shouted "SNAP" first, and to avoid
arguments, both the matching stacks are placed in the middle and added to the
"Snap pool". When "SNAP" is next called unambiguously and correctly, the winner
will get both the matching stacks and any cards in the "Snap pool". The stakes
have suddenly got higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things quieten down for a few rounds until Penelope runs out of face-down cards
to put onto her face-up stack. At this point she simply flips over her face-up
stack and it becomes her face-down stack. Play continues as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after a few more calls of "SNAP", Penelope finds that she's run out
of cards and so out of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam and Will play together until, through luck and fast reactions, Sam finds
himself with all the cards and he's declared the winner of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's how you play Snap..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="rules_of_snap"&gt;The rules illustrated in this deliberately precise story describe
&lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;, given certain states of affairs, such-and-such things must
happen. States of affairs unambiguously describe how things are in the world.
For example, "there are two stacks of face-up cards whose top cards are of
matching value". When I describe how such-and-such must happen, I mean clear
and unambiguous instructions describe &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; play proceeds given a
certain state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, this is &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the game of Snap is played.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is Snap played?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because, in addition to knowing the rules, we understand that playing the game
of Snap means modifying one's behaviour to follow these rules. If everyone
modifies their behaviour in accordance with the rules then folks can play
together. Obviously, we don't explain card games in such a formal manner to
very young children. But, as my description shows, children discover it's lots
of fun to informally learn and skilfully follow rules that bring about
exciting situations in games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing how to play Snap is analogous to knowing how computers work. Looking
beyond the rules of Snap to appreciate that human behaviour and enjoyment
motivates people to follow the rules of the game, shows us &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; Snap is
played. This insight may also inspire us to invent new games. Perhaps we become
inspired to explore further aspects of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milgram_experiment" target="_blank"&gt;human behaviour relating to following rules&lt;/a&gt;,
or we may even
&lt;a href="https://theoryoffun.com/" target="_blank"&gt;reflect upon the nature of play or games&lt;/a&gt;.
In any case, exploring &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; provides a
fascinating perspective from outside the system (of Snap, in this case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to achieve an analogous enlargement of perspective beyond &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;
computers work in order to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; computers work. Only by acquiring a
perspective outside current norms can we possibly hope to invent or improve
technology and explore the nature and use of such devices. The alternative is
churn and recycling of existing ideas within the current system ~ a situation
that stifles innovation or positive change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The computing-related rules and states of affairs I'm going to describe are not
much more complicated than the game of Snap explained above. However, what
follows may include a few &lt;em&gt;brain twists&lt;/em&gt; where I expect you to use your
imagination to see things in a seemingly unusual or unintuitive way! I'm
challenging you to acquire a new perspective about seemingly everyday things.
The external world remains as it was before, but you will have changed. Your
newly acquired perspective reveals a deeper understanding of what you're
observing and why this makes computing possible. It's fun and can result in
rather pleasant "aha" moments (if you were a cartoon character, it's that
feeling you get when a lightbulb appears above your head).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next chapter in our story is a beautiful brain twist: to think about
thinking...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-1/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 07:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Social Media Hermit</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/social-media-hermit/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have deleted my Twitter account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I no longer use it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social media isn't fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are better ways to connect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retaining my account feels hypocritical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, that's all there is to it (and it feels good).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter encourages infantile, reactionary and shallow discourse. What do you
expect from a technology that enforces a 280 character limit and trains us to
read in bite size chunks? Twitter may as well enforce &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newspeak"&gt;other arbitrary
limitations&lt;/a&gt;, for example the exclusive
use of monosyllabic words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want no part of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If folks genuinely want to connect with me, they'll be in touch (as I will be
with them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/social-media-hermit/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 07:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Being Together</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/on-being-together/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;(Some raw thoughts I've written down solely to help me clarify my thinking.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being together with people I love and who love me in return is a source of
great joy and solace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet being with people can also lead to distress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many, I've encountered rejection and resulting feelings of loneliness,
I've been the target of ignorant nastiness, and some make it clear I am of no
value while others happily place unreasonable burdens upon me. My own
experiences are but a small selection from the menu of unwelcome situations
that could be, and often are, meted out to people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dealing with complicated experiences and finding a way to work through
challenging encounters often feels painful and can lead to a sense of failure
or hopelessness. But I believe this process is also an opportunity for growth,
albeit through small, difficult, and often misplaced, steps. Allowing
complicated feelings, pain and failure to manifest is certainly better than the
alternative: sweeping things out of sight means the distress is never
addressed, explored or dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, being together requires conscious work and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good stuff can take as much effort as the bad. To be loving, compassionate,
tolerant and forgiving towards others requires great strength of character. The
bad stuff shows we are all flawed sensitive beings whose strength often fails
us. We have an endless capacity to hurt and be hurt by each other. This is
especially true if we don't allow ourselves the time and energy to reflect upon
and consciously adjust our behaviour towards each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, some simply don't care for others or for such self reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, narcissists (by definition) lack empathy or compassion and only
make an effort in relationships if they see a benefit to themselves. This is a
tragic form of ignorance, for they will never know the joy of relationships
shared with loved ones who reciprocate emotional investment and mutual care.
For them, being together is an exercise in self aggrandisement, domination or
profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The origins of such self-centredness are complicated. Ironically, introspection
and self-reflection - the very traits such people fail to exercise - would help
address and overcome such origins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe everyone has a unique and valuable journey through life, even if
their current location or direction of travel is deeply problematic.
Recognising this applies to a narcissist or other difficult individual takes
(the afore mentioned) strength of character. But it means it is possible to be
together without getting crushed by the weight of their ego or toxic behaviour.
Sadly, sometimes this is simply not possible and you have to cut your losses
and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I often wonder how to respond to the difficulties that arise from being
together with others. I continue to believe that being together is often a
privilege and a source of happiness and growth. Yet some of my recent
collaborations have also been a source of great pain (interactions with aspects
of the Python community
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/compassion/"&gt;spring to mind&lt;/a&gt;). As a result, my
feelings about being together have changed significantly over the past
couple of years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to be all about promoting "the community" as a way of being together.
An immediate problem is "the community" is an amorphous blob of a term that
folks never pin down. This is a significant cause of many problems as
misunderstanding is rife. In any case, I naively contributed and volunteered my
code, time, effort and money. In short, I tried very hard to be a positive part
of "something". For the past 12 years or so, this "something" was the Python
programming community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, there are two common contrasting ways folks describe or
think about the notion of "community": top-down (meaning the community is
managed) and bottom-up (where the community emerges through participation). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always been reticent about top-down bureaucratic, formal and
hierarchical notions of community. Often they are well meaning yet ineffectual
(or sometimes even damaging) self defeating processes. They can also easily
turn into toxic dumpster fires full of malice (politics and power plays being
well known examples of contributing factors to such a sorry state of affairs).
Finally, they tend to gain a momentum that makes it easy to squash and ignore
rather than cherish and nourish individuals and creative innovation. While
my experience of the "formal" Python community has mostly been extraordinarily
positive, there has been enough not-so-good-stuff that I've chosen to step
away. I can only but wish the Python community well, but it's a ship in which I
no longer sail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don't want to find myself in a chaotic bottom-up community either.
While these are ad hoc, improvised and informal, there is still a hierarchy,
along with impositions of power and other negative political machinations.
These are lived out through hidden communication channels, gossip or because
the loudest or most charismatic folks hold the floor. People are either "in"
or "out" of the circle of these "movers and shakers".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least more formal communities appear to be up front about hierarchy, the
exercise of power, the scope and relations of roles and how one assumes
positions therein..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't help but feel that something is missing when we view communities as
such formal structures. Communities are collections of individual people and,
perhaps, the missing element to make sense of being together is an explicit
focus on the "character" of participants. Just how do individuals reflect and
choose to behave when being together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm reminded of &lt;a href="https://www.lewissociety.org/innerring/"&gt;this rather interesting essay&lt;/a&gt;,
by C.S.Lewis. I first read it when I was a music undergraduate and found it via
my Christian room-mate. Lewis describes an "Inner Ring", something akin to the
circle of "movers and shakers" vying for influence, power and prestige that I
describe above. The part of the essay that most speaks to me comes at the very
end:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"And if in your spare time you consort simply with the people you like, you
will again find that you have come unawares to a real inside: that you are
indeed snug and safe at the centre of something which, seen from without,
would look exactly like an Inner Ring. But the difference is that the secrecy
is accidental, and its exclusiveness a by-product, and no one was led thither
by the lure of the esoteric: for it is only four or five people who like one
another meeting to do things that they like. This is friendship. Aristotle
placed it among the virtues. It causes perhaps half of all the happiness in
the world, and no Inner Ring can ever have it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reaching back in time to feel like my 18 year old undergraduate self, I want to
be with folks who are open to compassionate, collaborative, cooperative
ways of working but without any extra problematic notions of "community" (as
described above). I simply want to bring myself, and welcome others who want to
join me, in a place where there's recognition, a connection, frisson or
creative energy from which we can mutually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, I am inviting friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friendship requires trust, honesty, tolerance, compassion and forgiveness...
all those things that depend upon strength of character. Putting in such effort
for others is the antipode of the machinations needed to become one of the "in"
crowd or a member of the organisational elite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here's the thing... the tech world has its fair share of folks who forget or
don't understand what I believe makes a place positive, friendly and safe when
being with each other. Such folks see collaboration in terms of gaining
prestige and power. This is the stuff of narcissistic day dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an organised community such behaviour is addressed by a code of conduct (and
the Python community spend a lot of time and energy acting on this with varying
degrees of success, from [alas] hollow virtue signalling through to very
effective networks of support centred on extraordinarily kind and caring
individuals). Conversely, informal communities tend to lack this sort of
public or explicit "framework" often with detrimental results (folks are able
to capitalize, abuse or manipulate the informal "hidden" networks and
relationships to selfish or unpleasant ends with no clear way to call them
out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My focus on self-reflection and things within my own control explains why I've
found myself writing a sort of poetic personal code I call
"&lt;a href="https://github.com/ntoll/being_together"&gt;on being together&lt;/a&gt;".
I'll make it a part of all my future coding projects (and encountering
&lt;a href="https://github.com/Xe/creators-code"&gt;Xe's Creator's Code&lt;/a&gt;
inspired this effort). It's very much a work in progress and has become an
expression of what you can expect from me and what I hope from you should we
find ourselves "being together" in a place to collaborate with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
When being together, especially if things go wrong,&lt;br&gt;
we acknowledge and work through differences.&lt;br&gt;
In so doing, we transform and enlarge each other.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
To nurture our mutual growth,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    this is a place of&lt;br&gt;
        learning, understanding, and sharing;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    this is a place to&lt;br&gt;
        affirm tolerance and compassion;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    this is a place for&lt;br&gt;
        collaborative creativity.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
All the aspects of yourself you choose to bring to this place&lt;br&gt;
are welcome here.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Reciprocate! Welcome, embrace and learn from others&lt;br&gt;
(even in the face of apparent hostility or misunderstanding).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
To act against this spirit invites ostracism,&lt;br&gt;
a loss that diminishes us all.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Thank you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/on-being-together/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 16:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Twisty Passages at EuroPython 2020 </title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/twisty-passages-at-europython/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://ep2020.europython.eu/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; took place last month and the
raw video footage of the talks has just been published online. EuroPython has
always been one of my favourite conferences and is a special place for me:
it's where I gave my first ever programming talk back in 2010. It's also one of
the most culturally cosmopolitan coding conferences and was the world's
first community organised Python software conference. I always come away
feeling enriched by EuroPython.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, as always, to the volunteer organisers who work so hard to bring about
this remarkable event. Such thanks are especially well deserved in 2020 since
it was held online due to the spread of the COVID-19 virus. The potential for
technical mishaps and problems was huge, yet the friendly and supportive team
behind the conference ensured a slick and engaging event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, there were many great talks with a particular highlight for me being
a fascinating explanation of building "artistic artefacts" (computer generated
pictures in the style of human painters) with
&lt;a href="https://ep2020.europython.eu/talks/BSeL2FG-painting-with-gans-challenges-and-technicalities-of-neural-style-transfer/"&gt;Generative Adversarial Networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I sorely missed the corridor track - when you walk around the physical
conference venue and bump into an old buddy, find yourself striking up a
conversation with a friendly co-attendee in the coffee queue, or join a huddle
of welcoming folks discussing something interesting. The corridor track is
where the community comes alive. I'll have more to say about this in a
moment...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to make two contributions to this year's conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first was a wonderful opportunity to bring some music to the conference. My
friend and EuroPython's own force of nature,
&lt;a href="https://www.malemburg.com/marc-andre-lemburg"&gt;Marc-André&lt;/a&gt; got in touch
to say that they were looking for musical contributions to a "jam session". I
have, on several occasions, inflicted my love of tubas on Marc-André so
he knew I used to be a professional classical musician. I can only assume his 
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hzJZObBSU7E"&gt;Germanic inclination for oompah-bands&lt;/a&gt;
was at the back of his mind when he reached out. I responded that tuba music is
"rather niche" at the best of times, let alone as part of a "jam session".
Nevertheless, I agreed to contribute something, "perhaps a piece of classical
piano music?" (since I'd been playing lots of piano during lock-down here in
the UK).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I went for some
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Brahms"&gt;Brahms&lt;/a&gt; ~ an
&lt;a href="https://www.mfiles.co.uk/scores/brahms-intermezzo-op118-no2.pdf"&gt;Intermezzo&lt;/a&gt;
written "as a token of friendship" for his friend, the concert pianist and
composer &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clara_Schumann"&gt;Clara Schumann&lt;/a&gt;. It's
my musical token of friendship towards everyone at EuroPython.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/V2nCyL0hZko" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second contribution was
&lt;a href="https://ep2020.europython.eu/talks/AGaSaW8-how-to-run-a-corridor-track-in-a-remote-conference-with-python/"&gt;a presentation&lt;/a&gt;.
The slides I prepared, including the links to all the resources I mention
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/static/presentations/textsmith_ep2020/index.html#/"&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation is an exploration of how one might recreate a remote corridor
track via the internet. I think it speaks for itself (honestly, go watch it, I
had a lot of fun preparing and presenting it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0FC5T396NVk" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary is that I feel deeply uncomfortable about the way friendships,
conversation and community are mediated in a technical context at this moment
in time. This is something we should be especially concerned about given how
much of our interactions have taken place online during these times of virus
related lock-down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I offer a quick explanation of what I find so uncomfortable about the current
state of the art and look into the history of computing for other, more humane,
respectful (of users) and creative means of communication via computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I describe how I'm using Python to recreate a programmable
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MUD"&gt;MUD&lt;/a&gt; (a multi-user, real time text based
virtual world) based upon ideas first explored in the late 1970s and which I
encountered in both the 1980s (while at school) and in the mid-1990s (when I
was at university). Such creations were famous for their mazes of twisty
passages that players could explore and inhabit together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've never heard of MUDs before, here's
&lt;a href="https://mud.co.uk/richard/"&gt;Richard Bartle&lt;/a&gt; (one of the authors of the
original MUD and author of the
&lt;a href="https://mud.co.uk/dvw/"&gt;bible for virtual worlds&lt;/a&gt;) describing an old
technology for talking directly to the imagination...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Zctp972y_Eg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I love feedback, comments and constructive criticism offered in good
faith. Assuming the lock-downs have eased, next year's EuroPython will be in
Dublin, Éire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love Ireland. Can't wait!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you at next year's EuroPython!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/twisty-passages-at-europython/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2020 Changes</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/2020-changes/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've spent today updating everything to do with ntoll.org. Many
thanks to my buddy &lt;a href="https://kushaldas.in/"&gt;Kushal Das&lt;/a&gt; for the invaluable
advice on various technical matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what I've done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The website is run using &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; ~ a Python based
   static site generator. It was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; easy to migrate away from my previous
   hand-coded solution made with a custom
   &lt;a href="https://palletsprojects.com/p/flask/"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; script and HTML.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's hosted on &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; which is both free
   and makes it very easy to manage code and deployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've switched email hosting to &lt;a href="https://www.fastmail.com/"&gt;Fastmail&lt;/a&gt;, who 
   made the whole migration process extraordinarily easy. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've archived the code for the old website for "safe keeping", even though
   all the content has moved over to the new site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of things have changed in addition to my own technical infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just finished a very busy period of freelance work with two clients -
the &lt;a href="https://freedom.press/"&gt;Freedom of the Press Foundation&lt;/a&gt; for whom I
contributed Python code to an
&lt;a href="https://securedrop.org/"&gt;application for journalists&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://digital.nhs.uk/"&gt;NHSDigital&lt;/a&gt; for whom I fulfilled the remote role of a
code mentor / developer coach (like an agile coach, but much more technical).
I was collaborating with a team of Java developers who were learning Python and
Django while building APIs for internal customers and users. I also provided
Python training, which was very rewarding since I love teaching and the
NHSDigital folks were already technically very strong and lots of fun. Both
teams were exceptionally talented and friendly. I had a blast and made lots of
new friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In just over a week I'll be starting a new gig with the
&lt;a href="https://mojdigital.blog.gov.uk/"&gt;Ministry of Justice&lt;/a&gt; as a senior Python
engineer. I'm &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; looking forward to this since the work is useful,
interesting and challenging. I'm looking forward to learning from my new
colleagues and making contributions to our collective effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for all my other projects (for instance
&lt;a href="https://codegrades.com/"&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://codewith.mu/"&gt;Mu&lt;/a&gt;)..?
Ironically, I believe I'll have more rhythm to my day and so my work on these
projects will continue in my own time, but at a more predictable pace. Watch
this space. :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the current Corona virus pandemic is affecting life in rather
unforeseen ways: my daughter and older son have had their summer exams
cancelled. Apparently, their results will be based upon their predicted grades.
It means my daughter is going to read Mathematics at university with a
scholarship (dependent on her achieving her target grades, which she will in
light of the current situation) and my son will have the grades needed to go
onto study Physics, Maths, Music and Design Technology at "A" level (his
current plan is to read engineering at university). My youngest son continues
school lessons, completed at home via an online platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've also had to purchase some home-studio equipment (mics, pre-amp, monitor
speakers, midi keyboard and related audio software). Mary, my wife, uses this
to teach her many instrumental students remotely via video calls. It soon
became apparent that laptop or mobile phone mics are not great for cello
or piano teaching. Happily, the new equipment is proving to be a great success
and Mary is able to continue teaching most students without disruption and from
the comfort of our own music room:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Our home studio" src="https://ntoll.org/images/studio.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; have the equipment available to produce my own (Python)
training materials and the kids are having a great time mixing all sorts of
different types of music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's hoping you stay safe and remain healthy during this challenging time.
Since most of us are in lock-down, don't hesitate to get in touch if you fancy
a chat..! Social distancing rules don't mean you have to be anti-social.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/2020-changes/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sponsorship</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The majority of the code I write is given away for free for the benefit of
others. This is unsustainable so I often think about how such voluntary work
could be supported. One solution is related to my
&lt;a href="http://codegrades.com/"&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; idea. But this is a slow
burn project that has involved, and continues to demand, a huge amount of
time, effort and money before I'll have anything to show for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another solution is simply to ask folks for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been a musician, I'm used to this feeling. I used to busk with some
buddies as a way of trying to make ends meet. However, as my grandmother once
pointed out, it's a form of begging. In one sense, this is a tragedy: begging
is a last resort because nothing else you do is of value. You're forced to
rely on the compassion and generosity of others. Yet in another sense it's like
the activity of a mendicant asking for alms for their service or contributions
to society. In any case, no matter how you "spin" it, it's a precarious
situation to find oneself in ~ be you a musician or free software developer
(and I'm both!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are some kind hearted individuals and (even rarer) companies or
organisations who are happy to help support such work, most think, "meh, I'll
just use the software" (without so much as a thank you). Even worse (and I have
personal experience of this) some folks will pass off such voluntary work as
their own and reap the rewards for such a lie. This is why I actually earn
money-to-live by writing software as a freelance developer (it gives me the
flexibility I need to work on my own coding projects).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it was with some interest that I noticed GitHub had created what
they describe as account sponsorship. "Sponsorship" is an interesting word
to use because it makes the begging / mendicant aspect of the situation more
palatable. It also cheerfully suggests that the free/open-source software world
is full of generous hearted folks or organisations just waiting to give back to
the selfless volunteers who make all this code available via their GitHub
account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, a fiction. It's also normalising begging as a solution
to funding free software volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I'm open minded and willing to give anything a go, especially if it
means it'll cover my costs. So I've signed up and now &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can give me
money for my efforts. As of the time of writing, and after tweeting about this
to my 3,000+ followers, this is what my account looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/github_sponsors.png" style="border: 1px solid #ccc;"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can't help but think that in six months time, it'll still look the same.
But at least I can say I gave it a go. Despite my misgivings, I feel it
important to give ideas a chance to flower and I'm trying very hard (yet
failing) to view this as a mendicant rather than beggar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you've ever found my work or activities useful, beneficial or
supportive, please consider helping me sustain my efforts. You can do so by
visiting my "&lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/ntoll"&gt;sponsorship&lt;/a&gt;"
page to find out more about what I do and how to give "alms". The summary is
that I focus on education: I develop software that helps folks learn the
skills and knowledge they need to imagine, develop and program the stuff they
want. If you believe this is important work, sponsor me with a monthly
contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, and many thanks to the small number of you who have already
done this, you can send me a virtual hug-as-a-book by buying me
something from my &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/hz/wishlist/ls/3B63FUSVDIJJS"&gt;Amazon wish list&lt;/a&gt;
(none of the items are particularly expensive). Small gestures, such as gifting
books or music with a supportive message, can actually mean a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll report back in a few months to let you know how I get on. I have to
admit, I don't hold out much hope. Best knuckle down on CodeGrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well... what are you waiting for..? Go on... get your wallets out. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Honestly, I quite understand if you don't. I have the same misgivings
you're probably having after reading the sentence above. Such a feeling is the
nub of what I want to demonstrate in this blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 08:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CircuitPython 2020</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/blinka-computer.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My buddy &lt;a href="http://tannewt.org/"&gt;Scott&lt;/a&gt;, one of the wonderful
people at &lt;a href="https://adafruit.com/"&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, recently asked folks
in the wider CircuitPython community to
&lt;a href="https://blog.adafruit.com/2020/01/01/what-do-you-want-from-circuitpython-in-2020-circuitpython2020-circuitpython/"&gt;share their thoughts&lt;/a&gt;
about what they'd like to see for the project and community during 2020. This
is my contribution to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three aspects to my hopes for CircuitPython in 2020:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Things I hope will continue,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Developments I hope to happen,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;"Moon on a stick" wishes for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to start by reaffirming my belief that Adafruit, and those
involved with CircuitPython in particular, do inspiring stuff when it
comes to fostering an open, welcoming, supportive and collaborative tech
community. This is an extraordinary achievement. My own experience in the
wider Python community is that it takes a huge amount of effort, patience,
compassion and thoughtfulness to grow and sustain such a
"&lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2008/06/scenius-or-comm/"&gt;scenius&lt;/a&gt;"
(and, sadly, this can be destroyed very quickly by only a few bad actors). So
my wish for continuation in 2020 is that everyone involved in the
CircuitPython community grasp opportunities to enlarge positive aspects of
ourselves such as mutual appreciation, the sharing of tools and techniques,
latent network effects, and a spirit of tolerance, compassion and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I hope happens this year is a broadening of CircuitPython's horizons.
My passion for tech can be summed up by a quote from David Allen, the producer
on the original BBC micro from the 1980s -- my first computer. He
&lt;a href="https://www.nesta.org.uk/report/the-legacy-of-bbc-micro/"&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt;
that, "[t]he aim was to democratise computing. We didn't want people to be
controlled by it, but to control it." CircuitPython feels to me like it sits
very much in the hobbyist / enthusiast "segment" of users who already know
something of programming. I'd love CircuitPython to make inroads into
beginner related education. This probably involves a focus on
learning what teachers would like from a coding platform, honest appraisals of
how beginner coders (no matter their age or background) find their first steps
with CircuitPython and Adafruit boards, as well as making the results of such
findings accessible to all. This final point is important. Learning to code
shouldn't just be an option for English speaking, able bodied folk from a
cultural background that means examples and cultural assumptions are
easily understood. I hope you agree that education should be an inclusive
endeavour, and this takes concerted and conscientious effort. I hope the
CircuitPython community find the time and space to invest in the (never
finished) work such a focus entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/static/images/moon_stick.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My "moon on a stick" is a CircuitPython based mobile phone with a touch
screen and a simple
(&lt;a href="https://pypercard.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;PyperCard&lt;/a&gt; like?)
Python UI that's easily hackable. Think
of it as the open, easy-to-assemble, relatively cheap and "hack friendly"
version of something like the
&lt;a href="https://www.thelightphone.com/"&gt;Light Phone&lt;/a&gt; with all the
schematics and design assets (e.g. files for 3d printing the case) available
under open source licenses so folks can go mod-crazy. Now wouldn't that
be a turn up for the books..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll finish by wishing everyone in the CircuitPython a flourishing and
happy new year. Here's to wonderful things in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's go..!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Classical Playlist of Love</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When my Canadian buddies &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndreaMcInnes21"&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://snarky.ca/"&gt;Brett&lt;/a&gt; visited the UK in
the summer, we visited the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Albert_Hall"&gt;Royal Albert Hall&lt;/a&gt; to hear a classical music
concert that was part of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Proms"&gt;the Proms&lt;/a&gt; -- the world's largest
classical music festival. I think they must have enjoyed themselves because
they recently got in touch asking me to suggest a playlist of
classical music. What follows is my response along with videos of performances
of the pieces I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than put together a playlist of apparently random
choices, I decided it would be interesting to assemble a set of pieces
related to a particular feeling. In this case, I chose love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because love is complicated, tragic, happy, joyful, funny, raunchy and many
more aspects too numerous to list here. The western classical
tradition has around 900 years of musical reactions, settings and descriptions
of love -- plenty of opportunity to reveal a breadth and depth of music. So,
I'm going to associate each piece with some aspect of love, provide
a short commentary and embedded a video of a performance of
the selected piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to my sharing videos of performances. Ideally,
you'd listen to these pieces in person at a concert. Only in such a live
situation can you really experience the fleeting moment of the performance,
executed by highly trained musicians and feel that sense of being in a
particular unique moment, together with all the others in attendance. The
videos are a less than perfect replacement, yet still have the potential to
move you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For convenience I've put them into a
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yjz2TvC2TT4&amp;amp;list=PLzCYc445IVNTPApt_F6PkGCRRPNfG-JmA"&gt;playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is classical music, it may sound strange to modern ears not
familiar with styles and mannerisms from hundreds of years ago or it uses sung
or instrumental techniques that sound odd because they're not used much in
contemporary popular music. If classical music isn't your thing, consider
this an invitation to explore a new musical world -- a world that rewards
repeated engagement, an open mind and long term listening. This is music that
makes demands of the listener, but will reveal depths one cannot even imagine
until you experience them for yourself. For those of you who are already
immersed in classical music you'll find none of my choices particularly
challenging. In fact, you may even roll your eyes and think, "oh, not that old
chestnut again". Please remember, this is an introductory playlist, but know
that I'm open to suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sincerely hope you are moved by the pieces I've selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tender Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gustav Mahler - Adagietto from Symphony No. 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical representation of Mahler's love for his wife Alma. Their
friend Wilem Engelberg recollects, "In place of a letter, he sent her this in
manuscript form, not adding a further word. She understood and wrote to him
telling him to come!!! They both told me this."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alma later revealed Gustav left her the following poem with the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In which way I love you, my sunbeam,&lt;br&gt;
I cannot tell you with words.&lt;br&gt;
Only my longing, my love and my bliss&lt;br&gt;
can I with anguish declare.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/P8LZ43LA2nY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tragic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky - Fantasy Overture to Romeo and Juliet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tchaikovsky was well acquainted with tragic love: he was a gay man in 19th
century Russia (a time and place full of prejudice towards someone such as
himself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such tragedy and pain as well as an overflowing sense of passion are
skilfully captured in this piece or "musical impressions" loosely assembled to
follow the story of Romeo and Juliet. Listen out for the overwhelming "love
theme" which has become a musical cliché for inevitably doomed lovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3x69wuewkJM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Romantic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergei Rachmaninoff - Piano Concerto No.2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachmaninoff, another Russian, is widely considered one of the greatest
pianists of all time, as well as one of the greatest composers for the
piano. This piano concerto is full of yearning melodies, gushing outpourings of
emotion, tender moments and joyful exuberance. Just like falling in love!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was effectively used in the David Lean romance from 1945, "Brief
Encounters", thus cementing it as a "romantic" classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rEGOihjqO9w" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Denied&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puccini - O Mio Babbino Caro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aria, from Puccini's opera "Gianni Schicchi", comes at the moment where
the daughter of Gianni tells him that she's fallen in love, wants to get
married, and if he won't let her go to her true love, she'll throw herself off
the Ponte Vecchio bridge in Florence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you imagine this sounds like a musical tantrum in the making, get ready
with the hankies and prepare for something absolutely not tantrum like at
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soprano singer in the video, Montserrat Caballé, is simply stunning. Her
charisma, presence, musicianship and vocal control is awe inspiring. Yes, she's
the one who sang with Freddie Mercury on his single "Barcelona".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RxZSP1Dc78Q" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Platonic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms - Intermezzo Op. 118 No. 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms wrote this beautiful piece for his friend Clara Schumann (Clara is
another musician considered one of the greatest pianists of all time and a
wonderful composer in her own right). I describe it as "Platonic" because Clara
was married to Brahms's mentor and friend Robert Schumann, who eventually
succumbed to mental health issues. Brahms and Clara were undoubtedly close and
shared a deep love for each other, but it was only ever a love between dear
friends. Imagine how you'd feel if you had been gifted such a piece of
music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78OO5v0lNtI" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fantastical Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berlioz - Symphonie Fantastique&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is sex, drugs and classical music with an added dose of musical story
telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is of the concert Andrea, Brett and I attended. I won't
say any more, since the performers do a fantastic job of explaining what's
going on. It's quite a spectacle (and watch out for the mirror balls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/t1sEI0JoZ8M" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Transformed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg - Verklärte Nacht&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg wrote this piece to closely follow the structure of the poem upon
which it is based, to the extent that the different sections in the musical
score map directly to lines in the poem. The poem, by Richard Dehmel, whose
title is translated as "Transfigured Night", tells of two lovers walking in the
woods. The woman opens up about a terrible burden she carries. Her lover is
full of compassion, love and support which transforms her burden into a shared
aspect of their life together. I'm being necessarily vague here so I don't
spoil the poem for you... just read it as
&lt;a href="https://allpoetry.com/Transfigured-Night-(Verklrte-Nacht)"&gt;translated here&lt;/a&gt;
and then listen to the piece. My favourite lines (and part of the piece)
are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just see how brightly the universe is gleaming!&lt;br&gt;
There’s a glow around everything;&lt;br&gt;
You are floating with me on a cold ocean,&lt;br&gt;
But a special warmth flickers&lt;br&gt;
From you into me, from me into you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the music sounds as if it's gleaming..! One other thing you
may hear, the violin (a high instrument) is prominent in the sections
representing the woman speaking, whereas the cello (a low instrument) is
prominent in the sections representing the man speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yzSaOWPBFqA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love's Dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fauré - Après un rêve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply a song about a dream of the poet's beloved. The words of the
poem (and their English translation) can be found &lt;a href="https://www.oxfordlieder.co.uk/song/15"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FlT1QhK4Wto" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Erotic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner - Prelude and Liebestod from 'Tristan Und Isolde'&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I start with this one..? This is erotic music. I don't mean humping
or "having a shag". Rather, it's a musical version of a passionate embrace
(between the protagonists, Tristan and Isolde).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In music theory we use the term "climax" to describe the point at which all
the tension in the music is released. There's a reason we call it a climax.
This piece has a famously ecstatic climax that takes a while to build, after
lots of tender pauses, gradually intensifying musical moments, soaring strings
and throbbing horns (no pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm sure you'll hear what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/W8EQcMurhAI" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Orgasmic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orff - Dulcissime (from Carmina Burana)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just watch and listen. No further explanation needed.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/BFq8vH7tPxs" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mendelssohn - Wedding March from A Midsummer Night's Dream&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You'll hear this in pretty much every church wedding you ever attend - and
quite rightly, it's very uplifting, celebratory and joyful music. Just what you
need for such an occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rIM5cWB2wmM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Moment of Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaughan Williams - Silent Noon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dante Gabriel Rossetti's poem "Silent Noon" recollects an intimate shared
moment of love that was both fleeting and intense. Vaughan Williams music
beautifully complements the nostalgic, thoughtful and timeless nature of the
moment in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Your hands lie open in the long fresh grass,--&lt;br&gt;
The finger-points look through like rosy blooms:&lt;br&gt;
Your eyes smile peace. The pasture gleams and glooms&lt;br&gt;
'Neath billowing skies that scatter and amass.&lt;br&gt;
All round our nest, far as the eye can pass,&lt;br&gt;
Are golden kingcup-fields with silver edge&lt;br&gt;
Where the cow-parsley skirts the hawthorn-hedge.&lt;br&gt;
'Tis visible silence, still as the hour-glass.&lt;br&gt;
Deep in the sun-searched growths the dragon-fly&lt;br&gt;
Hangs like a blue thread loosened from the sky:--&lt;br&gt;
So this wing'd hour is dropt to us from above.&lt;br&gt;
Oh! clasp we to our hearts, for deathless dower,&lt;br&gt;
This close-companioned inarticulate hour&lt;br&gt;
When twofold silence was the song of love.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rvl4Qo-z_KM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love's Yearning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck - Che farò senza Euridice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of Orfeo and Euridice is popular among composers. The hero,
Orpheus, is a master musician who can tame nature with his music. His beloved
Euridice dies and is taken to the Greek underworld. Missing his lover,
Orpheus travels into the underworld and charms Hades, the god of the
dead, with his music. As a result, Hades promises that Euridice can live and
return to the world of the living so long as Orpheus doesn't look back to see
if she follows him on the way home. Inevitably, Orpheus looks back and Euridice
is, once again, struck dead. It's at this point in the opera that we hear the
following aria for counter-tenor (the highest natural voice for a man to
sing). The title means, "What shall I do without Euridice?".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What will I do without Euridice&lt;br&gt;
Where will I go without my wonderful one.&lt;br&gt;
Euridice, oh God, answer&lt;br&gt;
I am entirely your loyal one.&lt;br&gt;
Euridice! Ah, it doesn´t give me&lt;br&gt;
any help, any hope&lt;br&gt;
neither this world, neither heaven.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll leave you to work out what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0mEKeaXST2s" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love's Pain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strozzi - Che si può fare&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Strozzi was a remarkable woman. Born in Venice in 1619, she was one
of the most well known musicians of her age. It is claimed she had more music
in print than any other composer of the era. This success was of her own doing
since she had no support from the usual sources of the church or nobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that if Bridget Jones were from Baroque era Venice, she'd be
listening to this instead of Céline Dion's "All By Myself".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What can I do?&lt;br&gt;
The stars have no pity and work against me;&lt;br&gt;
If heaven will give me no gesture&lt;br&gt;
Of peace for my pain,&lt;br&gt;
What can I do?&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
What can I say?&lt;br&gt;
The heavens are raining disasters on me;&lt;br&gt;
If Love will not grant me a moment of breath,&lt;br&gt;
to relieve all my suffering,&lt;br&gt;
What can I say?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1F458aC_FUM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smetana - Vltava (The Moldau) from Má vlast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the musical antidote to nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Czech composer Smetana uses music to represent the river Moldau as it
runs through his country in a celebration of the landscape, activity, folk
music, dance and industry of the people of the Czech republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works well as a musical metaphor, starting with the trickle of notes
from the opening flutes and building up to a flowing melody surrounded by
melodic eddys and currents in the strings. The river music keeps returning
throughout the piece as different musical interludes interject to describe
some aspect of where the river flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/l6kqu2mk-Kw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Nature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Pastoral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is an old friend of mine. Forget the Disney version from the
animated film "Fantasia" -- this is Beethoven musically representing a visit to
the country and the emotional impact that has on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the latter part of the work he paints a picture of a country dance
interrupted by a storm which he concludes with a hymn to nature. Beethoven
wasn't conventionally religious, but this is a certainly a spiritual reaction
to nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iQGm0H9l9I4" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Humanity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Choral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven's 9th is full of different emotions and a real journey of the soul
in musical form. But the part I want to particularly highlight is the finale,
the "Ode to Joy".&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven was famously misanthropic and that's how the finale starts with
the rather annoyed sounding cellos and double basses. But once the "joy" theme
is found the instruments try their hardest to make something of it. Yet
Beethoven's genius is to interrupt the finale at this point, and start again
with human voices. Schiller's words are a celebration of brotherhood,
togetherness and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it really does have the line, "here's a giant kiss for all" sung by the
massed choir. Thank you Ludwig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/-suf9BL9xRA?start=2663" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Parental Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shostakovich - Piano Concerto No.2 (Second Movement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dimitri Shostakovich wrote this concerto for his son Maxim. Maxim used it as
an audition piece for music conservatoire when he was a teenager. This second
movement is both sad yet hopeful, as a parent lets go and reflects on the child
leaving and growing into adulthood. The music full of love and sadness. Perhaps
if the orchestra is Dimitri, then Maxim is the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TPqMvoR2Buo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Ending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strauss - "Im Abendrot" from Four Last Songs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical and poetic meditation on two lovers coming to the end of
their long life together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Through sorrow and joy&lt;br&gt;
we have gone hand in hand;&lt;br&gt;
we are both at rest from our wanderings&lt;br&gt;
now above the quiet land.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Around us, the valleys bow,&lt;br&gt;
the air already darkens.&lt;br&gt;
Only two larks soar&lt;br&gt;
musingly into the haze.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Come close, and let them flutter,&lt;br&gt;
soon it will be time to sleep -&lt;br&gt;
so that we don't get lost&lt;br&gt;
in this solitude.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
O vast, tranquil peace,&lt;br&gt;
so deep in the afterglow!&lt;br&gt;
How weary we are of wandering--&lt;br&gt;
Is this perhaps death?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Giaf3qSqDHM" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar - Cello Concerto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife, Mary, once played this in a concerto competition (and won).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar wrote the piece soon after his wife, Alice, passed away. The cello is,
of course, Alice and the music Elgar creates reflects all the different
feelings he has now that she is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This very old performance, by Jacqueline du Pré on cello and Daniel
Barenboim conducting, is poignant. They were married but Jackie's playing
succumbed to multiple sclerosis soon after this recording was made. The MS
eventually killed her around a decade or so later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OPhkZW_jwc0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>