<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ntoll.org</title><link>https://ntoll.org/</link><description>Everything I say is false...</description><atom:link href="https://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:ntoll@ntoll.org"&gt;Nicholas H.Tollervey&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 13:54:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>On Debugging</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/debugging/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the stand-out collaborations of my career has been with my buddy
&lt;a href="https://dpgeorge.net/"&gt;Damien George&lt;/a&gt;. He's the creator of
&lt;a href="https://micropython.org/"&gt;MicroPython&lt;/a&gt; ~ a lean and efficient implementation
of the Python programming language optimised to run in constrained
environments. When Damien created MicroPython I think he imagined "constrained
environments" to mean microcontrollers - the small single chip computers
beloved of embedded systems engineers, Internet of Things enthusiasts and the
Maker community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did he realise that MicroPython was an amazing fit for another computing
context: the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="MicroPython" src="https://ntoll.org/images/MicroPython_Logo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The browser is an interesting space in which to work because of its unique
combinations of constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, everything needed to view a web page needs to be delivered over the
network. So, the smaller the asset to be delivered can be, the better.
MicroPython, when compressed for delivery to the browser is only around 170k in
size - smaller than most images you find on most websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the browser is perhaps the world's most battle tested sand boxed
computing environment. By this I mean that web browsers encounter all sorts of
interesting, nefarious, ill-performing, badly written and otherwise shonky
code. Such code should be constrained into a virtual sandbox, so it can't do
any damage to the user's wider system. Because of the recent development of
&lt;a href="https://bytecodealliance.org/"&gt;web assembly&lt;/a&gt; (shortened to WASM ~ a sort of
virtual microprocessor working in the browser), code written in C can be
compiled to run in the browser. MicroPython is written in C and Damien and his
collaborators have worked together to create
&lt;a href="https://github.com/micropython/micropython/tree/master/ports/webassembly"&gt;a port for web assembly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third and finally, the browser makes available to the developer of websites a
JavaScript object called &lt;code&gt;globalThis&lt;/code&gt;, through which all the other objects,
functions and data structures needed to
&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API"&gt;access the capabilities of the browser&lt;/a&gt;
are made available. By constraining developers to a single means of interacting
with the browser, there is only one way to go about making things happen.
MicroPython compiled to WASM has access to the full capabilities of the
sandboxed browser thanks to some of Damien's recent work on a foreign function
interface (FFI) that interacts with the JavaScript based APIs and capabilities
defined by &lt;code&gt;globalThis&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this context, what does MicroPython allow you to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From within MicroPython running in the browser, one simply imports the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt;
module (short for JavaScript). It's an object in MicroPython that acts as a
proxy for &lt;code&gt;globalThis&lt;/code&gt; in the browser. It makes interacting with the browser
from MicroPython an absolute joy. It's worth pointing out that Damien's work is
based upon the &lt;code&gt;js&lt;/code&gt; work done as part of the
&lt;a href="https://pyodide.org/en/stable/"&gt;Pyodide project&lt;/a&gt; (a version of the CPython
interpreter for the browser), so no matter the version of Python you use in the
browser, you access the browser's capabilities in exactly the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But recently, there was a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was due to give a talk about &lt;a href="https://pyscript.com/"&gt;PyScript&lt;/a&gt; (a platform
for taking MicroPython and Pyodide and making them easy to use in the browser)
at &lt;a href="https://europython.eu/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt; and I was putting together code
examples of ever increasing complexity to present as part of my talk. But I
kept hitting strange errors when using MicroPython. My colleague and
web-guru &lt;a href="https://webreflection.medium.com/"&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt; managed to isolate the
problem but had been unable to work out why it was happening. Put simply,
somewhere in MicroPython's FFI, at that point where JavaScript and MicroPython
were interacting, unwanted JavaScript objects were unexpectedly leaking into
the MicroPython world thus causing things to crash. Think of it as a JavaScript
shaped spanner in the MicroPython works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn't a good situation to find oneself in, a few days before presenting
at one of the Python world's largest and most prestigious conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damien and I decided to debug the problem, and we recorded ourselves doing so
because Andrea wasn't available at the time of our call. We figured that if he
could watch our debugging session, he might spot something we hadn't and
suggest a fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, what followed was a lot of fun, and the video of the debugging
session is embedded below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some things you need to know before you watch the video:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both Damien and I know JavaScript to a sufficient level to be
  "dangerous". We can get stuff done, but we're not guru level like Andrea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Damien is an expert in C (the language used to implement MicroPython) and
  clearly knows his way around the MicroPython codebase including the FFI that
  kept crashing. I am familiar enough with C to be able to read it, but not
  very experienced at writing it, and I certainly don't know anything about the
  MicroPython internals, including the FFI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were using a collaboration technique called pair programming: where one
  developer (Damien) is the "pilot" with the other developer (me) acting as
  "co-pilot". As you'll see in the video, Damien was sharing his screen so I
  could see what he was looking at and he'd often describe things, processes or
  problems to me, only for me to confirm them, explain them back or ask
  questions as a way to help maintain focus. As the one most ignorant of the
  language and code-base, I was in a good position to play the beginner to
  Damien's expert, and ask for clarifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our debugging involved taking very careful steps to investigate and change
  the code so the problem was (happily) eventually revealed, tested and fixed.
  As the Chinese proverb explains: when crossing a river, it's best to do so
  slowly and by feeling with one's toes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both of us were having a lot of fun in different ways. Damien was clearly
  fascinated by delving into the problem. I was enjoying Damien's virtuosic
  debugging performance, and found out some fun stuff as we went along.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So grab your popcorn, and enjoy the show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/uqBgSMB9dRY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/debugging/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 11:15:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Rejection and Renewal</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/talk-not-accepted/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;It is a rare privilege to find oneself in a community who genuinely cherish and
support the participation of all. Such company guarantees we encounter folk
who are different to ourselves: an opportunity to learn from each other's
contrasting backgrounds, experiences and perspectives. It's why &lt;em&gt;diversity is a
precondition for growth&lt;/em&gt;: our worlds are mutually enlarged by our differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this isn't an easy journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes compassion, empathy and thoughtfulness to nurture a safe space where
such encounters take place. Participants - through their actions, attitudes and
attention - embody and live the inclusive and open minded ethos necessary for
such a precious situation. This is a complex relationship
between the individual participant's personal outlook and the collective
&lt;em&gt;esprit de corps&lt;/em&gt; that emerges from the aggregate contributions and
interactions of many different individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the challenge: it's not enough for a group to say they're inclusive,
open-minded and whatnot... that's just empty virtue signalling. Merely
"going through the motions" is an ignorant and insidious sort of cultural cargo
cult ~ communication at the expense of community. It happens far too often, and
normalizing such behaviour actively diminishes the possibility of a genuinely
inclusive and open-minded space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather, such a community spirit springs
from the &lt;em&gt;quality of the interactions between individual participants&lt;/em&gt;.
Sometimes such interactions are unavoidably painful: as when a proposed
contribution to a community event is rejected by the organisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet it is at these moments when embodiment by individuals, and the emergent
community spirit, are so important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This applies to both organisers and participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are an organiser of a community event, and have a call for proposals but
limited space, then you will inevitably reject (and therefore exclude) some of
the proposed contributions. If you believe in a diverse and inclusive culture
then this process may feel deeply uncomfortable and paradoxical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is the puzzle you face, and (I'm sorry to say) there's no right
answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the notion that there &lt;em&gt;is an answer&lt;/em&gt; to such a situation is, I
believe, deeply flawed. Rather, &lt;em&gt;how you choose to conduct yourself, pay
attention to the situation and engage with the unfolding events&lt;/em&gt; will reveal
your community's spirit. I hope you choose compassion, empathy and
thoughtfulness over going through the motions of a brain dead cultural cargo
cult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively for participants, it can be deeply upsetting if your contribution
to an event has been rejected. All sorts of complicated feelings may come up
(although some may just shrug and move on). I want to reassure you that it is
natural and understandable to feel sad, disappointed or upset by such
rejection. Lean into such feelings and give them the time and space they
deserve. The worst thing you can do is ignore them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing is what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the organisers of the event embody an inclusive and empowering community
spirit, their interactions with you will be affirmative, compassionate and
supportive. If you engage in good faith such organisers will likely welcome
feedback or suggestions. But please remember they're human beings too and they
may respectfully disagree with you. This is what it is to be in a
diverse community - you'll meet folk with different outlooks to your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's an opportunity to learn!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an exercise in self-understanding and growth, you may want to
explore why your proposal was rejected (if this hasn't already been
explained). Such feedback is best received when you treat it as a gift, shared
with you in a spirit of constructive collaboration. You'll either discover how
to improve your next proposal or come to see how the event in question isn't a
good fit for what you want to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the former, reflect and refine for next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the latter, your niche might be elsewhere, so keep exploring!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the event organisers are simply going through the motions, you'll know to
avoid the event in future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, be you an organiser of or participant in community events, I want
to wish you the best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just remember flouishing and fulfilling communities are all about the quality
of individual interactions, something over which you have direct control: &lt;em&gt;how
&lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; choose to participate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/talk-not-accepted/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>8-Bit Archaeology: Part 1</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/8-bit-archaeology-1/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first in a semi-regular series of posts about digital archaeology
relating to 1980s era 8-bit microcomputers. In a strange turn of events, not
only am I the archaeologist, but it is my own code that is to be uncovered and
interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="section_break"&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim was to democratise computing. We didn’t want people to be controlled
by it, but to control it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~ &lt;a href="https://www.nesta.org.uk/report/the-legacy-of-bbc-micro/"&gt;David Allen, Project Editor, BBC Computer Literacy Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a child, the first programming language I learned was
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sophie_Wilson"&gt;Sophie Wilson's&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_BASIC"&gt;BBC Basic&lt;/a&gt;, written for Acorn's
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_Micro"&gt;BBC Micro&lt;/a&gt;. Without this formative
experience, I wouldn't have become a professional software engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my childhood was spent in the 1980s, and in 1982-ish the UK Government
ensured every school in the UK had a BBC micro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/bbc_micro.jpg" alt="A BBC micro from the 1980s" title="A BBC micro from the 1980s"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A BBC Micro from the 1980s. Source: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:BBC_Micro_Front_Restored.jpg"&gt;StuartBrady, Public domain, via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father was headteacher of a school, and so brought his newly arrived
computer back home one holiday to figure out how to use it. It didn't take very
long to prize the device away from him, and so I started to explore the
"Welcome" software, loaded from a tape via a sequence of squeaks and growls
(representing the bytes to load into the computer's memory). Since I would have
only been eight at the time the
&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/static/files/BBC_User_Guide.pdf"&gt;user guide&lt;/a&gt; was beyond my understanding,
so a trip to the local library furnished me with a new book aimed at kids who
wanted to play games on their computers. The book in question was
&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/0Bxv0SsvibDMTNlMwTi1PTlVxc2M/view?resourcekey=0-kaU6eyAmIVhT3_H8RkHfHA"&gt;Computer Spacegames&lt;/a&gt; published by
&lt;a href="https://usborne.com/"&gt;Usborne&lt;/a&gt;, a title in their famously brilliant series of
&lt;a href="https://usborne.com/gb/books/computer-and-coding-books"&gt;colourful and engaging books about coding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first proper program I ever typed into the BBC can be found on page 5. It's
a sort of text based rocket pilot game... you have to take off before the
aliens get you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;CLS&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"STARSHIP TAKE-OFF"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;LET&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;G&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;INT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;RND&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;LET&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;W&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;INT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;RND&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;40&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;LET&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;G&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;W&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"GRAVITY= "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;G&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;70&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"TYPE IN FORCE"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;FOR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;TO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;90&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;INPUT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;F&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;IF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;F&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;THEN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"TOO HIGH"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;110&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;IF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;F&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;THEN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"TOO LOW"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;120&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;IF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;F&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;THEN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;GOTO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;190&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;130&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;IF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;THEN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;", TRY AGAIN"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;140&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;NEXT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;150&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;160&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"YOU FAILED -"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;170&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"THE ALIENS GOT YOU"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;180&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;STOP&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;190&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"GOOD TAKE OFF"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a vivid memory of my aunt, uncle and cousins visiting at the
time. My cousin Michael (five years older than me) shared a fascination with
computers. As a teenager he was clearly at a more advanced level of
understanding, and it was from him that I got lots of tips, tricks and
encouragement to goof around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I changed line 160 to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;160&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"YOU ARE AN IDIOT"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I persuaded my unsuspecting Uncle Colin to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since he's an engineer I think he got the
impression there was some sort of simulated Newtonian mechanics going on and
took it quite seriously. Of course, if you read the code, it's just a glorified
guessing game. When he inevitably failed to take off, I remember he exclaimed
"how rude", muttered something about the computer being broken then wandered
off to escape any further computer-related space piloting catastrophes. But my
eight-year-old self was delighted. I spent the next ten minutes laughing
like a maniac at having hoodwinked an adult with my modified code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emboldened by this turn of events (and Michael's mischievous teenager-y
encouragement) I soon graduated to a new form of entertainment when dragged
shopping by my parents. I'd wander off on my own to find the computer
stands in retailers. Being a kid, I was mostly ignored as I typed code into
the demonstration machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;CLS&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;PRINT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"YOU ARE AN IDIOT"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nl"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;GOTO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd walk away (after typing &lt;code&gt;RUN&lt;/code&gt;) and surreptitiously observe the next person
to encounter the demonstration machines... all telling them they were an idiot
ad infinitum. I soon realised the shop assistants could clear my
school-boy silliness by pressing the &lt;code&gt;ESCAPE&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;BREAK&lt;/code&gt; keys. Yet I also
realised it was possible for the function of such keys to be modified: some of
the code ran on my school's BBC micro clearly made sure any accidental or
deliberate use of &lt;code&gt;ESCAPE&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;BREAK&lt;/code&gt; didn't interfere with whatever
software the teacher had set up for us to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to wait for the next visit of my cousin Michael to learn how to "improve"
my code so it defeated shop assistants. To cut a long story short it's possible
to rebind the &lt;code&gt;ESCAPE&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;BREAK&lt;/code&gt; keys to the extent that the only way to stop
the machine from doing what it's doing is to switch it off and on again. My
cousin pointed out that the answers to such problems could be found in the
(afore linked) user guide. In fact rebinding &lt;code&gt;BREAK&lt;/code&gt; was explained on page 143
and disabling &lt;code&gt;ESCAPE&lt;/code&gt; involved this magic incantation at the start of your
source code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nl"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;FX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="il"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was off!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I realised the user guide wasn't a boring manual for adults
but, if approached in the right way, it was the source of all sorts of useful
knowledge and information and I merely had to figure out how to find it. I was
also helped by yet-more-computer-books from Usborne and my local library, a
subscription to
&lt;a href="https://archive.org/search.php?query=acorn+user&amp;amp;sin=&amp;amp;and%5B%5D=mediatype%3A%22texts%22"&gt;Acorn User Magazine&lt;/a&gt;
and various aspects of the BBC's magnificent
&lt;a href="https://clp.bbcrewind.co.uk/"&gt;Computer Literacy Project&lt;/a&gt;,
including TV programmes like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/jtMWEiCdsfc" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href="https://clp.bbcrewind.co.uk/programmes"&gt;watch all the original 146 programmes online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the end I learned an important ethical lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving my unstoppable and mildly
insulting code running on a BBC micro at the Mansfield branch of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WHSmith"&gt;WHSmith&lt;/a&gt;, I was horrified to see one of
the retail assistants reprimanded by their supervisor. My joke wasn't funny and
I realised my code had consequences for others. A lesson that stays with me
to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned that revealing technical skill and knowledge can be tricky and,
at times, intimidating to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember getting a severe telling-off after I tried to help one of my
parent's teaching colleagues, the subject matter specialist for computing. I
was still at Primary school (probably around ten years old) and the ensuing
conversation, in front of my class mates, revealed the teacher's ignorance of
some aspect of how the BBC micro created sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation went something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TEACHER: "You can only make sounds like &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;br&gt;
ME: "But Mrs.S, it's easier to make sounds like &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt;."&lt;br&gt;
TEACHER: "You're wrong Nicholas. That simply won't work."&lt;br&gt;
ME: "Oh yes it will."&lt;br&gt;
(I demonstrate the damn thing working.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my enthusiasm to share a cool hack, I undermined the teacher and paid the
price with a bollocking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I wasn't rude. But I was certainly a confident enough ten-year-old
to know I had an easier way to make things work, while being naive to think
this would be welcomed. To be fair, I don't think they did themselves any
favours by telling me it simply wouldn't work. A more open minded teacher would
have said something like, "OK Nicholas, show me your way and let's compare
notes", and used the situation as an opportunity for learning. Yet, as a former
teacher myself, I know that it's often impossible to go off piste in a tightly
structured or time constrained lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such reminiscences are a prelude to the real digital archaeology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I found my old BBC micro, and a box full of floppy disks, in my
parent's loft. With their permission I took my finds to the UK's
&lt;a href="https://www.tnmoc.org/"&gt;National Museum of Computing&lt;/a&gt; (based at Bletchley Park
~ a mere 15 minute drive from where I live). I'll describe the details in a
follow-up post, but with the generous help of others, I was able to extract the
content of the disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By way of preview, &lt;a href="https://bbc.godbolt.org/?&amp;amp;disc1=https://ntoll.org/static/bbcdiscs/music.ssd&amp;amp;autoboot" target="_blank"&gt;this link takes you to an online BBC emulator running a
sort of "greatest hits" compilation of programmed musical performances&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put together the disk
from various sources floating around my friendship group, and included some of
my own code too. The disk's menu system is of my own creation but based upon
two other fragments of code I found in a magazine: one for driving a disk menu,
the other for using arrow keys for selecting items. I'm also responsible for
the rather awful renditions of "The Swan" and "The Road Goes Ever On" (a
musical setting of some of J.R.R.Tolkien's poetry from the Lord of the Rings,
by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_Swann"&gt;Donald Swann&lt;/a&gt;). If I remember
correctly, I was thirteen years old (in year 9, 1987) when I put this disk
together. As we'll see in future posts, it was a significant year for me in
terms of coding and music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the up and down arrows on your keyboard to navigate the menu. Keys like
&lt;code&gt;RETURN&lt;/code&gt; (to make a selection) and &lt;code&gt;ESCAPE&lt;/code&gt; (to stop a piece and return to the
menu) will behave as usual. However, I'm sorry to report I used the &lt;code&gt;*FX 200,3&lt;/code&gt;
trick with "The Swan" ~ you're just going to have to sit through that
monstrosity in its entirety without the use of the &lt;code&gt;ESCAPE&lt;/code&gt; key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"You're welcome", says my thirteen year old self. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is but a small example of some of the fascinating things I've found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In future posts I'll reveal more about my programming, dive a little
into the technology I was using and try to place it all into the context of
my life at the time. As some of you already know, I'm actually a classically
trained musician, and this has some bearing on what I've managed to find... or
more accurately, what I've managed to find has some bearing on why I'm a
classically trained musician, who works as a software engineer with a passion
for computing education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it turns out that the BBC micro didn't
&lt;a href="https://www.nesta.org.uk/report/the-legacy-of-bbc-micro/"&gt;create a legacy of fond memories and technical skill just for me&lt;/a&gt;.
There are many folks of my age who have similar stories to tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy new year! More soon...&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/8-bit-archaeology-1/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PyCon Ghana 2022</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/ghana2022/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;It was an extraordinary privilege to be one of the keynote speakers at this
year's &lt;a href="https://gh.pycon.org/"&gt;PyCon Ghana&lt;/a&gt;. I was also very lucky to have the
support of my employer (&lt;a href="https://anaconda.com/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt;) who covered the
costs associated with the trip for myself and my colleague,
&lt;a href="https://cheuk.dev/"&gt;Cheuk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this was my first trip to Ghana (actually, it was my first trip to
Africa), this was not my first Ghanaian interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't begin to describe how important and nourishing the stimulating
interactions I've had with Ghana based friends Mannie and Michael have been.
Two years ago we were introduced by our mutual friend Conrad Ho, and since then
have met every month, in video calls, to discuss Python in education. The work
done by the Ghanaian Python community to engage in educational activities is
truly inspiring, and you can find out more
&lt;a href="https://www.pythonghana.org/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That both Mannie and Michael are part of the PyCon Ghana organising team, and
this year's focus was on Python in education give a clue as to how I got
invited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/accra.jpg" alt="A view from our accommodation"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The view of Accra from our accommodation.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an eventful flight to Accra, both Cheuk and I went exploring during our
first full day. Adjacent to our accommodation was Oxford Street, containing
lots of shops, banks and other useful things we needed to visit. My immediate
impression was very positive... the Ghanaian folk we met were all friendly
and welcoming. "Good morning", "Hello", "Welcome to Ghana" and other such
greetings were common as we walked through the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also met the PyCon Ghana organisers at the venue. Having been involved with
community organising for well over a decade, I looked on in sympathy and (where
possible) got stuck in trying to help get everything set up. Like most aspects
of the Python community, PyCon Ghana is run by volunteers, and I'd like to
acknowledge their strength of character, friendliness and can-do attitude, led
by their chair, Francis. I saw first hand, that the Ghanaian Python community
is in good hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I was ill on Thursday's tutorial day. My son had shared his cold with
me and it meant I had to stay home instead of attend Cheuk's amazing
&lt;a href="https://humbledata.org/"&gt;humble data&lt;/a&gt; workshop. But the enforced day of rest
meant I was ready for Friday and Saturday at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was honoured to meet &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nii_Quaynor"&gt;Nii Quaynor&lt;/a&gt;
a Ghanaian gentleman who is often described as the father of the African
internet and an inductee to the &lt;a href="https://www.internethalloffame.org/"&gt;Internet Hall of Fame&lt;/a&gt;.
Nii eloquently spoke with considerable experience and authority of the
challenges and opportunities for working with governmental and international
agencies. I hope folks were paying attention since the Python community
in Ghana could be a significant contributor and collaborator in the technical
growth of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also many other interesting talks, panels and workshops happening at
the event which made it feel like a typical Python conference found anywhere in
the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first proper contribution to the conference was to run a two day workshop
on MicroPython on the micro:bit for young people. I have to say this was an
absolute joy and, assisted by Anthony and Joanna, we were also joined by
a collection of teachers, tech folk and IoT curious. The vibe was friendly and
the young people brought lots of energy and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a video, shot on the second day while folks were building a project with
their micro:bit, to give a flavour of what went on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TBsl7WvQELM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the &lt;a href="https://microbit.org/"&gt;MicroBit Foundation&lt;/a&gt; for supporting
PyCon Ghana via the donation of 20 devices for participants to use and then
keep. Every device found a safe home, with many asking where they can be
obtained in Ghana..!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My keynote, on the subject of Python in Education, went well and as usual, I
especially enjoyed answering the questions at the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was especially pleased to channel my "inner teacher" by (half jokingly)
setting the conference some homework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pointed out that somewhere will become known as a place of African technical
innovation. Somewhere will be lauded as having the most accessible and
creative coding education programme in Africa. Somewhere will famously
contribute a uniquely African story to our global technical community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked, "why not you..?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My homework task to the audience was to discover and become their own unique,
colourful and extraordinary community. They already have a small but strong,
vibrant and close knit nucleus from which to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope, in ten years time,
to visit Ghana again and have some of today's community say to me, "see what
we did, and look where we're going...", and for me to be amazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/ghana.jpg" alt="Ghanaian friends."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ghanaian friends.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another aspect of the conference was its friendliness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the breaks I
spoke to many different people, from all over Africa, and drew energy from
their passion, enthusiasm and openness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also enjoyed the warmth of their
conversation and willingness to share games with me... I especially appreciated
learning how to play &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oware"&gt;Oware&lt;/a&gt; from PyCon
Ghana organiser, Hillary. I enjoyed it so much I managed to buy a board in a
market in Accra and have taught my kids and wife how to play..! It's a big hit
in our house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/accra_beach.jpg" alt="The amazing view of a beach from the old presidential residence."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The amazing view of a beach from the old presidential residence.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my final day, the day after the conference, we hung out with the conference
organisers and visited tourist sites in Accra. It was wonderful to see
non-Pythonic aspects of Ghana... its cultural spaces, historic monuments, the
university and glimpse some of its natural beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the course of my stay, I saw the twi word "akwaaba" in many places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I asked what it meant I was told it was a sort of very hospitable form of
"welcome".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Akwaaba" is a pretty good word to describe my experience of PyCon Ghana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long may the Ghanaian Python community flourish and I look forward to 2032. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/ghana2022/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 13:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Code Reviews</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/code-reviews/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As I've &lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/pastures-new/"&gt;mentioned elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;, I've just started a new
role at &lt;a href="https://anaconda.com/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week after joining I was asked to contribute an article to an internal
newsletter called "Consider This!". The format is simple: write something
thoughtful on a subject of interest to folks within the company, and, at the
end, curate a list of questions to prompt further thought and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was invited to explore what I considered important aspects of great code
reviews. Thanks to Anaconda, the article is reproduced below. Additional thanks
to my colleagues Elise and Dan who provided invaluable and stimulating feedback
to significantly improve my first draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="section_break"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask a room of engineers what makes a great code review, and you’ll have as many
different opinions as there are engineers. Yet, in my experience, common themes
and archetypes emerge from the gloriously colourful and diverse descriptions of
a great code review. This article aims to explore what they might be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, a code review is exactly what it says: asking another to review
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why might one do this? Often the simple answer is, “because I have to”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code hosting sites, like GitHub, make it easy for code reviews to be part of
the development process through concepts like pull requests (PRs for short).
Simply make a change to the code, bundle your changes into a PR, submit it and
wait for feedback from maintainers or colleagues. Sometimes you have to submit
code for review because of corporate governance, your employer or the open
source project to which you’re contributing may have an existing review process
for all contributions. Or it may simply be habit or herd instinct to follow
so-called “best practices”... folks do code reviews because everyone else does
code reviews and so they’re living up to expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A code review could be an assessment to overcome, where someone in authority
accepts or rejects your changes. It might involve checking your changes to
ensure you’ve followed stylistic and technical conventions for a project, like
a teacher correcting work with a red pen. Furthermore, opinions about the
approach taken, methodology used or even the intention behind the change might
be offered, like a critic describing a restaurant, film or concert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s another, more engaging reason to participate in code reviews: if
done well, your world as a coder is enlarged by the process, be that as a
reviewer or contributor. In so doing, engagement with the project is a process
of growth, and the quality of the codebase is improved to reflect the shared
goals, ideas and aesthetic of those bringing the project into the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a code review is used as a means of exercising authority then it’s no better
than pandering to another’s ego. Many projects have stylistic and technical
conventions, and checking such things can be easily automated so contributors
are confident their changes meet such minimum requirements before ever
submitting their code for review. Finally, if a critique of the approach,
methodology or intent is offered as part of a code review, then it’s happening
too late; such things should be discussed before code is submitted for
inclusion in the project, perhaps in early drafts (so called “code spikes”) or
exploratory proofs-of-concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the contributor’s point of view, a code review is an opportunity to share
their work so others understand and see what they are offering. In other words,
a code review is an exercise in education as others encounter and explore new
aspects of the code base. From a reviewer’s point of view, a code review is an
opportunity to explore, internalise and offer constructive feedback of
another’s contribution. Once again, it’s an exercise in education as the
contributor is invited to explore their own work through the fresh eyes and
constructive commentary of the reviewer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I deliberately used the word “enlarge” when I said a code review
enlarges the world of those who participate. Enlargement is not synonymous with
“fun”, “positive” or “easy”. The process of enlarging one’s view of the code
might feel uncomfortable (perhaps you’re trying to get your head around a
difficult or unfamiliar concept), negative (you feel frustrated with yet
another bug in a hard-to-fathom part of the project) or difficult (the task at
hand is complex and requires much effort simply to engage effectively).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, enlargement implies growth, understanding and progress, and I’m reminded
of the types of fun mountaineers use to categorise climbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A climb that is &lt;em&gt;type one fun&lt;/em&gt; is fun because it’s fun to do, &lt;em&gt;type two fun&lt;/em&gt;
is not fun at the time but fun to recollect afterwards because of the
achievement gained or lesson learned, and &lt;em&gt;type three fun&lt;/em&gt; is not fun at the
time, nor fun to recollect because you realise you never want to be in that
situation ever again. Given a receptive spirit of learning, a mountaineer’s
view of the world is enlarged through a mixture of both &lt;em&gt;positive and
affirmative&lt;/em&gt;, as well as &lt;em&gt;negative and difficult&lt;/em&gt;, experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how do we foster a spirit of enlargement in code reviews?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe mutual respect is key. Respect involves showing empathy, gratitude
and acknowledgement that, when difficulties arise, folks involved are acting
with the best of intentions. Another key factor is trust, an attribute of a
team that only comes through working together over time, making mistakes
together, and seeing evidence that folks support each other. I’d add that
compassion (an awareness of and sympathy for another’s feelings and situation,
mixed with a proactive desire to engage) is a great way to show support. When
things inevitably become difficult, then compassion for each other is a way to
embody mutual respect and build trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the context of code reviews, such attributes help our judgement to become
deeper, more refined and aware of the wider context of the project and its
participants. A code review is no longer just an arbitrary measurement of
“quality” (have you followed our code conventions?), but becomes an exercise
in mutual learning and improvement that encompasses both enjoyable and
challenging aspects of participating in a coding project. At the heart of this
process is a strangely humorous paradox, as demonstrated by this old joke:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STUDENT: O Guru, what is the secret of success?&lt;br&gt;
GURU: Good judgement.&lt;br&gt;
STUDENT: How do you get good judgement?&lt;br&gt;
GURU: Experience.&lt;br&gt;
STUDENT: How do you get experience?&lt;br&gt;
GURU: Bad judgement!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when folks feel safe to exercise potentially bad judgement (through the
code they offer or the feedback they give), will they be able to gain
experience and learn good judgement. The code review is a place to pay
attention to each other’s contributions to facilitate mutual learning and
growth. This will, ultimately, improve the project as a whole, and help its
participants better engage with the tasks at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But”, I hear you ask, “what things should one do in a code review?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re expecting a “top ten interventions to make in a code review” type
post, you’re in the wrong place. In fact, such naive shopping lists
demonstrate a rather transactional and limited view of the process of a code
review, while completely missing the point I’m trying to make. I hope you
focus on embodying and passing on the sort of attributes that make a project
an enlarging place in which to contribute: mutual respect, trust and
compassion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we could learn by examining what other disciplines do when something
is offered and feedback is given. For example, such a process is at the heart
of musicians rehearsing (no matter the genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This short fragment shows Leonard Bernstein rehearsing an orchestra. Clearly
the triangle players are not playing to the high standard he expects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ebf6_7nHciw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to the relationship between the musicians
involved. How do Bernstein and the percussionists appear to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Folks might think Bernstein is condescending, sarcastic and not particularly
supportive. Others might see him as setting clear (and very high) expectations
through humour. Others might focus on Bernstein’s clear ignorance of triangle
playing and the resulting laughter from the percussionists. That we see the
same thing in different ways is itself an interesting and important outcome of
our diverse and multifaceted backgrounds (and it’s important to acknowledge and
recognise such differences).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important relationship, upon which I want us to focus, is that between
Bernstein and the musicians. Only when there's mutual respect, a feeling of
safety and trust can such potentially difficult conversations, involving the
giving and receiving of constructive criticism to fulfil some important end,
take place. How such discussions unfold will reflect the unique relationship
cultivated between the participants. So long as both parties share a bond of
trust and respect, and we recognise and respect such a bond &lt;em&gt;reflects their
unique relationship with each other&lt;/em&gt;, then we can engage with and learn from
the feedback and what the outcome tells us about the endeavour. In other words,
our world is enlarged by observing their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions to Explore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How has your world been enlarged through a recent code review?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember a time when you received valuable feedback or an important lesson
  that enlarged your world; how was it revealed to you?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your team’s approach to code reviews?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do you and your collaborators cultivate a place of mutual respect, trust,
  and compassion?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put yourself in Bernstein’s shoes, what would you say to the percussionists?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagine you’re the percussionists, how would you respond to Bernstein’s
  feedback?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of a recent PR submitted for you to review. How did you help enlarge
  the world of the author? How was your world enlarged?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/code-reviews/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EuroPython 2022</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/europython-2022/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I had a wonderful time at &lt;a href="https://ep2022.europython.eu/"&gt;EuroPython&lt;/a&gt;, last
week, in Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important aspect of the conference, for me personally, involved giving
my talk entitled "Music and Code". It was an opportunity for me to reveal and
explore how I feel about programming, teaching and learning and the place of
tech in our wider culture. I've wanted to give a talk like this for over ten
years, but only recently have I figured out how to express what I wanted to say
through music as a metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/4McW0mrONLo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important aspect of the conference was friendship and it was a huge
pleasure to be a small part of the organising team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I especially
want to highlight collaborating with &lt;a href="https://blog.europython.eu/humans-of-europython-vicky/"&gt;Vicky&lt;/a&gt;
(a remarkable friend who embodies so many of the wonderful aspects of our
Python community: a pro-active "can do" attitude, an inclusive and
compassionate outlook towards others, and a formidable determination to
thoughtfully do "the right thing" for the benefit of the whole community). The
two of us flapped and faffed to fulfil a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maker_culture"&gt;Maker&lt;/a&gt; space within EuroPython.
Given the amount of positive engagement from attendees, I hope this becomes a
regular feature of the conference. A case in point being the DIY robots
competing to solve a maze in the fastest time, organised by the energetic and
enthusiastic folks at the &lt;a href="http://niraspberryjam.com/"&gt;Northern Ireland Jam&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TGb4g-E70Fk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to mention &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/boyang-dou/"&gt;Raquel&lt;/a&gt;, who
chaired this year's EuroPython. Her clear leadership, &lt;em&gt;from the front&lt;/em&gt;, her
apparently infinite energy, &lt;em&gt;displayed through her considerable efforts&lt;/em&gt;, and
her humane connection with folks, &lt;em&gt;embodied by her patience, friendliness and
compassion&lt;/em&gt; are generous gifts she has shared with us all. I sincerely hope
she's taking some post-conference time off, and I want to thank her for
reaching out to me, all those months ago, to become a part of organising
EuroPython. And I have to say all my fellow organisers were an absolute joy to
work with. Their collective courtesy, hard work, enthusiasm and friendliness is
a very rare and special thing that I hope we can sustain, nourish and
cultivate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other group of friends deserves a mention - my fellow maintainers of
&lt;a href="https://codewith.mu/"&gt;the Mu code editor&lt;/a&gt;. It was a huge amount of fun for us
to be together in the same place for the first time ever. I was especially
delighted to meet &lt;a href="https://github.com/xbecas"&gt;Vasco&lt;/a&gt;, face to face, for the
first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final part of EuroPython were two days of "code sprints", where open-source
collaborators work together on their projects, meet to discuss technical and
other aspects of our collective work, and welcome new collaborators and friends
to our efforts. We, the maintainers of Mu, had a wonderful time focusing on
Mu related things, and collaborating with new contributors who have made
welcome enhancements to Mu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a picture of all the Mu maintainers at EuroPython:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/mu_maintainers.jpg" alt="The five core Mu maintainers" title="The five core Mu maintainers"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The five core Mu maintainers:
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tjguk"&gt;Tim&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tmontes"&gt;Tiago&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/carlosperate"&gt;Carlos&lt;/a&gt;,
myself and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/xbecas"&gt;Vasco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I heard many wonderful talks, enjoyed the conversations with many
friends old and new in the famous corridor track and took part in some really
stimulating workshops (with my amazing daughter, who was attending her first
PyCon as a proper attendee with an interest in data science - she especially
enjoyed both
&lt;a href="https://djangogirls.org/en/dublin/"&gt;Django Girls&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://ep2022.europython.eu/humble-data"&gt;Humble Data&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love EuroPython's culturally cosmopolitan feeling, something that's hard to
recreate at a national PyCon. I love how folks keep coming back to EuroPython,
there are people who mean a lot to me, who I only ever see at this conference.
I also love EuroPython's peripatetic nature, as a community we are welcomed to
all sorts of fun places and have an opportunity to soak up the vibe of
different countries and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long may it last, and I hope to see you at next year's EuroPython.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/europython-2022/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2022 13:20:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pastures New</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/pastures-new/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been a freelance software engineer for almost 17 years. In that time, as
is usual for a freelancer, I have changed roles every 18 months to two years.
Often I took time off between gigs to work on personal projects, write, reflect
or learn something new. For instance, in 2008 I left my role as a senior .NET
developer for an investment bank in London to learn Python, then reset my
career as a junior Python coder three months later and never looked back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've relished my freedom and independence, and it has been a privilege to work
on a huge variety of projects for a diverse range of companies in many
different sectors. I have been enriched by my colleagues, made many wonderful
friends, and learned a huge amount from folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet change is in the air... Since January I've been in discussions with
&lt;a href="https://www.anaconda.com/"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt; and from today (the Northern Hemisphere's
summer solstice no less!), I'm delighted to reveal I'll be joining them as
a principal engineer. Long may the sun shine on this endeavour. 🌞&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; big change for me and my family is that I'm an employee rather than
freelancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big factor in persuading me to step away from freelancing were the folks I
met in interviews and the company culture I encountered leading up to my offer
of employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important factor was the nature of the work I'll be doing. I can't go
into details, but I'm very excited to work with an exceptionally talented group
of folks, on something that I'll relish getting my teeth into. Importantly, it
is an opportunity for me to bring together and use skills from many different
aspects of my background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Anaconda understand what motivates folks passionate about creative
coding: I'll still be active as an open source contributor and will continue to
develop projects such as &lt;a href="https://codegrades.com/"&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; in my own time,
as has been the case so far.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's to new adventures.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/pastures-new/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Complete</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offa-all/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;For completeness, here's a list of all the Offa's Dyke related blog posts in
chronological order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-1/"&gt;Day 1&lt;/a&gt; - Chepstow, pizza and first steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-2/"&gt;Day 2&lt;/a&gt; - Monmouth to Pandy over rolling countryside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-3-4-5/"&gt;Days 3, 4 and 5&lt;/a&gt; - Things don't go to plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-6/"&gt;Day 6&lt;/a&gt; - The Centre for Alternative Technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-7-8-9/"&gt;Days 7, 8 and 9&lt;/a&gt; - Shropshire hills, Welsh lakes and castles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-final/"&gt;Days 10, 11 and 12&lt;/a&gt; - Improvising and going with the flow to our destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offa-all/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Days 10, 11 and 12:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-final/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We found our relaxing rhythm during the final few days of our holiday. Our lack
of a plan allowed us to follow our noses, and intuitively improvise an itinerary
during each day. As you'll see from the photos below, we spent a lot of time
focusing on four things: historic monuments, gardens, food and travel through
beautiful places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our tenth day started with breakfast in Ruthin, at Gail's coffee and tea rooms
on Upper Clwyd Street. Many of our stop overs have provided us with spectacular
food and drink, and the vegetarian full cooked breakfast at this modest and
out of the way cafe was up there with the best. Their friendly chef suggested
a few sights to see in Ruthin and furnished us with a map. And so our typical
modus operandi of chatting with locals and improvising on the spur of the
moment led us to the grounds of Ruthin castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/ruthin_castle_display.jpg" alt="Peacocks in the gardens of Ruthin Castle." title="Peacocks in the gardens of Ruthin Castle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Peacocks in the gardens of Ruthin Castle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chef at Gail's had explained the peacocks who live in the castle grounds
were a friendly bunch, and we were not disappointed to find several of them
displaying to the peahens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/ruthin_castle_gardens.jpg" alt="Ruthin Castle gardens." title="Ruthin Castle gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ruthin Castle gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The castle itself was undergoing renovation, since the original fortified
remains had been converted into a stately pile during the 19th century, and
were now used as a hotel of some sort. With the abundance of dramatic castles
in this part of the world, it was inevitable we'd find a few that had been
repurposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our chef at Gail's also suggested we visit the Ruthin Arts Centre, and we
spent an extended period of time wandering the relatively small but open plan
galleries. Both Mary and I particularly enjoyed the exhibition of
husband-and-wife artists
&lt;a href="https://paulineburbidge-quilts.com/"&gt;Pauline Burbridge&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://charlespoulsenartwork.co.uk/"&gt;Charlie Poulsen&lt;/a&gt;. We immersed ourselves
in the artworks and lost track of time... as we encountered the art in three
distinct phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow wandering around the exhibition as we let our intuition guide us as we
were drawn different pieces,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a sort of inquisitive "deep dive" as we read the prose attached to the
exhibitions and watched a couple of videos where the artists describe their
works, process and intents,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a recapitulation as we explore the exhibition one final time now that we're
more familiar with the pieces, the artists and the story being told.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/artwork.jpg" alt="A fragment from a Charlie Poulsen piece." title="A fragment from a Charlie Poulsen piece."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A fragment from a Charlie Poulsen piece.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a wonderful state of mind to inhabit and we both wished there had
been more of this to explore and encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having put us both in a thoughtful mood, and given the glorious weather, Mary
suggested we go visit &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bodnant_Garden"&gt;Bodnant garden&lt;/a&gt;
to continue our pensive strolling. Since we had the car and we felt like
touring through North Wales, we instructed the sat-nav and slowly wound our way
to our destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/bodnant_gardens.jpg" alt="Bodnant gardens." title="Bodnant gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bodnant gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found ourselves in a large and
varied garden containing an abundance of benches on which we could both sit,
look, listen and soak up our surroundings. I think my favourite aspect of the
gardens were the woods containing paths and shallow brooks and many different
sorts of tree and woodland life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with the art gallery, our slow meandering meant we encountered and
re-encountered aspects of the garden in a manner that encouraged a slow and
thoughtful attention to all the ways the garden stimulated our senses: the
colourful floral displays, smell of pine, sound of running water or warmth of
the sun touching our faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/bodnant_gardens_terrace.jpg" alt="Bodnant gardens terraces." title="Bodnant gardens terraces."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Bodnant gardens terraces.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening we found ourselves staying at a community run inn that was
holding a quiz night. After an early dinner we joined the locals and had a
friendly evening answering questions about such diverse topics as the game of
Cluedo, Elton John's back catalogue, the plural noun for crows (it's a "murder"
of crows, in case you're wondering), and other out of the way trivia. The quiz
was both taken seriously, yet in a spirit of silliness, as many of the locals
made humorous commentary of the emerging themes in the questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, our modus operandi of chatting with locals and improvising on the
spur of the moment led us to something fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our penultimate day started with the realisation that it was our penultimate
day. So, we decided to make use of the car and go visit the seaside, since that
was the only type of terrain we'd not yet visited during our break. We chose to
head towards Porthmadoc since it would mean driving through the beautiful Welsh
mountain range called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snowdonia"&gt;Snowdonia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey was, indeed a sight to behold as we made our way to the coast, yet
upon our arrival at Porthmadoc we both felt underwhelmed by the place.
Wondering what our options might be, and in the spirit of improvisation, we
spotted a castle on the coastline in the distance and pointed the car in that
general direction only to pick up signs for
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harlech_Castle"&gt;Harlech Castle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/harlech_castle.jpg" alt="Harlech castle." title="Harlech castle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Harlech castle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This well preserved ruin is an imposing sight so we imagined it would be very
busy with tourists, due to its prominence. Yet the village was relatively
empty and we easily got into the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only was the castle an amazing sight, but the views from it were
magnificent as we were able to take in a full panorama from the Irish sea to
the mountains of Snowdonia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/harlech_view.jpg" alt="The view of Snowdonia from Harlech." title="The view of Snowdonia from Harlech."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The view of Snowdonia from Harlech.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its good state of repair, it was possible to explore many different
parts of the castle. For instance, we walked up and down spiral staircases to
get to the battlements and then to the very highest tower. I'm OK with heights
but Mary (and several others) found the drop from the walls rather intimidating
and so we didn't spend &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; long up there. Luckily it was a bright sunny day
with little wind to speak of, otherwise I imagine the reaction of folks might
be very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/harlech_walls.jpg" alt="Walking the castle walls of Harlech." title="Walking the castle walls of Harlech."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Walking the castle walls of Harlech.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were having our lunch we noticed a cameraman and several people faffing
about and talking about "positioning", "shots" and "delivery". One of them, a
lady in sunglasses, spotted us watching the events unfold and came over to
explain what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out she and her colleague were professional story tellers
specialising in Welsh legends (particularly, the 
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mabinogion"&gt;Mabinogion&lt;/a&gt;), and were at Harlech to
tell stories in both English and beginner level Welsh, to help keep this
beautifully musical language alive. The UK's &lt;a href="https://www.itv.com/"&gt;ITV news&lt;/a&gt;
had turned up to do a short feature on their work and were just filming a
talking head segment in front of the castle before filming the actual story
telling in the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't realise such bardic activity was going on, but both of us love
listening to a well told yarn, so quickly finished our lunch and headed back
over the bridge into the castle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside we found perhaps a hundred people sitting on benches, low walls and the
grass as our bespectacled friend started to tell us a story. I won't describe
stories she and her colleague told. Rather, I heartily encourage you to seek
out such folk and let them cast their magic. In our case, as they told their
tales in Harlech, the story tellers embodied and communicated the worlds they
described in a way that only an oral story teller can. The best special effects
happen as part of the story seen inside one's head, the interaction between the
story teller and their audience adds an extra dimension of connectivity to the
telling of tales that our screen laden world often lacks and, ultimately, our
stories are just that... connections between ourselves that deeply and
fundamentally move and speak to us through distances of time and space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the video segment broadcast by ITV, it is but a shadow cast by the
brilliance of their story telling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="video-container"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6Oo9uypliq8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must have spent hours in the castle, since we both mentioned exploring the
village of Harlech at the same time. Almost immediately we discovered a small
ice cream shop, selling home made produce made earlier in the day. This was some
of the best ice cream either of us have ever tasted, and the owner explained how
she hand made the produce fresh each day. Clearly this woman had a passion
for ice cream, and we could taste it in abundance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/mary_icecream.jpg" alt="Mary, with her amazing ice cream." title="Mary, with her amazing ice cream."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Mary, with her amazing ice cream.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just around the corner was an knick-knack shop in which I found a piano. On
the music stand was Debussy's &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suite_bergamasque#3._Clair_de_lune"&gt;Clair de Lune&lt;/a&gt; (which I know),
so I rattled it off, after finding a very convenient candelabra to help free up
a hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/nicholas_piano.jpg" alt="Nicholas on the piano, but where is his ice cream?" title="Nicholas on the piano, but where is his ice cream?"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Nicholas on the piano, but where is his ice cream?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was lovely to play after more than a week away, and I even got a round of
applause!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon leaving Harlech we decided to take the long and winding road over
the mountains of Snowdonia, just to take in the views and make space for
enjoying a slow and gently winding journey together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/snowdonia.jpg" alt="Snowdonia." title="Snowdonia."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Snowdonia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the morning of our final day (today), we finished the last of many full
breakfasts and set off for Prestatyn to conclude our walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/offas_sign.jpg" alt="The sign to Chepstow." title="The sign to Chepstow."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The sign to Chepstow.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little did we realise, almost a fortnight ago, how different our adventure
along Offa's Dyke would be, compared to what we had imagined or prepared for.
We certainly enjoyed walking the first third of the trail (almost 60 miles),
and we both reflected that the injuries and improvised change to a touring
holiday had taught us a lesson: go with the flow, and unexpected change is to
be embraced and welcomed if you're going to make something of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/offas_stone.jpg" alt="The stone marking the end of Offa's Dyke." title="The stone marking the end of Offa's Dyke."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The stone marking the end of Offa's Dyke.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, as I write this back at home in Towcester, both Mary and I feel
glad to have returned after our journey together. We're especially looking
forward to seeing our children again and giving them gifts we found on our way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think this won't be the last time Mary and I do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've had too much fun not to do it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa10/offas_selfie.jpg" alt="The two of us, at the end of our adventure." title="The two of us, at the end of our adventure."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The two of us, at the end of our adventure.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onwards!&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-final/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2022 13:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Offa's Dyke - Days 7, 8 and 9:</title><link>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-7-8-9/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas H.Tollervey</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Since we are supposed to be on a walking holiday, Mary and I decided to try
out a shorter walk, and one with which we were familiar, on day 7. We were in
Mary's part of the world (the beautiful Shropshire hills) and so we found
ourselves driving to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stiperstones"&gt;Stiperstones&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/stiperselfie.jpg" alt="The two of us walking along the ridge at Stiperstones." title="The two of us walking along the ridge at Stiperstones"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The two of us on the ridge at Stiperstones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived relatively early in the morning and easily found a parking space,
gingerly put on our boots and started to make our ascent. Given we were both
injured in some sense (me with my blisters and Mary with her knee) we went at a
slow and steady pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/stiperstones.jpg" alt="An outcrop at Stiperstones." title="An outcrop at Stiperstones"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;An outcrop at Stiperstones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the top of the ridge (one of the highest points in Shropshire), the
outcrops of quartzite rock make obvious waypoints for hiking. We found several
folks &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bouldering"&gt;bouldering&lt;/a&gt; on the rock
formations and paused to watch them and take in the glorious views and drink in
the fresh clear air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/underfoot.jpg" alt="Conditions underfoot at Stiperstones." title="Conditions underfoot at Stiperstones"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Very poor conditions under foot at Stiperstones.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conditions underfoot on many parts of the ridge are not good, and it's easy to
go over on one's ankle or painfully stub a toe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our slowness was thus more compounded by both the injuries and rough-shod rocks
strewn all over the paths. Yet we made progress and walked the full extent of
the ridge in glorious sunshine and accompanied by larks chirruping
away:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;q&gt;He rises and begins to round,&lt;br&gt;
He drops the silver chain of sound&lt;br&gt;
Of many links without a break,&lt;br&gt;
In chirrup, whistle, slur and shake,&lt;br&gt;
All intervolv’d and spreading wide,&lt;br&gt;
Like water-dimples down a tide&lt;br&gt;
Where ripple ripple overcurls&lt;br&gt;
And eddy into eddy whirls;&lt;/q&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href="https://allpoetry.com/The-Lark-Ascending"&gt;The Lark Ascending&lt;/a&gt; ~ George Meredith&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All told we walked almost five miles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="map-day7" style="height: 400px"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon we visited the small town of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bishop's_Castle"&gt;Bishop's Castle&lt;/a&gt;,
having heard the high street contained a number of book shops and a
&lt;a href="https://poetrypharmacy.co.uk/"&gt;Poetry Pharmacy&lt;/a&gt;, which sounded like it was
just what we needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/bishops-castle.jpg" alt="Bishop's Castle high street." title="Bishop's Castle high street."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The high street at Bishop's Castle - including a poetry pharmacy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end we spent most of our time in the wonderful &lt;a href="https://www.hocmuseum.org.uk/"&gt;House on Crutches Museum&lt;/a&gt;
where I was able to examine some of the old brass instruments from the former
town band (not in a good state), and learn all about local
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morris_dance"&gt;Morris dancing&lt;/a&gt; troupes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poetry pharmacy was another highlight, although I was unable to find
anything to read that suited my mood. Perhaps, given that I usually have my
nose in a book, this holiday is also a holiday from reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening we stayed near &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Welshpool"&gt;Welshpool&lt;/a&gt;
and found evidence of the local knitting circle's guerilla Easter decoration
operation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/welshpool.jpg" alt="Easter knitting in Welshpool." title="Easter knitting in Welshpool."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Easter knitting in Welshpool.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day started with a drive to lake Vyrnwy (you pronounce it,
"ver-in-wee"). The lake is man-made and to reach the car park involves crossing
this rather imposing dam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/vyrnwy-dam.jpg" alt="The dam at Lake Vyrnwy." title="The dam at Lake Vyrnwy."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The imposing dam at Lake Vyrnwy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We timed our arrival perfectly since the car park was empty and hardly anyone
appeared to be around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to walk around the lake until we found a quiet beach on which we
could sit, relax and simply ponder the world. It can't have taken more than 20
minutes to find such an isolated spot, and we spent over two hours just
chatting, relaxing or throwing skimmers into the lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the morning we were joined by various passers-by: a young
family, a Polish couple with their daughter, a group of students. Everyone was
friendly and happy to be by the lakeside and the opportunity for moments of
reflection that it offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/lake-vyrnwy.jpg" alt="Lake Vyrnwy." title="Lake Vyrnwy."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lake Vyrnwy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our walk back to the car we appeared to meet a bank holiday weekend tour for
the "young fellers with souped-up cars" motoring club. The sound of noisy
exhausts, the look of go-faster stripes and the thinness of sports tyres
(clearly, for country roads) were much in evidence. A massive traffic jam was
also in evidence as the posse (what is the correct plural noun?) of young men
in souped up cars, took on the overweight hairy bikers and caravan owners in a
three way battle for the junction leading to the dam. It wasn't a pretty sight
as helpful bikers attempted to direct the traffic, only to be ignored by one of
the other tribes (in the end, the old fellers just stood in the way of the
traffic to control the flow). Well, done to the hairy bikers for their public
service!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took our time getting back to the car, not wishing to be involved in the
traffic chaos, but in the end the blockages had been cleared and the route to
the dam was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended up driving to our overnight rest stop at &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Llanymynech"&gt;Llanymynech&lt;/a&gt;
and spent some time exploring the remains of the lime industry in the area.
This included a lovely walk in some woods reclaiming the area used for
processing and delivering treated lime into barges on the Shropshire Union
canal. Among the thickets we found a huge abandoned lime kiln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/lime-kilns.jpg" alt="Lime kilns in Llanymynech." title="Lime kilns in Llanymynech."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Lime kilns in Llanymynech.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today started with a trip to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chirk_Castle"&gt;Chirk Castle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As members of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Trust"&gt;National Trust&lt;/a&gt;
we got in for free and spent the morning wandering the amazing gardens and
grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/chirk_castle.jpg" alt="Chirk Castle." title="Chirk Castle."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Chirk Castle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gardens ranged from managed woodland to formal gardens with statues and
topiary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/chirk_formal_gardens.jpg" alt="Chirk gardens." title="Chirk gardens."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Chirk gardens.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside the castle were displays depicting different aspects of the castle's
history, including the dungeon, the clockwork for the clock tower, the
servant's hall and a collection of knight's helmets. These final items made
me smile, as each helmet appears to bear a different expression, much like a
medieval metal emoji.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/helmet_emoji.jpg" alt="A selection of knight's helmets." title="A selection of knight's helmets."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A selection of knight's helmets.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon we visited the town of Llangollen. It being bank holiday
Monday, the small town was heaving with visitors (like us) and the tourist
traps were doing a swift trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A highlight was watching canoeists tackle the Dee river running through the
town (they had hung slalom gates over the river). This led us to the railway
station, run by volunteer enthusiasts, and we ended up escaping the scrum of
tourists by taking a trip up the valley in an open train to the village of
Berwyn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src="https://ntoll.org/images/offa7/llangollen.jpg" alt="The river Dee at Llangollen." title="The river Dee at Llangollen."&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The river Dee at Llangollen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we enter the final stretch of our holiday, we're both starting to feel like
all this relaxing and touring is quite tiring. It means our holiday has done
its job: we're looking forward to throwing ourselves back into our usual day to
day routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
var map_day7 = L.map('map-day7').setView([51.505, -0.09], 13);
L.tileLayer('http://{s}.tile.openstreetmap.org/{z}/{x}/{y}.png', {
  attribution: 'Map data &amp;copy; &lt;a href="http://www.osm.org"&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;'
}).addTo(map_day7);
var gpx_day7 = "/static/files/gpx/stiperstones.gpx"; // URL to your GPX file or the GPX itself
new L.GPX(gpx_day7, {
  async: true,
  marker_options: {
    startIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-start.png',
    endIconUrl: '/static/images/pin-icon-end.png',
    shadowUrl: '/static/images/pin-shadow.png'
  }
}).on('loaded', function(e) {
  map_day7.fitBounds(e.target.getBounds());
}).addTo(map_day7);
&lt;/script&gt;</description><guid>https://ntoll.org/article/offas-dyke-7-8-9/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 17:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>