<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/python.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Pythonic aricles by Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>Saying Thank You</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/saying-thank-you</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/saying-thank-you</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/saying-thank-you&quot;&gt;Saying Thank You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Monday 11th September 2017 (9:00am)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year PyCon UK are running the inaugural John Pinner awards for
community service. For those of you who don&#x27;t know, here&#x27;s some context about
John, the awards and some encouragement for you to nominate people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended the very first PyCon UK back in 2007 (I&#x27;ve circled myself in the
image below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/pyconuk2007.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The very first PyCon UK&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a C# developer in a large investment bank in London investigating
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ironpython.net/&quot;&gt;IronPython&lt;/a&gt; (the version of Python on
Microsoft&#x27;s .NET platform). While I was an experienced programmer, I knew
nothing of Python nor did I know anyone in the Python community. Being of a shy
disposition (yes, honestly!) it was with some trepidation that I turned up to
the Birmingham Conservatoire with around 200 other people on the first day. We
were ushered into the hall and a bearded gentleman introduced himself as &quot;John
Pinner, chair of the organising committee&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;I am a Pythonista!&quot;, is how he proudly opened the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained how Python was a language created by a community of volunteers,
that many such volunteers lived in the UK, how some of these volunteers decided
there should be a conference for this community, and here we all are, so say
&quot;hello&quot; to each other, feel welcome and have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that this was not like any programming conference I&#x27;d ever
attended!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first day contained a free workshop for beginner Python programmers.
This sounded right up my street and so I turned up with about 10 other people.
Into the room strolled John wearing a Cheshire cat grin. He was carrying a
large cardboard box containing ring-binders full of paper. Everyone was given a
binder to keep and therein was a step-by-step course for learning Python,
written by, none other than, John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;We&#x27;ll start at the beginning&quot;, he said, &quot;...ask questions and let&#x27;s see how
far we get.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before letting us loose he gave us all one bit of advice about Python that
still holds true today and which I use myself with any Python beginners: use
the REPL with the &lt;code&gt;help&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dir&lt;/code&gt; functions to explore
the language, so don&#x27;t be afraid to poke around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the next two days it became clear that John was a
Pythonic force-of-nature who took part in the conference by training beginners
(like me), chairing sessions, giving a talk, solving problems at the help desk
and even making cups of tea in the breaks. This was in addition to the onerous
task of founding and organising the conference. Most significantly all this
work was voluntary. He inspired a group of people to create a space for our
community to come together. As John was to say at the opening of PyCon UK 2013
(channelling Abraham Lincoln), our conference was &quot;by the community, of the
community and for the community&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John taught Python programming and its community focused values to me and
many other people in the UK. This kind and gentle man understood the value of
such an outlook and, through his own voluntary work as the founder and chair of
PyCon UK, promoted it with great zeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John tragically lost his fight with cancer in 2015. He is a sorely missed
mentor, leader and friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/john_pinner.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;John Pinner&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year is the 10th anniversary of that first PyCon UK and it seems
appropriate that we should celebrate this milestone by recognising those in our
community who volunteer their time and effort to making it the welcoming,
diverse and interesting place that it is (just as John did). That these awards
are named after John is a wonderful way to sustain the memory of this
remarkable man and his ethos of volunteering for the benefit of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we need such community awards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who have never organised a meetup, user group, dojo or
conference, I want you to understand that it takes a huge amount of time and
effort to make such things happen. Furthermore, there are many people in our
community who give freely of their time for others through mentorship, teaching
or simply answering the many questions that turn up on mailing lists, community
forums and online chat channels. There are also many people who write
documentation, create resources and author blog-based tutorials for our
community. It means Python is a wonderfully accessible language that empowers
people to grow, explore and take control of their digital world. I hope you
agree with me when I say that this is &quot;a good thing&amp;trade;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, over the years I have seen many of my friends burn out after
volunteering for our community. Bringing people together is often a thankless
task involving a financial burden too (for example, who pays for the deposit on
the room hire?). Furthermore, some in our community treat those who volunteer
with an air of entitlement that assumes such volunteers owe them service, some
sort of on-call technical support or demand that they should change their
efforts to address such-and-such a point of view. This is a toxic attitude that
destroys our community - it makes it a demanding and unfriendly place to be.
It&#x27;s demoralising and mentally draining for those on the receiving end and
shows a complete lack of respect for others from the perpetrators of such a
selfish attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that PyCon UK want to foster more of the former positive
context and challenge those whose behaviour causes the latter hurtful
environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contrast to the negativity outlined above is where we, as a community,
acknowledge, celebrate and thank people for their contributions. If you attend
a user group, ask questions on a mailing list or follow various blogs because
they post interesting content (and, let&#x27;s be honest here, that&#x27;s pretty much
everyone in our community), why not say &quot;thank you&quot; to someone whose
volunteering helped you in some way? It takes hardly any time or effort on your
part but it makes those who contribute feel positive, proud and happy to be
told that their efforts are appreciated. It gives them momentum to continue to
contribute and, in the context of a community of volunteers, this is the
antidote to burn out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us in the community are lucky to benefit already from our voluntary
work: we&#x27;re invited to speak at conferences, get interviewed in community
podcasts and are the recipients of wider community recognition. The John Pinner
awards are not for such &quot;high profile&quot; members of our community. Why? Because
there are many in our community who don&#x27;t get the recognition or thanks that
they deserve. By instigating the John Pinner awards PyCon UK is giving
&lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, the community, an opportunity to recognise and thank those
oft-overlooked volunteers who make the UK&#x27;s Python community such a wonderful
place to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can think of someone who deserves such recognition (and I certainly
hope you do), then please visit
&lt;a href=&quot;http://2017.pyconuk.org/pinner-award/&quot;&gt;the PyCon UK website&lt;/a&gt; and
fill in the very simple form. It takes but a minute or two. You can nominate as
many people as you can think of, and PyCon UK will make a fuss of the most
nominated members of our community with public recognition, a free ticket to
next year&#x27;s PyCon UK and a rather swanky medal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what are you waiting for? Don&#x27;t just sit there, nominate someone! It is
just a little bit of effort put into recognising a friend, colleague of
collaborator who has helped our wonderful community in some way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Mu</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/mu-pi</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/mu-pi</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/mu-pi&quot;&gt;Mu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Wednesday 3rd May 2017 (5:30pm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mu (&lt;a href=&quot;https://codewith.mu/&quot;&gt;codewith.mu&lt;/a&gt;) is a simple code editor
for beginner programmers. In case you&#x27;re wondering, you pronounce it like
&quot;moo&quot;, and it is named after the Greek character &quot;&amp;mu;&quot;, used to represent
micro units of measurement in the decimal system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote the first version in December 2015 as a Sunday-afternoon &quot;hack&quot;. At
the time I was volunteering effort for the BBC&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://microbit.org/&quot;&gt;micro:bit&lt;/a&gt; project - a computing device for
kids that encourages them to learn how to code. I had already written a browser
based editor for the project but, unfortunately, when I tested it on teachers,
kids and developers it soon became apparent that it wasn&#x27;t a great experience.
While the convenience of a browser-based editor was initially welcomed, the
faffing about caused by the browser-imposed limitations of the editor meant it
wasn&#x27;t a pleasant experience in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problematic situation motivated me to put together the simplest yet
most useful editor I could imagine. I wrote it so beginner programmers could 
easily write MicroPython code for the micro:bit. Et voil&amp;agrave;, Mu was
born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly formulated a &quot;Mu philosophy&quot; to help guide my development
process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Less is More&lt;/em&gt;: Mu has only the most essential
    features, so users are not intimidated by a baffling interface.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keep it Simple&lt;/em&gt;: It&#x27;s quick and easy to learn Mu -
    complexity impedes a novice programmer&#x27;s first steps.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Path of Least Resistance&lt;/em&gt;: Whatever the task, there is
    always only one obvious way to do it with Mu.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have Fun&lt;/em&gt;: Learning should inspire fun - Mu helps
    learners quickly create and test working code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had three goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;An editor that clearly demonstrated the design philosophy outlined
    above.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;An editor with a simple enough code base that an enthusiastic teenager
    could learn from and contribute to the project.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;An editor that was well tested so we could be confident in the quality
    and stability of its code, while giving us the confidence to make changes
    as the project moved forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I used a wish-list enumerated by my buddy
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MissPhilbin&quot;&gt;Carrie Anne&lt;/a&gt; (who is the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;Rasperry Pi&lt;/a&gt;&#x27;s Director of
Education) as my feature guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raspberry Pi is &lt;strong&gt;the most successful computing-in-education
project in history&lt;/strong&gt; if you measure number of devices shipped. This
success means Carrie Anne has had feedback from a huge number of teachers and,
most importantly, beginner programmers concerning what it feels like to take
those first steps in learning to write code. This feedback informed
her &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_gU7sfTrz4c&quot;&gt;keynote
address&lt;/a&gt; to 2015&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://europython.eu/&quot;&gt;EuroPython
conference&lt;/a&gt; where she listed the sorts of things needed for a beginner&#x27;s
code editor. This, in turn, inspired me in terms of prioritising and
implementing features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then something funny happened. My goofy editor became popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that lots of people love learning with Mu. Its simplicity is
often described as a key factor. The wider Python community have also taken
an interest with many fellow Pythonists contributing improvements. It has taken
on a life of its own with a friendly community of contributors and
users. This makes me very happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most requested improvement from our users is that Mu become a &quot;general&quot;
editor rather than just targeting the micro:bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m delighted to say this will happen very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the support of the Raspberry Pi Foundation I&#x27;ll be spending the
next three months transitioning Mu into a &quot;generic&quot; beginner&#x27;s editor. I&#x27;ll be
working closely with Carrie Anne and her colleagues to learn how best to help
beginner programmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mu will still work with the micro:bit, but it will also work with other
boards too (such as those from the awesome people at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt; and MicroPython&#x27;s original
&lt;a href=&quot;https://micropython.org/&quot;&gt;PyBoard&lt;/a&gt;). Of course, it will act as an
editor for &quot;regular&quot; Python code running on your Raspberry Pi, laptop or PC.
I&#x27;ve even created a very simple visual debugger to help you watch and inspect
your code as it runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very exciting and I&#x27;ll post regular updates since we aim to follow
the mantra, &quot;release early, release often&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we want &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; to be involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try out a new version when we release it. Tell us about bugs. Can you think
of a way to improve Mu? What&#x27;s the most useful thing you&#x27;d love Mu to do? Tell
us about the niggles and gremlins you wish could be ironed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, Mu belongs to its community and we&#x27;d love you to join us to take
part in shaping its future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>PyCon India</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/india</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/india</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/india&quot;&gt;PyCon India&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Saturday 24th October 2015 (1:00AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an enormous honour to be invited as a keynote speaker at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://in.pycon.org/&quot;&gt;PyCon India&lt;/a&gt;. It turned out to be one of
my most enjoyable PyCons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; programming community is famous
for being a diverse and welcoming place. Apparently someone once said that
they&#x27;d came to Python for the programming language, but stayed because of the
community. That has been my experience too. Visiting PyCon India reinforced
this outlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is free software in two ways: anyone is free to make use of it in
any way they see fit and it is given away for free. To paraphrase, it is
both free as in speech and free as in beer. Volunteering time, effort and
expertise is at the core of the Python community and every PyCon is different
since it reflects the volunteer community that organises it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 1500 attendees PyCon India is the second largest PyCon in the
world. The reason it is so big is because the organisers have managed to
foster and grow a community of amazing volunteers to run the conference. This
was brought home to me during my first evening in India: wanting to make some
friends I turned up at the conference venue to volunteer in some way. I ended
up stuffing 1500 swag bags (full of leaflets from the conference sponsors),
in what can only be described as a nerdy form of &quot;keep-fit&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works like this: volunteers
run around in circles holding open bags while others stand in the middle
throwing &quot;swag&quot; into them. At the end of each lap yet more volunteers are on
hand to stack the bags ready for distribution to the attendees the next day.
This process starts haphazardly, but people change roles and slot
themselves in where there are bottlenecks in order to improve the efficiency
of the &quot;bag stuffing algorithm&quot;. Other techniques to speed things up included
shouting a lot, chanting and laughing at each other. This process is
beautifully illustrated in the following video of a &quot;lap&quot; that I took on my
mobile phone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Ejr6iqqCdhc?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the evening we were a well oiled machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, the first full conference day, was interesting - I was still used
to UK time so when my alarm went off at 6am (or around 1:30 am UK time) I
decided to sleep in for &quot;just another 10 minutes&quot;. Four hours later I was
woken by a phone call from reception. An Indian buddy had turned up at my
hotel to look for me and give me a lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&#x27;d come on a motorbike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d never been on a motorbike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my first time on a motorbike was sitting on the back, hanging onto this
dude&#x27;s back pack, no helmet, dust in my eyes, zipping through Bangalore&#x27;s
morning rush-hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Is it safe?&quot; I asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Of course it is...&quot;, he replied. &quot;The traffic is so bad we never go faster than 15 mph anyway!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick appears to be not to pay attention to all the car horns, shouting
and never to look over your shoulder at what could squish you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also observed that traffic lights in Bangalore are only for decorative
purposes. I particularly enjoyed getting stuck at a junction and giving an
ancient lady in a colourful sari sat on the back of an adjacent moped a
big grin and having it returned (but without teeth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following video (taken from the relative safety of a taxi) doesn&#x27;t
even begin to convey the chaos of the traffic in Bangalore. Can you spot the
stray cow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6KOLKBoPF9A?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of the conference I found everyone, without exception,
to be very friendly and I was made to feel very welcome. Thank you to my new
friends in India for your wonderful warm hospitality. I hope that if you ever
make it to the UK we&#x27;ll be able to welcome you as well as you did me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday was the day of my keynote. I was addressing all 1500 delegates in
the main hall and I&#x27;d chosen to focus on education as the topic of my
presentation. I was actually really looking forward to giving the talk and
had a lot of fun whilst giving it. The live demo went well, people laughed at
my jokes, they had lots of interesting questions and it took me about an hour
and a half to field all the comments I received in the corridor afterwards.
In fact, one of the organisers told me that my keynote was a top trending item
on Twitter in India. Wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the whole thing in the video below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Q3kXXtlviiM?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I love to get feedback (both good and bad). Please feel free to
&lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;drop me a line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special mention should be made of the two main organisers, Vijay Kumar and
Kracekumar Ramaraju, who put on an amazing event. I&#x27;d also like to publicly
thank my friend Kushal Das and his family and colleagues for being my guides
around Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I go back to India? Absolutely! It&#x27;s an amazing place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a privilege.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2015 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>