<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/python.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Pythonic aricles by Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>The Story of MicroPython on the BBC micro:bit</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/story-micropython-on-microbit</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/story-micropython-on-microbit</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/story-micropython-on-microbit&quot;&gt;The Story of MicroPython on the BBC micro:bit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Tuesday 20th October 2015 (8:00AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a child of the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the formative experiences of my childhood was the arrival of our
first computer. My father was a headteacher - one half-term holiday he brought
home his school&#x27;s computer to learn how to use it. Yet it was my brother and I
who spent most time on it. This was my first program, written in a language
called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_BASIC&quot;&gt;BASIC&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;basic&quot;&gt;10 CLS
20 PRINT &quot;YOU&#x27;RE AN IDIOT&quot;
30 GOTO 20&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the infectious enthusiasm of a number of my teachers: my
design and technology teacher, a gentleman called Eric Rose, showing me how to
program a robot arm he&#x27;d made and the school librarian, Philip Wilson,
encouraging me to explore and experiment with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bulletin_board_system&quot;&gt;bulletin-board
systems&lt;/a&gt; and a long-forgotten service called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prestel&quot;&gt;PRESTEL&lt;/a&gt; (forerunners of
today&#x27;s consumer internet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&#x27;t be a programmer were it not for such positive formative
experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/bbcmicro.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A BBC Micro&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computer I used was, of course, the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BBC_Micro&quot;&gt;BBC Micro&lt;/a&gt;:
the result of an extraordinary initiative called the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naec.org.uk/organisations/bbc-computer-literacy-project/towards-computer-literacy-the-bbc-computer-literacy-project-1979-1983&quot;&gt;BBC Computer Literacy Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Allen, the project&#x27;s producer,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nesta.org.uk/publications/legacy-bbc-micro&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt;
that, &quot;[t]he aim was to democratise computing. We didn&#x27;t want people to be
controlled by it, but to control it.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the efforts of teachers in organisations such as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computingatschool.org.uk/&quot;&gt;CAS&lt;/a&gt; and extraordinary
world-changing projects like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;RaspberryPi&lt;/a&gt;, computing education is
undergoing a renaissance in the UK and the BBC are stepping up to help once
more. The Python programming language is part of this effort and
&lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; can get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is the story so far...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2014 the BBC announced their intention to create a mysterious
computing-in-education project with &quot;partners&quot;. I had recently organised
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pyconuk.org/education/&quot;&gt;PyCon UK&#x27;s education track&lt;/a&gt;,
people knew I was a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf/&quot;&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt; (PSF)
fellow and kept asking me if the PSF was involved. I decided to
investigate and, with the blessing of the PSF board, applied for the PSF to
join said partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BBC explained a staggering &quot;moon-shot&quot; project: to create a small,
computing device to be delivered to &lt;strong&gt;ALL&lt;/strong&gt; year 7 children
(11-12 years old) in the UK. The newly christened
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/mediapacks/microbit&quot;&gt;BBC micro:bit&lt;/a&gt;
would facilitate the first step towards inspiring digital creativity in a new
generation of school children. I could identify with that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/microbit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A BBC micro:bit&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2015 a partnership was formed to deliver such a device
and the PSF were on board to deliver educational support, resources and Python
expertise. The BBC told us they already had a partner to create a Python
&quot;solution&quot; for the device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the spring I volunteered my time to attended meetings at the BBC and
got to know several of our fellow partners:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arm.com/&quot;&gt;ARM&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techwillsaveus.com/&quot;&gt;Tech Will Save Us&lt;/a&gt; were designing
the hardware, Microsoft was to supply a child friendly
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.touchdevelop.com/&quot;&gt;development environment&lt;/a&gt; and many
more were tackling other aspects of the project. I spent my time working out
how to engage with our extensive network of Python-using teachers who could
experiment with the device, create resources and train colleagues. I also
wondered how to engage the wider Python community who, I was certain,
would be very excited by the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I encountered two problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the project is covered by an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-disclosure_agreement&quot;&gt;NDA&lt;/a&gt;.
The partnership agreement states that when the device is delivered all the
resources needed to recreate the project are to be released under an open
license ~ the laudable intention being an unencumbered legacy so others can
build upon and adapt the work of the partnership. The NDA exists for the same
reason there&#x27;s a pre-broadcast NDA in place for the makers of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006q2x0&quot;&gt;Doctor Who&lt;/a&gt;:
it avoids spoilers that would lessen the impact of the launch. Unfortunately,
saying &quot;NDA&quot; to anyone from a free software background (such as Python) is a
sure-fire way to turn them off (at best) or become hostile (at worst). This
wouldn&#x27;t be an easy sell!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, at the end of April I was asked to a meeting at the BBC where
I was told the partner tasked to supply Python had dropped out. &quot;We must
have Python on the micro:bit&quot; said the BBC. &quot;I think you want the moon on a
stick&quot; I thought. Nevertheless, I agreed to look at Microsoft&#x27;s TouchDevelop
platform with a view to creating a version of Python to sit on top of the
development environment and cloud based compilation service. I would need help,
so asked those UK based Pythonistas I knew who had the right skill-set and
interest in education to sign the NDA and help me evaluate what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/TouchDevelop&quot;&gt;TouchDevelop&lt;/a&gt; is a
fascinating open source project: it&#x27;s a browser based visual IDE for kids that
generates a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://json.org/&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt; based
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_syntax_tree&quot;&gt;AST&lt;/a&gt; that&#x27;s
turned into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B&quot;&gt;C++&lt;/a&gt; and sent
to ARM&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mbed.com/en/&quot;&gt;mBed&lt;/a&gt; cloud compilation service.
Ultimately, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intel_HEX&quot;&gt;hex&lt;/a&gt; file
is delivered to the user&#x27;s browser and downloaded onto their local file-system.
Plugging in the micro:bit makes it appear as USB storage and you flash it
by dragging the hex file onto the device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is, of course, a dynamic interpreted language rather than a static
compiled language such as the one used by TouchDevelop. Furthermore, a version
of Python that compiled to the TouchDevelop AST would be a completely new
language - a Pythonic
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shim_(computing)&quot;&gt;shim&lt;/a&gt; to make
TouchDevelop feel like Python. Finally, TouchDevelop itself is written in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TypeScript&quot;&gt;TypeScript&lt;/a&gt;, an
interesting Microsoft-developed language that compiles to JavaScript. None of
us evaluating TouchDevelop knew TypeScript and the thought of creating a
new compiler for a sort-of-Python, frankly, gave us the collywobbles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, designing and creating something Python-ish to work on
TouchDevelop appeared to be impossibly difficult (or difficultly impossible,
depending on how you looked at it) for a handful of volunteers working in
their spare time in an unfamiliar language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at this time that something amazing happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at a partner&#x27;s meeting at the BBC and, quite by accident, struck up a
tea-break conversation with &quot;Jonny from ARM, pleased to meet you&quot;. It turned
out that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaustin&quot;&gt;Jonny&lt;/a&gt; is a fellow geek, but
one that inhabits a different layer of the computing stack (I generally work
in high level languages like Python or JavaScript, Jonny feels more at home
close to the bare metal hacking hardware).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we&#x27;d figured out the above, Jonny asked, &quot;have you ever heard of &lt;a href=&quot;http://micropython.org&quot;&gt;MicroPython&lt;/a&gt;?&quot; (MicroPython is a full
re-implementation of Python 3 for microcontrollers used in small devices such
as the micro:bit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Why yes&quot;, I replied, &quot;I&#x27;ve spoken to Damien several times over the phone
since he was invited to speak at last year&#x27;s PyCon UK&quot;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dpgeorge&quot;&gt;Damien&lt;/a&gt; is the Cambridge based creator of MicroPython).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Cool, I know Damien too, he&#x27;s my next-door-neighbour&quot;, explained Jonny,
after which he casually told me, &quot;you know, it should be possible to get
MicroPython to run on the micro:bit&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Really..? The BBC had told me they&#x27;d looked into MicroPython but the
device had the wrong chipset...&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Oh, that was correct for the prototype. But we&#x27;ve changed the chipset.
I&#x27;m pretty certain it&#x27;ll work now.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after I went to see Damien in Cambridge. I explained the project and
he agreed he&#x27;d be willing to volunteer some time to explore porting MicroPython
onto the device (Damien, like me, has a full time job). I organised for him to
sign the NDA and Jonny supplied Damien with the appropriate things needed
to compile MicroPython for the target chipset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a week later (at the very end of May) Damien emailed myself, Jonny
and a few interested people at the BBC:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Thanks Jonny for the nRF mkit dev board, it has proved very useful!
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
I signed up to mbed, exported the blinky example for the mkit and got
it compiling locally using a local toolchain.  And then using this I
managed to get MicroPython compiling and running on the mkit!  There
is a surprisingly large amount of room: I could enable floating point
support, aribitrary precision integers, most of the Python features
and a few builtin modules.  The REPL works over the USB-UART with
history and tab completion.  It even has a working ctrl-C (meaning you
can break out of an infinite loop).  I implemented a basic &quot;pyb&quot;
module with LED and Switch classes, and a delay function.  So you can
do something like:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
led = pyb.LED(1)&lt;br&gt;
while True:&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;led.toggle()&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;pyb.delay(100)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not ashamed to say that I danced around the room fist-pumping the air
shouting &quot;woo hoo&quot; when I read Damien&#x27;s email. It confirmed there was a real
possibility of getting &lt;strong&gt;proper Python to run directly on the
device itself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week later I was in London for another partner&#x27;s meeting where I was to
get my hands on one of the very first batch of final-design devices.
It was heartbreaking to be given such a cool device only to have to pass it to
Jonny with the sad plea, &quot;can you post this through Damien&#x27;s letter box
please?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next days Damien, Jonny and I kept in touch as Damien worked
around some teething problems. Then, on the 17th June, Damien emailed
again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Using your new USB serial firmware and demo program I have now got
MicroPython running on the micro:bit!&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally had confirmation that MicroPython was going to work on the
device! Much dancing, fist-pumping and shouts of &quot;woo hoo&quot; took place as I
emailed the BBC with the good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They asked how we could integrate our work into TouchDevelop so I embarked
upon writing a browser-based code editor (starting from the excellent
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ace.c9.io/&quot;&gt;ace&lt;/a&gt; editor). This is mostly done apart from
some design tweaks. It&#x27;s currently embedded in a test instance of
TouchDevelop and works really well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, because this is Python we don&#x27;t have to use the cloud
compilation toolchain. Since hex files are a simple format we worked out a way
of encoding Python scripts written in the editor in such a way that
they can be inserted into the appropriate place in MicroPython&#x27;s hex file.
When the device starts up it discovers the embedded Python and the script
is automatically run. Since the size of the MicroPython hex file is a lot less
than say, the total size of the BBC&#x27;s news
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news&quot;&gt;frontpage&lt;/a&gt;, we embed the hex file
within our HTML (it&#x27;s in a hidden div) and do all the processing locally in the
user&#x27;s browser. It means the Python editor will work offline. We also have a
non-TouchDevelop version to run from your local filesystem (so you
don&#x27;t need to be connected to the internet at all!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it&#x27;s possible to use the Python
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop&quot;&gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt;
via the USB connection. It means it&#x27;s possible to &quot;live code&quot; the device by
typing commands into a prompt, just like I used to do on my
old BBC Micro. It&#x27;s a wonderful mechanism for playful exploration and
experimentation so kids and teachers get to see the results of their code
running immediately on the device. Such a tight feedback loop is very
useful and lots of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, we&#x27;ve implemented a &lt;code&gt;microbit&lt;/code&gt; module to
access the device&#x27;s hardware (a couple of buttons, an LED matrix, compass,
IO pins, accelerometer and so on). We also held a code sprint at
PyCon UK a few weeks ago and, after various bits of NDA related fun, we&#x27;ve been
able to add some wonderful new collaborators. We&#x27;re pushing ahead on interesting
new capabilities such as game-related functionality, optimizations
so it&#x27;s easy to create animations on the LED display and a music API: connect
a speaker via crocodile clips to the IO pins and listen to bleeps and
bloops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below, created for a friend who blogs about &quot;favourite
modules&quot;, is a few weeks old but gives a flavour of our current status:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/HAx9sJB1_eY?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also sent a micro:bit to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guido_van_Rossum&quot;&gt;Guido&lt;/a&gt; who appears
to be quite chipper about the project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been playing with micropython on the BBC micro:bit and it&amp;#39;s amazing! &amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Guido van Rossum (@gvanrossum) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gvanrossum/status/653975453691080704&quot;&gt;October 13, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is still lots to do and we are a small team! The BBC
understand the danger of a low
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_factor&quot;&gt;bus factor&lt;/a&gt; (especially
when work is being done by a small ad hoc band of community volunteers) and how
important it is to engage with existing communities who are sympathetic with
the cause of computing education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result I&#x27;m immensely pleased that from today the BBC have agreed that we
can continue our work in the open and outside the restrictions of the NDA. The
micro:bit related parts of MicroPython have been released under the MIT
license and can be found at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bbcmicrobit/micropython&quot;&gt;this GitHub
repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The browser based code editor will follow soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please take a look, poke around and help. If you feel you can contribute I
will &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;no promises&lt;/strong&gt;) to get you a device for
development purposes - but I will need to be confident that you&#x27;ll do work and
push code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can contribute in other ways too: documentation needs writing and we
want to generate educational resources for the device. Get in touch if this
interests you! Alternatively, if you have an idea for a fun Python related
project, tell us about it and I&#x27;ll try (again, no promises) to get you a
device for testing purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions are welcome without prejudice from anyone irrespective of age,
gender, religion, race or sexuality. Good quality code, ideas and engagement
with respect, humour and intelligence win every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; contribute something to a project that will
touch the lives of 1 million children and create a legacy &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt;
can use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>PyconUK 2014 Round Up</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-2014-roundup</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-2014-roundup</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-2014-roundup&quot;&gt;PyconUK 2014 Round Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Saturday 11th October (5:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;(This write-up is a bit late: I&#x27;ve been ill and we&#x27;ve recently had a
death in the family.)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year was the biggest ever &lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/&quot;&gt;PyCon UK&lt;/a&gt;
conference - a community organised event for users of the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; programming language. Just under 500
tickets were booked including 45 for teachers and 75 for kids. We couldn&#x27;t
have done it without the support of the sponsors, especially
&lt;a href=&quot;http://corp.bankofamerica.com/&quot;&gt;Bank of America&lt;/a&gt;, the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf/&quot;&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;Raspberry Pi Foundation&lt;/a&gt; without
whom the education track would not have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the person responsible for the education track, I had most fun
working with the teachers and kids who turned up. I also seemed to be giving
far too many presentations (four in total during PyCon UK). I also realised,
due to circumstances beyond my control, that I have many kind and generous
friends in the Python community and that when disaster strikes people step up
and make &quot;stuff&quot; happen even at 4 o&#x27;clock in the morning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a privilege to watch several masters at work during the education
track:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raspberrypi.org/resources/teach/&quot;&gt;education
team&lt;/a&gt; from the RaspberryPi Foundation are insane, inspiring and intelligent
in equal measure - if you can attend one of their free
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raspberrypi.org/picademy/&quot;&gt;Picademy&lt;/a&gt; events for
teachers than you&#x27;re in for a real treat. It&#x27;s easy to sound bombastic
about the work of the Raspberry Pi Foundation (so allow me to demonstrate):
the pedagogical forces that they unleash are both unique (because who&#x27;d have
thought such a small, cheap and &quot;raw&quot; piece of kit would result in such a
huge amount of interest) and important (because the Raspberry Pi liberates
computing education from the boring sad little world of locked down RM boxes,
presentations and spreadsheets). That they are a UK based effort makes it all
the more important that we, the UK&#x27;s Python community, give them as much of
our support as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also wonderful to see
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stuffaboutcode.com/&quot;&gt;Martin O&#x27;Hanlon&lt;/a&gt; work his
Minecraft magic on both teachers and students. Martin introduces Python
programming via only a handful of very simple Minecraft related concepts that
he uses to build some amazing things within the Minecraft world (his
in-game house that follows you around was a big hit with the kids). He&#x27;s so
good at this sort of thing that
he&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://eu.wiley.com/WileyCDA/WileyTitle/productCd-111894691X.html&quot;&gt;written a book&lt;/a&gt;
on this very subject (that&#x27;s bound to be a big hit with young programmers and
teachers alike - what an inspiring textbook &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; would be).
In case you can&#x27;t wait for its publication you can
&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/folderview?id=0BwqjqhNUlUf1TTFxNEc0d2F6OXc&amp;usp=sharing&quot;&gt;grab his PyCon UK resources here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here&#x27;s a photo of Martin and fellow author Carrie Anne looking like the
cartoon versions of themselves used in their books.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/pyconuk2014-martandcarrieanne.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was especially pleased to welcome
&lt;a href=&quot;http://splashofcreativity.co.uk/&quot;&gt;John Pinkney&lt;/a&gt; and his
&lt;a href=&quot;https://asknao.aldebaran.com/&quot;&gt;NAO&lt;/a&gt; robots. I met John at a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computingatschool.org.uk/&quot;&gt;CAS&lt;/a&gt;
hub meeting over the summer where he described how he uses
robots as a catalyst for all sorts of interesting educational activities.
The visual programming tool used to interact with the robots strikes me as
particularly child-friendly. Interestingly the code behind the visual building
blocks used to describe the robot&#x27;s behaviour is all written in Python (and
thus handily gave me an excuse to invite John to PyCon UK). John gave two
workshops (one for teachers, the other for kids) and the fact that he managed
to keep both groups in rapt awe for an hour is testament to both his
skill as a teacher and the &quot;charisma&quot; of the robots. We also ran a
robot code dojo at which we let the developers play with the bots. I gave a
quick overview of the Python API to the assembled developers and my slides
can be
&lt;a href=&quot;/static/presentations/pyconukrobots/index.html&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FIwVyb9MY5U?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidames&quot;&gt;Dave Ames&lt;/a&gt; also deserves a
special mention for leading a couple of excellent
workshops on using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pygame.org/&quot;&gt;PyGame&lt;/a&gt; project. Dave&#x27;s
workshops involved taking an existing (yet broken / unfinished) game and
modifying the code to fix things and make it your own. I &lt;em&gt;really like this
approach&lt;/em&gt; since it gives students an existing base to work from. It also
makes sure that beginner coders begin the think about debugging their own and
other people&#x27;s code (for which we provided all attendees with a PyCon UK
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging&quot;&gt;Debug Duck&lt;/a&gt;.
This rather excellent state of affairs is wonderfully encapsulated in the
following video from the kids&#x27; day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/kxD2XbTDyjk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/teknoteacher&quot;&gt;Alan O&#x27;Donohoe&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ManchesterBudo&quot;&gt;Ben Smith&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vikkiville&quot;&gt;Vikki Dodd&lt;/a&gt; are three teachers without which
the education track would not function. Alan&#x27;s pragmatic encouragement when
disaster struck (twice) was invaluable and Ben and Vikki made innumerable
contributions throughout the event that meant I was regularly thinking, &quot;Oh
wow, [Ben/Vikki] has already done that.&quot; That&#x27;s what I mean when I say that
people &quot;step up&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an immense privilege and a lot of fun to work with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NaomiCeder&quot;&gt;Naomi Ceder&lt;/a&gt; (founder
of the PyCon US Education Summit) on our own small contribution to the
education track: introducing object oriented programming to teachers
&lt;a href=&quot;/static/presentations/oopy/index.html&quot;&gt;through the medium of
cows&lt;/a&gt;. I especially enjoyed the tag wrestling modus operandi of our talk.
I&#x27;ll leave you to guess which one of us was Big Daddy or Giant Haystacks (a
UK specific cultural reference I&#x27;m sure Naomi will be delighted to quickly
forget). In any case, both teachers and developers got stuck into our
Parrot related exercise (as the picture below shows):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/pyconuk-2014-teachers.jpg&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MissPhilbin&quot;&gt;Carrie Anne&lt;/a&gt; gave
a stonking keynote address to the whole conference on Sunday afternoon. I&#x27;ve
heard far too many
boring-yet-worthy-important-people-talking-about-boring-yet-worthy-important-things
as conference keynotes in my time. Happily it soon became apparent that Carrie
Anne&#x27;s keynote was definitely &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a boring-yet-worthy talk
about matters of an educational nature. If you want
to actually know what Carrie Anne said you should invite her to
your conference to give the keynote. It would be definitely worth it:
evidence via social networks suggests hers was the warmest
received and most highly regarded keynote of this year&#x27;s conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other wonderful aspects of this year&#x27;s PyCon UK included the beer for the
conference meal (brewed using Python), the charity cheese shop that raised
several hundred pounds for a local children&#x27;s hospice and the inevitable
silliness during the lightning talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it was a pleasure to catch up with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/VanL&quot;&gt;Van Lindberg&lt;/a&gt; (chair of the Python
Software Foundation). I&#x27;ll leave what we discussed for a separate blog post
but, in the meantime, you should all totally sign up to be members of the
PSF &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/accounts/signup/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Why?
Because,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The mission of the Python Software Foundation is to promote, protect, and advance the Python programming language, and to support and facilitate the growth of a diverse and international community of Python programmers.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;ve already started planning next year&#x27;s conference. If you can think of
any ways in which we can make it better please don&#x27;t hesitate to get in
touch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2014 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>PyconUK 2014 and the Education Track</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-edu-2014</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-edu-2014</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-edu-2014&quot;&gt;PyconUK 2014 and the Education Track&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Saturday 21st June (02:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write software. I use a programming language called
&lt;a href=&quot;http://python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;. As well as being very easy to learn
and fun to use Python is an amazingly powerful language that&#x27;s used by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/about/success/&quot;&gt;thousands of organisations&lt;/a&gt;
the world over - from the likes of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://google.com/&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://corp.bankofamerica.com/&quot;&gt;Bank of America / Merrill Lynch&lt;/a&gt;,
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nasa.gov/&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt; to small start-ups and scrappy little
websites such as this one. Every day, &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; inadvertently encounter
thousands of digital creations made with Python. By any measure of technical
success Python, it seems, is a triumph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all Python&#x27;s technical prestige, I believe the most important aspect of
Python is the community that has evolved around the language. Perhaps
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/~guido/&quot;&gt;Guido&lt;/a&gt;&#x27;s desire for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/doc/essays/cp4e/&quot;&gt;computer programming for
everyone&lt;/a&gt; set the seeds for the growth of such a community. Of course,
the development of Python is an entirely voluntary affair and inevitably
attracts the sort of person who likely wants to contribute to the wider public
good. Maybe it&#x27;s because the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf-landing/&quot;&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
(the charitable organisation that promotes Python and coordinates its
development) is not just &lt;em&gt;sympathetic to&lt;/em&gt; but
&lt;em&gt;proactive in&lt;/em&gt; encouraging engagement in Python programming
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/community/diversity/&quot;&gt;no matter your
background&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;especially if you belong to an underrepresented group
of nascent programmers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, the UK&#x27;s Python community are a diverse bunch who maintain a
reputation as a friendly, welcoming and dynamic group. Every year we meet
for our community organised &lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/&quot;&gt;PyconUK&lt;/a&gt;
conference. We come together in a way that reflects the widely held view that
diversity and friendliness are strengths of our community to be celebrated
and fostered (to paraphrase PyconUK&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.net/CodeOfConduct&quot;&gt;statement on diversity and
conduct&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past three years we have welcomed colleagues who are teachers of
Python in UK schools. For the past two years we have put on a special
education track to promote programmer / teacher collaboration and mutual
learning. Last year we ran a kids&#x27; day where the proto-programmers of tomorrow
explored Python with the technologists of today. The following videos give
you a flavour of what we got up to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/qOya5R9g1T8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/uPq1VJpMEgw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yerWCR3mppk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/u4IMlpmjbYg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/PXPoc9HCTlo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RZJFdeDpo8w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to be running an education track at this year&#x27;s
PyconUK (to be held on 19th-22nd September in Coventry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophy of the education track is simple: wonderful things happen
when diverse groups of people come together to learn about and explore
empowering technology such as Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a teacher, parent, programmer or young person interested in
exploring technology then the education track has something for you. We have
secured some very generous support for teachers, parents and young people to
attend at little or no cost. Kudos to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://corp.bankofamerica.com/&quot;&gt;Bank of America&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf-landing/&quot;&gt;The Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hp.com/&quot;&gt;Hewlett Packard&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;The Raspberry Pi Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
and our very own
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/&quot;&gt;PyconUK Society&lt;/a&gt; for their extraordinarily
abundant support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full details can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/education&quot;&gt;http://pyconuk.org/education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book now because places are limited!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2014 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>