<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>CircuitPython 2020</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020&quot;&gt;CircuitPython 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 7th January 2020 (05:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/blinka-computer.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My buddy &lt;a href=&quot;http://tannewt.org/&quot;&gt;Scott&lt;/a&gt;, one of the wonderful
people at &lt;a href=&quot;https://adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, recently asked folks
in the wider CircuitPython community to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.adafruit.com/2020/01/01/what-do-you-want-from-circuitpython-in-2020-circuitpython2020-circuitpython/&quot;&gt;share their thoughts&lt;/a&gt;
about what they&#x27;d like to see for the project and community during 2020. This
is my contribution to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three aspects to my hopes for CircuitPython in 2020:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Things I hope will continue,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Developments I hope to happen,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&quot;Moon on a stick&quot; wishes for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to start by reaffirming my belief that Adafruit, and those
involved with CircuitPython in particular, do inspiring stuff when it
comes to fostering an open, welcoming, supportive and collaborative tech
community. This is an extraordinary achievement. My own experience in the
wider Python community is that it takes a huge amount of effort, patience,
compassion and thoughtfulness to grow and sustain such a
&quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/2008/06/scenius-or-comm/&quot;&gt;scenius&lt;/a&gt;&quot;
(and, sadly, this can be destroyed very quickly by only a few bad actors). So
my wish for continuation in 2020 is that everyone involved in the
CircuitPython community grasp opportunities to enlarge positive aspects of
ourselves such as mutual appreciation, the sharing of tools and techniques,
latent network effects, and a spirit of tolerance, compassion and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I hope happens this year is a broadening of CircuitPython&#x27;s horizons.
My passion for tech can be summed up by a quote from David Allen, the producer
on the original BBC micro from the 1980s -- my first computer. He
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nesta.org.uk/report/the-legacy-of-bbc-micro/&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt;
that, &quot;[t]he aim was to democratise computing. We didn&#x27;t want people to be
controlled by it, but to control it.&quot; CircuitPython feels to me like it sits
very much in the hobbyist / enthusiast &quot;segment&quot; of users who already know
something of programming. I&#x27;d love CircuitPython to make inroads into
beginner related education. This probably involves a focus on
learning what teachers would like from a coding platform, honest appraisals of
how beginner coders (no matter their age or background) find their first steps
with CircuitPython and Adafruit boards, as well as making the results of such
findings accessible to all. This final point is important. Learning to code
shouldn&#x27;t just be an option for English speaking, able bodied folk from a
cultural background that means examples and cultural assumptions are
easily understood. I hope you agree that education should be an inclusive
endeavour, and this takes concerted and conscientious effort. I hope the
CircuitPython community find the time and space to invest in the (never
finished) work such a focus entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/moon_stick.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &quot;moon on a stick&quot; is a CircuitPython based mobile phone with a touch
screen and a simple
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypercard.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;PyperCard&lt;/a&gt; like?)
Python UI that&#x27;s easily hackable. Think
of it as the open, easy-to-assemble, relatively cheap and &quot;hack friendly&quot;
version of something like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelightphone.com/&quot;&gt;Light Phone&lt;/a&gt; with all the
schematics and design assets (e.g. files for 3d printing the case) available
under open source licenses so folks can go mod-crazy. Now wouldn&#x27;t that
be a turn up for the books..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll finish by wishing everyone in the CircuitPython a flourishing and
happy new year. Here&#x27;s to wonderful things in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s go..!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>A Classical Playlist of Love</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love&quot;&gt;A Classical Playlist of Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Thursday, 28th November 2019 (02:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my Canadian buddies &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AndreaMcInnes21&quot;&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://snarky.ca/&quot;&gt;Brett&lt;/a&gt; visited the UK in
the summer, we visited the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Albert_Hall&quot;&gt;Royal Albert Hall&lt;/a&gt; to hear a classical music
concert that was part of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Proms&quot;&gt;the Proms&lt;/a&gt; -- the world&#x27;s largest
classical music festival. I think they must have enjoyed themselves because
they recently got in touch asking me to suggest a playlist of
classical music. What follows is my response along with videos of performances
of the pieces I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than put together a playlist of apparently random
choices, I decided it would be interesting to assemble a set of pieces
related to a particular feeling. In this case, I chose love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because love is complicated, tragic, happy, joyful, funny, raunchy and many
more aspects too numerous to list here. The western classical
tradition has around 900 years of musical reactions, settings and descriptions
of love -- plenty of opportunity to reveal a breadth and depth of music. So,
I&#x27;m going to associate each piece with some aspect of love, provide
a short commentary and embedded a video of a performance of
the selected piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to my sharing videos of performances. Ideally,
you&#x27;d listen to these pieces in person at a concert. Only in such a live
situation can you really experience the fleeting moment of the performance,
executed by highly trained musicians and feel that sense of being in a
particular unique moment, together with all the others in attendance. The
videos are a less than perfect replacement, yet still have the potential to
move you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For convenience I&#x27;ve put them into a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yjz2TvC2TT4&amp;list=PLzCYc445IVNTPApt_F6PkGCRRPNfG-JmA&quot;&gt;playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is classical music, it may sound strange to modern ears not
familiar with styles and mannerisms from hundreds of years ago or it uses sung
or instrumental techniques that sound odd because they&#x27;re not used much in
contemporary popular music. If classical music isn&#x27;t your thing, consider
this an invitation to explore a new musical world -- a world that rewards
repeated engagement, an open mind and long term listening. This is music that
makes demands of the listener, but will reveal depths one cannot even imagine
until you experience them for yourself. For those of you who are already
immersed in classical music you&#x27;ll find none of my choices particularly
challenging. In fact, you may even roll your eyes and think, &quot;oh, not that old
chestnut again&quot;. Please remember, this is an introductory playlist, but know
that I&#x27;m open to suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sincerely hope you are moved by the pieces I&#x27;ve selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tender Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gustav Mahler - Adagietto from Symphony No. 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical representation of Mahler&#x27;s love for his wife Alma. Their
friend Wilem Engelberg recollects, &quot;In place of a letter, he sent her this in
manuscript form, not adding a further word. She understood and wrote to him
telling him to come!!! They both told me this.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alma later revealed Gustav left her the following poem with the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In which way I love you, my sunbeam,&lt;br/&gt;
I cannot tell you with words.&lt;br/&gt;
Only my longing, my love and my bliss&lt;br/&gt;
can I with anguish declare.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yjz2TvC2TT4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tragic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky - Fantasy Overture to Romeo and Juliet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tchaikovsky was well acquainted with tragic love: he was a gay man in 19th
century Russia (a time and place full of prejudice towards someone such as
himself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such tragedy and pain as well as an overflowing sense of passion are
skilfully captured in this piece or &quot;musical impressions&quot; loosely assembled to
follow the story of Romeo and Juliet. Listen out for the overwhelming &quot;love
theme&quot; which has become a musical cliché for inevitably doomed lovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3x69wuewkJM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Romantic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergei Rachmaninoff - Piano Concerto No.2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachmaninoff, another Russian, is widely considered one of the greatest
pianists of all time, as well as one of the greatest composers for the
piano. This piano concerto is full of yearning melodies, gushing outpourings of
emotion, tender moments and joyful exuberance. Just like falling in love!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was effectively used in the David Lean romance from 1945, &quot;Brief
Encounters&quot;, thus cementing it as a &quot;romantic&quot; classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rEGOihjqO9w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Denied&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puccini - O Mio Babbino Caro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aria, from Puccini&#x27;s opera &quot;Gianni Schicchi&quot;, comes at the moment where
the daughter of Gianni tells him that she&#x27;s fallen in love, wants to get
married, and if he won&#x27;t let her go to her true love, she&#x27;ll throw herself off
the Ponte Vecchio bridge in Florence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you imagine this sounds like a musical tantrum in the making, get ready
with the hankies and prepare for something absolutely not tantrum like at
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soprano singer in the video, Montserrat Caballé, is simply stunning. Her
charisma, presence, musicianship and vocal control is awe inspiring. Yes, she&#x27;s
the one who sang with Freddie Mercury on his single &quot;Barcelona&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RxZSP1Dc78Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Platonic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms - Intermezzo Op. 118 No. 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms wrote this beautiful piece for his friend Clara Schumann (Clara is
another musician considered one of the greatest pianists of all time and a
wonderful composer in her own right). I describe it as &quot;Platonic&quot; because Clara
was married to Brahms&#x27;s mentor and friend Robert Schumann, who eventually
succumbed to mental health issues. Brahms and Clara were undoubtedly close and
shared a deep love for each other, but it was only ever a love between dear
friends. Imagine how you&#x27;d feel if you had been gifted such a piece of
music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78OO5v0lNtI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fantastical Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berlioz - Symphonie Fantastique&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is sex, drugs and classical music with an added dose of musical story
telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is of the concert Andrea, Brett and I attended. I won&#x27;t
say any more, since the performers do a fantastic job of explaining what&#x27;s
going on. It&#x27;s quite a spectacle (and watch out for the mirror balls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FqTU8m8BJwQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Transformed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg - Verklärte Nacht&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg wrote this piece to closely follow the structure of the poem upon
which it is based, to the extent that the different sections in the musical
score map directly to lines in the poem. The poem, by Richard Dehmel, whose
title is translated as &quot;Transfigured Night&quot;, tells of two lovers walking in the
woods. The woman opens up about a terrible burden she carries. Her lover is
full of compassion, love and support which transforms her burden into a shared
aspect of their life together. I&#x27;m being necessarily vague here so I don&#x27;t
spoil the poem for you... just read it as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://allpoetry.com/Transfigured-Night-(Verklrte-Nacht)&quot;&gt;translated here&lt;/a&gt;
and then listen to the piece. My favourite lines (and part of the piece)
are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just see how brightly the universe is gleaming!&lt;br/&gt;
There’s a glow around everything;&lt;br/&gt;
You are floating with me on a cold ocean,&lt;br/&gt;
But a special warmth flickers&lt;br/&gt;
From you into me, from me into you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the music sounds as if it&#x27;s gleaming..! One other thing you
may hear, the violin (a high instrument) is prominent in the sections
representing the woman speaking, whereas the cello (a low instrument) is
prominent in the sections representing the man speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yzSaOWPBFqA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love&#x27;s Dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fauré - Après un rêve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply a song about a dream of the poet&#x27;s beloved. The words of the
poem (and their English translation) can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxfordlieder.co.uk/song/15&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FlT1QhK4Wto&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Erotic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner - Prelude and Liebestod from &#x27;Tristan Und Isolde&#x27;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I start with this one..? This is erotic music. I don&#x27;t mean humping
or &quot;having a shag&quot;. Rather, it&#x27;s a musical version of a passionate embrace
(between the protagonists, Tristan and Isolde).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In music theory we use the term &quot;climax&quot; to describe the point at which all
the tension in the music is released. There&#x27;s a reason we call it a climax.
This piece has a famously ecstatic climax that takes a while to build, after
lots of tender pauses, gradually intensifying musical moments, soaring strings
and throbbing horns (no pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m sure you&#x27;ll hear what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/W8EQcMurhAI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Orgasmic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orff - Dulcissime (from Carmina Burana)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just watch and listen. No further explanation needed.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/BFq8vH7tPxs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mendelssohn - Wedding March from A Midsummer Night&#x27;s Dream&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&#x27;ll hear this in pretty much every church wedding you ever attend - and
quite rightly, it&#x27;s very uplifting, celebratory and joyful music. Just what you
need for such an occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rIM5cWB2wmM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Moment of Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaughan Williams - Silent Noon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dante Gabriel Rossetti&#x27;s poem &quot;Silent Noon&quot; recollects an intimate shared
moment of love that was both fleeting and intense. Vaughan Williams music
beautifully complements the nostalgic, thoughtful and timeless nature of the
moment in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Your hands lie open in the long fresh grass,--&lt;br/&gt;
The finger-points look through like rosy blooms:&lt;br/&gt;
Your eyes smile peace. The pasture gleams and glooms&lt;br/&gt;
&#x27;Neath billowing skies that scatter and amass.&lt;br/&gt;
All round our nest, far as the eye can pass,&lt;br/&gt;
Are golden kingcup-fields with silver edge&lt;br/&gt;
Where the cow-parsley skirts the hawthorn-hedge.&lt;br/&gt;
&#x27;Tis visible silence, still as the hour-glass.&lt;br/&gt;
Deep in the sun-searched growths the dragon-fly&lt;br/&gt;
Hangs like a blue thread loosened from the sky:--&lt;br/&gt;
So this wing&#x27;d hour is dropt to us from above.&lt;br/&gt;
Oh! clasp we to our hearts, for deathless dower,&lt;br/&gt;
This close-companioned inarticulate hour&lt;br/&gt;
When twofold silence was the song of love.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rvl4Qo-z_KM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love&#x27;s Yearning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck - Che farò senza Euridice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of Orfeo and Euridice is popular among composers. The hero,
Orpheus, is a master musician who can tame nature with his music. His beloved
Euridice dies and is taken to the Greek underworld. Missing his lover,
Orpheus travels into the underworld and charms Hades, the god of the
dead, with his music. As a result, Hades promises that Euridice can live and
return to the world of the living so long as Orpheus doesn&#x27;t look back to see
if she follows him on the way home. Inevitably, Orpheus looks back and Euridice
is, once again, struck dead. It&#x27;s at this point in the opera that we hear the
following aria for counter-tenor (the highest natural voice for a man to
sing). The title means, &quot;What shall I do without Euridice?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What will I do without Euridice&lt;br/&gt;
Where will I go without my wonderul one.&lt;br/&gt;
Euridice, oh God, answer&lt;br/&gt;
I am entirely your loyal one.&lt;br/&gt;
Euridice! Ah, it doesn´t give me&lt;br/&gt;
any help, any hope&lt;br/&gt;
neither this world, neither heaven.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll leave you to work out what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0mEKeaXST2s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love&#x27;s Pain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strozzi - Che si può fare&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Strozzi was a remarkable woman. Born in Venice in 1619, she was one
of the most well known musicians of her age. It is claimed she had more music
in print than any other composer of the era. This success was of her own doing
since she had no support from the usual sources of the church or nobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that if Bridget Jones were from Baroque era Venice, she&#x27;d be
listening to this instead of Céline Dion&#x27;s &quot;All By Myself&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What can I do?&lt;br/&gt;
The stars have no pity and work against me;&lt;br/&gt;
If heaven will give me no gesture&lt;br/&gt;
Of peace for my pain,&lt;br/&gt;
What can I do?&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
What can I say?&lt;br/&gt;
The heavens are raining disasters on me;&lt;br/&gt;
If Love will not grant me a moment of breath,&lt;br/&gt;
to relieve all my suffering,&lt;br/&gt;
What can I say?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1F458aC_FUM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smetana - Vltava (The Moldau) from Má vlast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the musical antidote to nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Czech composer Smetana uses music to represent the river Moldau as it
runs through his country in a celebration of the landscape, activity, folk
music, dance and industry of the people of the Czech republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works well as a musical metaphor, starting with the trickle of notes
from the opening flutes and building up to a flowing melody surrounded by
melodic eddys and currents in the strings. The river music keeps returning
throughout the piece as different musical interludes interject to describe
some aspect of where the river flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/l6kqu2mk-Kw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Nature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Pastoral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is an old friend of mine. Forget the Disney version from the
animated film &quot;Fantasia&quot; -- this is Beethoven musically representing a visit to
the country and the emotional impact that has on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the latter part of the work he paints a picture of a country dance
interrupted by a storm which he concludes with a hymn to nature. Beethoven
wasn&#x27;t conventionally religious, but this is a certainly a spiritual reaction
to nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iQGm0H9l9I4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Humanity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Choral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven&#x27;s 9th is full of different emotions and a real journey of the soul
in musical form. But the part I want to particularly highlight is the finale,
the &quot;Ode to Joy&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven was famously misanthropic and that&#x27;s how the finale starts with
the rather annoyed sounding cellos and double basses. But once the &quot;joy&quot; theme
is found the instruments try their hardest to make something of it. Yet
Beethoven&#x27;s genius is to interrupt the finale at this point, and start again
with human voices. Schiller&#x27;s words are a celebration of brotherhood,
togetherness and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it really does have the line, &quot;here&#x27;s a giant kiss for all&quot; sung by the
massed choir. Thank you Ludwig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/-suf9BL9xRA?start=2663&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Parental Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shostakovich - Piano Concerto No.2 (Second Movement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dimitri Shostakovich wrote this concerto for his son Maxim. Maxim used it as
an audition piece for music conservatoire when he was a teenager. This second
movement is both sad yet hopeful, as a parent lets go and reflects on the child
leaving and growing into adulthood. The music full of love and sadness. Perhaps
if the orchestra is Dimitri, then Maxim is the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TPqMvoR2Buo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Ending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strauss - &quot;Im Abendrot&quot; from Four Last Songs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical and poetic meditation on two lovers coming to the end of
their long life together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Through sorrow and joy&lt;br/&gt;
we have gone hand in hand;&lt;br/&gt;
we are both at rest from our wanderings&lt;br/&gt;
now above the quiet land.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Around us, the valleys bow,&lt;br/&gt;
the air already darkens.&lt;br/&gt;
Only two larks soar&lt;br/&gt;
musingly into the haze.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Come close, and let them flutter,&lt;br/&gt;
soon it will be time to sleep -&lt;br/&gt;
so that we don&#x27;t get lost&lt;br/&gt;
in this solitude.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
O vast, tranquil peace,&lt;br/&gt;
so deep in the afterglow!&lt;br/&gt;
How weary we are of wandering--&lt;br/&gt;
Is this perhaps death?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Giaf3qSqDHM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar - Cello Concerto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife, Mary, once played this in a concerto competition (and won).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar wrote the piece soon after his wife, Alice, passed away. The cello is,
of course, Alice and the music Elgar creates reflects all the different
feelings he has now that she is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This very old performance, by Jacqueline du Pré on cello and Daniel
Barenboim conducting, is poignant. They were married but Jackie&#x27;s playing
succumbed to multiple sclerosis soon after this recording was made. The MS
eventually killed her around a decade or so later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OPhkZW_jwc0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Testing CircuitPython Modules</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests&quot;&gt;Testing CircuitPython Modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Monday, 25th November 2019 (1:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://micropython.org/&quot;&gt;MicroPython&lt;/a&gt;, a project by my
buddy &lt;a href=&quot;http://dpgeorge.net/&quot;&gt;Damien George&lt;/a&gt;, is a
complete reimplementation of the Python programming language for
microcontrollers and embedded systems. Put simply, it&#x27;s Python for extremely
small computers (and I once
&lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920056515.do&quot;&gt;wrote a book about it&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;a href=&quot;https://circuitpython.org/&quot;&gt;CircuitPython&lt;/a&gt;, a friendly fork of
MicroPython, is sponsored by the fantastic folks
at &lt;a href=&quot;https://adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, a company who make playful and
easy-to-use &quot;hackable&quot; technology while promoting a welcoming, friendly and
diverse community of makers. They are led by legendary founder and electrical
engineer extraordinaire, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ladyada.net/&quot;&gt;Limor &quot;ladyada&quot; Fried&lt;/a&gt;.
CircuitPython is MicroPython for Adafruit&#x27;s line of boards and with a
consistent API for accessing the numerous bits of cool hardware you can use
with such devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was privileged to recently complete a block of work for Adafruit: I&#x27;ve
written a CircuitPython module called &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; that makes it
easy for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth&quot;&gt;Bluetooth&lt;/a&gt; enabled
Adafruit boards to communicate with each other. The API is
a simplified version of the work myself and a number of other volunteers did on
the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://microbit-micropython.readthedocs.io/en/v1.0.1/radio.html&quot;&gt;equivalent functionality&lt;/a&gt;
for the BBC micro:bit (&lt;a href=&quot;https://microbit-micropython.readthedocs.io/en/v1.0.1/tutorials/radio.html&quot;&gt;here&#x27;s a tutorial I wrote for the micro:bit
radio&lt;/a&gt;, to make electronic &quot;fireflies&quot; blink at each other over
Bluetooth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new Adafruit module, sending a message is as simple as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()
r.send(&quot;Hello&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving requires a loop (to allow the device to keep checking for
messages), but is equally as simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()

while True:
    message = r.receive()
    if message:
        # Do something useful with the message.
        print(message)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best model for thinking about this module is that of kids&#x27;
walkie-talkies. Each
radio is tuned to a certain channel upon which it broadcasts and receives.
If you send a message, anyone else listening in on that channel and within
range will receive it. You&#x27;ll also receive messages broadcast on that
channel from others within range. 
This is an ideal network topology because it&#x27;s both familiar
yet capable since other, more specialised, network topologies can be built on
top of it. There is potential for users to grow from a simple &quot;walkie-talkie&quot;
model of networking to something more sophisticated and of their own
devising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/walkie-talkie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kids on walkie-talkies&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The channels in the module are numbered between 0-255 and can be set when
creating a &lt;code&gt;Radio&lt;/code&gt; object (the default channel number is 42 in
honour of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Adams&quot;&gt;Douglas Adams&lt;/a&gt;, who
saw so much humane potential in new technology yet mischievously warned of the
polluting effect of technology for technology&#x27;s sake via the inept
work of the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technology_in_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Sirius_Cybernetics_Corporation&quot;&gt;Sirius Cybernetics Corporation&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio(channel=123)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can change channel at any time via the &lt;code&gt;Radio&lt;/code&gt;
object&#x27;s &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; method (continuing the example above):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;r.configure(channel=7)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in addition to sending strings of characters it&#x27;s also possible to
send and receive arbitrary bytes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()
r.send_bytes(b&quot;Hello&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving bytes gives you the full context of the message expressed as a
Python tuple consisting of three values: the raw bytes, the RSSI reading (i.e.
strength of the signal, from 0 [max] to -255 [min]), and a timestamp
representing the number (and fraction of) seconds since the device powered up,
as demonstrated in the following REPL based example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from adafruit_radio import Radio
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r = Radio()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r.receive_full()
(b&#x27;Hello&#x27;, -40, 3245.155408037)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s it! You can find the code in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntoll/Adafruit_CircuitPython_Radio&quot;&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.
Special mention and thanks must be made to Adafruit&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tannewt.org/&quot;&gt;Scott Shawcroft&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://danhalbert.org/&quot;&gt;Dan Halbert&lt;/a&gt; who
wrote the Bluetooth API I used. Because of their
work I was able to create my module with less than a hundred lines of Python
(at time of writing). Thanks chaps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this context, I&#x27;m going to explain why and how I created a
comprehensive test suite for the &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d summarise my approach to testing as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Testing is fundamental for creating and maintaining well designed
    software. My experience is that it tends to produce code that is both
    simple and easy to understand because nobody wants to write complicated
    tests to exercise equally complicated code. The process of exercising code
    through tests forces a developer to think carefully about how their code
    is written while having the added benefit of demonstrating it works as
    expected. Simplicity and ease of understanding are
    desirable properties because such code is easier to read, correct and
    maintain and also indicates the author&#x27;s own clarity of thought (a good
    sign). I also believe it helpful and friendly to write code that&#x27;s easy
    for others to read and understand (I often imagine my code will be read by
    an intelligent beginner coder, because it forces me to explain and address
    my own assumptions about my code).&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;I personally don&#x27;t practice strict test-driven development, where one
    writes tests before writing the implementation. I prefer to explore,
    improvise, extemporise and play at first. I often try various different
    approaches to the task in hand and regularly re-draft. I&#x27;ll often seek
    advice and comments from collaborators, colleagues and potential users of
    my code as soon as possible. Therefore, my highest priority when I start a
    new project is making my code simple enough so that it is very easy to
    change. Often this step in the coding process is called a &quot;spike&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Only when a project settles on a certain architecture, implementation
    or foundation of code do I add tests. I think of this as a sort of
    &quot;hardening&quot; process. When I&#x27;m happy with an approach I&#x27;ll often re-draft
    the exploratory code I&#x27;ve already written, alongside writing tests to
    exercise that specific piece of code. I aim for, and often achieve, 100%
    test coverage (every line of my code is exercised in some way by a test).
    This process allows me to get a feel for how my API works from the point of
    view of a fellow coder encountering it for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;The hardening has another effect: I&#x27;ve baked in an expectation for how
    the code should behave via the tests. I also make sure my tests are
    commented in such a way that a meaningful intention behind the test is
    revealed. They&#x27;re also a useful source of information for future users
    and/or maintainers of my code. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, they
    help manage change.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;No useful software is ever finished simply because the universe changes
    (and so must software). Despite our best efforts, software is often
    complicated and it&#x27;s easy to forget something or not realise how a change
    in one part of the
    code may break another apparently unrelated part. Having a suite of
    tests to check all the aspects of a codebase helps future maintainers make
    changes with confidence.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Being pragmatic, I sometimes don&#x27;t follow the playful explorations
    outlined above. If I&#x27;m dealing with a well defined or mature protocol
    (for example), I&#x27;ll quickly settle on an approach, usually based upon
    research into how other folks have solved the same problem, and proceed by
    writing tests based upon the protocol in order to measure the completeness,
    accuracy and progress of my resulting implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem for developers writing for CircuitPython is that such code is
usually to be run on microcontrollers with certain hardware capabilities. Yet
such code is invariably written on conventional computers running operating
systems such as Windows, OSX or Linux. The only way to know your code works is
to try it on the target device. This is, to say the least, laborious compared
to having the benefits of running an extensive test suite in a matter of
seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having written my small and simple &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; module I
found myself missing the benefits of a comprehensive test suite. After asking
around, I found most Python modules for CircuitPython don&#x27;t have a test suite
and there hadn&#x27;t been much (if any) exploration for how to address this. Scott
suggested I add what I thought best in terms of testing to my module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted my solution to meet the following requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It works with existing Python testing tools so non-specialist Python
    developers feel at home and can bring their existing skills to
    CircuitPython with little effort.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;It runs on a conventional computer, because that&#x27;s where developers do
    the majority of their work. (I&#x27;m constantly running and re-running my
    test-suite as I make changes to code.)&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;It handles the problem of using CircuitPython-only modules in a
    test-suite run on a conventional computer with standard Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to focus on using an existing, well known and mature Python
testing tool called &lt;a href=&quot;http://pytest.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;PyTest&lt;/a&gt; (the
creation of another friend of mine, the extraordinarily prolific and very
thoughtful &lt;a href=&quot;https://holgerkrekel.net/&quot;&gt;Holger Krekel&lt;/a&gt;). The
advantage of using PyTest is that it has a large number of plug-ins that are
both useful and familiar to a large number of Python programmers. One such
plug-in I use a lot is the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest-cov&quot;&gt;Pytest coverage tool&lt;/a&gt;,
which makes it easy to spot areas of a code base that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; 
exercised by a test suite. PyTest also has a well defined mechanisms to extend
it to work in specialist testing situations (such as our own CircuitPython
based context).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I was concerned, using PyTest met the first two of my self-imposed
requirements. I was left with the final problem of dealing with CircuitPython
only modules that wouldn&#x27;t work on a conventional computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I need to introduce the concept of &quot;mocking&quot; in a test suite
(as in &quot;mocked up&quot; rather than poking fun). Mocking is a way to replace parts
of your system under test with &quot;mocked up&quot; objects and then make assertions
about how such objects have been used. Thanks to another friend of mine (the
huge hearted, funny and rather hairy
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.voidspace.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Michael Foord&lt;/a&gt;), mocking is built
right into Python&#x27;s standard library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My idea was simple: automatically mock away those parts of CircuitPython
that don&#x27;t work on a conventional computer. Such objects give the developer a
way to check and ensure the module under test is working as expected with
CircuitPython. It&#x27;s even possible to specify how such mock objects should
behave under certain conditions (such as when they may be the source of some
sort of data which the module under test will use). However, this aspect of
mocking should be used with great care -- more on which later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a developer creates a &lt;code&gt;conftest.py&lt;/code&gt; file in their test suite
PyTest will import it before running any of the test code and use various
functions found therein to configure the test suite. For example, if PyTest
finds a function called &lt;code&gt;pytest_runtest_setup&lt;/code&gt; in the
&lt;code&gt;conftest.py&lt;/code&gt; file, then this function will always be called
immediately prior to any test function. Just what we need!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntoll/Adafruit_CircuitPython_Radio/blob/master/tests/conftest.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;conftest.py file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
is very short and simply mocks away named aspects of CircuitPython which cannot
be run on a conventional computer immediately before any test is run, via the
aforementioned &lt;code&gt;pytest_runtest_setup&lt;/code&gt; convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means I can write conventional looking PyTest based unit tests like the
following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def test_radio_receive_full_no_messages(radio):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    If no messages are detected by receive_full then it returns None.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    radio.ble.start_scan.return_value = []
    assert radio.receive_full() is None
    radio.ble.start_scan.assert_called_once_with(
        adafruit_radio.AdafruitRadio, minimum_rssi=-255, timeout=1
    )
    radio.ble.stop_scan.assert_called_once_with()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things you should know: &lt;code&gt;radio.ble&lt;/code&gt; is a mocked away part of
CircuitPython. As a result, on the first line of my test function, I&#x27;ve been
able to tell the mock that the result of calling the &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt;
method is an empty list. Then I can assert that the method I want to test (the
&lt;code&gt;radio.receive_full&lt;/code&gt; method returns &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt; in this
context. Furthermore, I&#x27;m able to check in the final two statements of the
function that the &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt; method was called with the expected
arguments, and that an additional &lt;code&gt;stop_scan&lt;/code&gt; method was called
too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I run the test suite, I see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pytest --cov-report term-missing --cov=adafruit_radio tests/
============================= test session starts ==============================
platform linux -- Python 3.7.5, pytest-5.3.0, py-1.8.0, pluggy-0.13.0
rootdir: /home/ntoll/src/adafruit_radio
plugins: cov-2.8.1
collected 12 items                                                             

tests/test_adafruit_radio.py ............                                [100%]

----------- coverage: platform linux, python 3.7.5-final-0 -----------
Name                Stmts   Miss  Cover   Missing
-------------------------------------------------
adafruit_radio.py      61      0   100%


============================== 12 passed in 0.09s ==============================
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note all the feedback about code coverage..! Neat, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mock object, by its very nature, is a mock-up of something else... it&#x27;s
not the real thing..! So what happens when the real thing (that has been
mocked-up in the test suite) changes? For instance let&#x27;s imagine that the
result of a call to &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt; is no longer an empty list, but
something else. The tests will still pass because the mocked-up object doesn&#x27;t
reflect the real object, yet when the module under test is used on a real
device with the changed version of CircuitPython then it won&#x27;t work
correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously not a good situation and why I mention mocks should be
used with great care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious solution is for the developer in charge of the test
suite to be careful and check API updates in the release notes of the modules
being mocked away. However, this becomes a burden if the test suite mocks away
a huge number of modules. It&#x27;s also open to human error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to mitigate this problem, but because it&#x27;s early days
I&#x27;ve not been able to investigate these potential solutions properly. The best
I can do at this point in time is shrug my shoulders, say things are under
construction and invite folks to dive in and help. Our community would
certainly be enriched by such collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I&#x27;m quite pleased with this first step in equipping
CircuitPython modules with comprehensive test suites. Yet there&#x27;s still plenty
to do -- most notably, ways to address the problems mentioned with mocking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, comments, constructive criticism and ideas expressed in a
friendly, collaborative and supportive manner are most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over to you... :-)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 13:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>