<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>Why Computers Work</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-work</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-work</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/why-computers-work&quot;&gt;Why Computers Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Sunday, 17th December 2017 (9:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many explanations of computers on the internet. For example, my
buddy &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MissPhilbin&quot;&gt;Carrie Anne Philbin&lt;/a&gt; has a
series of videos introducing &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; various aspects of computing work. Go
watch them, they&#x27;re wonderful videos! Here&#x27;s a flavour of what you can
expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/tpIctyqH29Q?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; gesture=&quot;media&quot; allow=&quot;encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m taking a very different approach in this blog post. Rather than
describing &quot;how&quot;, I&#x27;ll explain &quot;why&quot; computers work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&#x27;s the difference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answers to &quot;how?&quot; questions tell us what method or steps make such-and-such
a thing work or happen. This is the approach taken in most explanations of
computers and so successfully demonstrated by Carrie Anne in her wonderful
video series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the answers to &quot;why?&quot; questions explain what makes
something possible, thus providing a broader context and the potential
to explore something at a more fundamental level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s the difference between a car mechanic who may understand &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;
an engine works (so they can fix broken engines), and a mechanical engineer who
understands the physics and chemistry of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; engines work (so they can
improve the design of engines). Of course, this is a simplistic metaphor and,
in reality, experts understand both &quot;how&quot; and &quot;why&quot; aspects of their
fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, just understanding how something works means your frame of
reference is limited to &lt;em&gt;within the system&lt;/em&gt;, whereas if you know why
something works you&#x27;re not limited to specific products, solutions or
practices. Knowing why something is possible is an invitation to be
creative, explore a problem area and exceed current solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My aim is to address the inbalance of the large number of &quot;how&quot; explanations
with a very simple exploration of &quot;why&quot; computers work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, the basics of why computing works are easy to understand. I&#x27;m going
to give you enough information so you can delve into details should you wish to
explore further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, be open minded. Explore, experiment and play. Let loose
your imagination and don&#x27;t limit yourself to thinking in terms of how things
currently are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our exploration starts with a card game...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Following Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you know how to play Snap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A Pile of Cards&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/cards.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The state of stacks of cards and following rules make playing Snap
possible.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s the sort of game very young children learn to play. It uses a
standard deck of cards and the aim is to win all the cards. Here&#x27;s how it
works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players sit in a circle with one of them acting as dealer. The dealer
shuffles the cards so they&#x27;re in a random order. The cards are dealt,
face down, to each player until the dealer has none left. Before the game
begins, each player should have a neat stack of face-down cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The player to the left of the dealer takes the first turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Players take a turn by moving the top card from their face-down stack onto
the top of an adjacent stack of face-up cards so the moved card is also facing
up. If the face-up stack doesn&#x27;t already exist a new stack is created. The
player to the left always goes next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player notices two face-up cards on different stacks have the same
value (for example, two aces are visible) then they shout &quot;SNAP!&quot;. The first
player who correctly shouts out wins all the cards in the matching stacks of
cards. The matching stacks are added to the bottom of the winner&#x27;s face-down
pile. Play continues to the left of the player who turned up the matching
card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player mistakenly shouts &quot;SNAP!&quot; at the wrong time they must pay a
forfeit of one card from their face-down stack to each of the other players.
These are added to the bottom of the other players&#x27; face-down stacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If two or more players shout &quot;SNAP!&quot; at the same time both of the matching
stacks are placed in the middle and added to the &quot;Snap Pool&quot;. When &quot;SNAP!&quot; is
next called correctly, the winning player wins both the matching stacks and the
Snap Pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a player runs out of face-down cards they flip over their face-up stack
and play continues as before. If a player completely runs out of cards, they
are out of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Play continues until the winning player holds all the cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rules describe how, given a certain state of affairs, such and
such things must happen. States of affairs describe how things are
in the world. For example, &quot;there are two piles of face-up cards that have
cards of matching values on the top of each&quot;. When I say that such and such
must happen, I mean clear and unambiguous instructions tell you how play
proceeds given a certain state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing the game of &quot;Snap&quot; means you modify your behaviour to follow the
rules of the game. If everyone follows the rules then we can all play
together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;re used to following rules. Obviously, we don&#x27;t explain card games in
such a formal manner to very young children. It&#x27;s a fun game: they learn the
entertainment of skillfully following the rules to bring about exciting
situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computing related rules and states of affairs I&#x27;m about to describe
are not much more complicated than the game of Snap explained above. However
what follows may include a few &quot;brain twists&quot; -- where I expect you to use your
imagination to see things in a seemingly unusual or unintuitive way! It&#x27;s fun
and can result in rather pleasant &quot;aha&quot; moments (that feeling you get when, if
you were a cartoon character, a lightbulb would appear above your head).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want you to remember the way it feels to follow the rules of a game like
Snap when when you read what follows. Fundamentally, they&#x27;re no different:
given a certain state of affairs you should do such and such a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is the story of how we turn our thoughts into programs that
instruct computers what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Movement of Thought&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s possible to apply rules to thinking about things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the study of Logic and applying these rules of thinking is called
reasoning. Reasoning with such rules makes you rational -- others can follow
the movements of thought that brought you to a certain conclusion. Furthermore,
because there are rules of thought it&#x27;s possible to notice when an argument
doesn&#x27;t make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many types of logic but the one we&#x27;re going to examine is called
propositional (or sentential) logic. If this sounds complicated or a little bit
intimidating, remember that one of the fun things about working with computers
is that you get to speak impressive sounding technobabble. &quot;Propositional&quot; (or
&quot;sentential&quot;) logic is just a name that describes what it does. This type of
logic concerns how sentences are formed by combining smaller propositions
called premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s a simple example of propositional logic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it is sunny and I&#x27;m wearing a coat then I will get hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to some important aspects of this sentence
that may not, at first, appear obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It contains two statements called premises (&quot;It is sunny&quot; and &quot;I&#x27;m
    wearing a coat&quot;). Premises make assertions about states of affairs that
    will either be true or false.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It ends with a conclusion (&quot;I will get hot&quot;). A conclusion asserts
    an expected state of affairs that&#x27;ll also be true or false.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The sentence is in the form of a conditional (&quot;if [premises] then
    [conclusion]&quot;). A conditional means that if the premises are true then
    the conclusion &lt;em&gt;must also be true&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The premises are related to each other by a logical operator called
    conjunction (&quot;and&quot;). If the related premises are evaluated together,
    &lt;em&gt;collectively they are true only if all of them are true&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propositional logic reveals the structure of a sentence so we can understand
how the argument works. Playing by the rules of logic forces everyone to reach
the same inevitable conclusion: if we accept that the premises are true
(it is sunny and that I&#x27;m wearing a coat) propositional logic dictates the
conclusion must be true (that I will get hot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A weather forecast&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/weather.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Is it sunny? Premises make assertions about states of affairs that
may only be true or false.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the brain twist: propositional logic doesn&#x27;t care about the meaning
of the overall sentence nor its component premises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could rewrite the sentence as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If A and B then C
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propositional logic only cares about truth and how propositions fit
together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn&#x27;t matter what A, B or C stand for nor what they may mean -- from
the perspective of propositional logic all that matters is there are two
conjugated premises (A and B) and a conclusion (C) expressed in a conditional
(if ... then ...). If one or both of the premises is false, then the
conclusion must also be false. Why? Because the logical rules pertaining to
conditionals and conjunctions make it that way! The brain twist is divorcing
yourself from meaning -- just concern yourself with the structure of the
argument and following the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In exactly the same way the rules of Snap explain what must happen given a
certain state of affairs, so the rules of propositional logic do the same with
logical arguments. Another way to look at it is to remember that the rules of
Snap don&#x27;t care what the specific values of cards are, just that such values
may match. Similarly, propositional logic doesn&#x27;t care what the specific
meanings of the premises or conclusion may be, just that there are such
propositions connected in a structure that can be evaluated using rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to express the rules that govern logical operations for
connecting propositions is with a truth table. Here&#x27;s how &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot;
(conjugation) is defined, can you see how it works?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;Conjunction outcomes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;A and B&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;The definition of &quot;and&quot; (conjunction) as a truth table.&lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two columns represent propositions labelled &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt;. The third column represents the outcome of the
&quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operation. Each possible combination of the truth values of
&lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; is enumerated as a row, and the value for
each row in the third &quot;&lt;code&gt;A and B&lt;/code&gt;&quot; column defines what the outcome
must be. It&#x27;s a tabular way to express the rules of propositional logic. If you
had any doubt how &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot; worked, you&#x27;d find the definitive answer
in this truth table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, take the first row: if propositions &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; are both false (the first two columns), if they&#x27;re evaluated as
part of an &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot; conjunction (the third column) the rule is that
the result &lt;em&gt;must be false&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the truth table that defines the rule for another logical operation
called &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; (disjunction):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;Disjunction outcomes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;B&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;A or B&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;The definition of &quot;or&quot; (disjunction) as a truth table.&lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s pretend that &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; is false but &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; is true. How
would you evaluate truth value of &quot;&lt;code&gt;A or B&lt;/code&gt;&quot;? Is it true or
false?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is that &quot;&lt;code&gt;A or B&lt;/code&gt;&quot; is true. Why? Because the second
line tells us so: the &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; column is false, the &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt;
column is true so the result, expressed in the third column, is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s one final truth table for you to ponder. It&#x27;s a bit different to the
other two since it only works on one premise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;Negation outcomes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;A&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;not A&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;caption&gt;The definition of &quot;not&quot; (negation) as a truth table.&lt;/caption&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;True&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;False&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s easy to see what the &quot;&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operation does to a
proposition: it flips its truth value so false becomes true and true becomes
false.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these logical operations have familiar names (&quot;and&quot;, &quot;or&quot; and &quot;not&quot;)
that &lt;em&gt;appear to relate to how they work&lt;/em&gt;, it is the truth table &lt;em&gt;and
only the truth table&lt;/em&gt; that defines how they behave not any similarity to
how we may use such words in everyday English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logical puzzles become fun when you combine logical operations to build more
complicated structures. Take for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
(A and B) or (C or not D)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve put parenthesis around propositions so you can see how they relate to
the logical operators. If we pretend all the propositions represented by
letters are false, what is the overall truth value?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you answer, here&#x27;s a hint to help work it out: there are four
logical operations in the sentence -- an &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot;, &quot;&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;&quot;
and two &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot;s. The &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operates on &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; whereas the &quot;&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operates on &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt;.
The two &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot;s are interesting: one of them operates on
&lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; and the result of &lt;code&gt;not D&lt;/code&gt; (notice how the
&quot;&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;&quot; needs to be evaluated before the enclosing &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot;
can be worked out). The other &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operates on the result of the
&quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operation and the previously mentioned
&quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the state of affairs where all the proposition letters represent
false, how do we use the rules of propositional logic to evaluate the overall
truth of the sentence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play the logical &quot;game&quot; in the same way we would with Snap: we just
follow the rules. Here&#x27;s how:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start by evaluating the operators within the parenthesis. If we replace the
propositions &lt;code&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt; with their truth values
(remember, in this case, all the propositions are false), we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
(false and false) or (C or not D)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the truth table described earlier, the first &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot;
operation evaluates to false because both the propositions are false. Here&#x27;s
how the sentence looks as a result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
false or (C or not D)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned previously, to evaluate the &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; in the
remaining parenthesis we should first evaluate the &quot;&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operator.
If &lt;code&gt;D&lt;/code&gt; is false then the truth table for &quot;&lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;&quot; tells us
that &quot;&lt;code&gt;not D&lt;/code&gt;&quot; must evaluate to true. Since &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; is false,
the sentence looks like this when &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;not D&lt;/code&gt; are
replaced by their truth values:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
false or (false or true)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s evaluate the &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; in the parenthesis. The truth table for
&quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; tells me that if one of the propositions is
true then the &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operation must evaluate to true, resulting
in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
false or true
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-using this rule again to evaluate the final &quot;&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;&quot; operator
gives the result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
true
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;only way&lt;/em&gt; to solve such logical puzzles is by following the
inevitable steps dictated by the rules. If Logic provides an inevitable, almost
mechanical framework for thinking about things (and propositional logic is only
one type of logic we may use for this purpose) then we should be able to build
machines to work with such seemingly mechanical logical rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that we can and that we call such machines computers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Representation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often pretend one thing represents something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in the UK we know where the Queen is because the
building, car, boat or aircraft containing the Queen always flies the royal
standard. Put another way, the presence of the royal standard represents the
presence of the Queen. This isn&#x27;t a scientific fact -- it&#x27;s not like the Queen
is also a mysterious force of nature who manipulates flags and flag poles.
Rather, we collectively understand the royal standard represents the Queen&#x27;s
presence and somebody, somewhere has the job to make sure flags are correctly
aligned with what she&#x27;s up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;The Royal Standard&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/royal_standard.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Royal Standard for the kingdoms of England, Wales and Northern
Ireland (Scotland has its own variation).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine this sounds like a lot of trouble to take over a flag, especially
when you consider the complicated and extensive travel plans of the Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, imagine Her Majesty insisted on a radical modernisation. Why not
use electronics to show the Queen&#x27;s presence at the touch of a button? Perhaps
there could be a light to represent her status: if it were on, she was
present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a device could be built using the simple circuit diagram shown
below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A simple circuit&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/simple_circuit.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A simple circuit, fit for a Queen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diagram is easy to read. At the top is the symbol representing a battery
that supplies the electrical power for the components. Notice that it has a &quot;+&quot;
sign to designate its positive end. Lines form a rectangle to join the battery
to the other two components at the bottom. The circle containing an &quot;X&quot;
represents a bulb and the gap created by the line veering off at an angle
represents a switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Pictures of components&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/components.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The components represented by the circuit diagram: a battery, a
bulb and a switch that can either be on or off.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The switch can be in two states: on (creating a circuit so electrical
current moves through the components, thus lighting the bulb) or off (where the
circuit is broken, stopping the electrical current and switching off the
bulb).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s a royal brain twist for you: can you think of something else that 
deals with only two possible states?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you thought, &quot;propositional logic!&quot; then you deserve a knighthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not use the on and off states of the circuit (as controlled by the
switch) to represent true and false, respectively? When the tourist walking by
Buckingham Palace wonders about the truth of the premise, &quot;the Queen is home&quot;
they can check for the answer by looking at the bulb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s another royal brain twist: it&#x27;s possible to make simple circuits that
mimic logical operations (&quot;and&quot;, &quot;or&quot;, &quot;not&quot; and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Queen has a husband -- the Duke of Edinburgh. Given the wonders of
modern technology it&#x27;s possible to light the bulb if both the Queen and her
husband are present or if only one of them is present. The bulb could
show:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Queen is present &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the Duke of Edinburgh is
    present;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Queen is present &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; the Duke of Edinburgh is present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since you were paying attention to propositional logic you&#x27;ll know that
the two sentences are the same as: &quot;&lt;code&gt;A and B&lt;/code&gt;&quot; and
&quot;&lt;code&gt;A or B&lt;/code&gt;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the diagram for the &quot;&lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;&quot; circuit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A simple AND circuit&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/and_circuit.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A simple AND circuit. Q = Queen, E = Duke of
Edinburgh.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two switches labelled &quot;Q&quot; (for Queen) and &quot;E&quot; (for Duke of
Edinburgh). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A simple OR circuit&quot; src=&quot;/static/images/or_circuit.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A simple OR circuit. Q = Queen, E = Duke of Edinburgh.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Electrical Circuits&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Transistors&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Chips&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Crank the Handle&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Instructions&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Assembler&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Code&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Python&lt;/h1&gt;


</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 21:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>(Anti)Social Media</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/antisocial-media</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/antisocial-media</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/antisocial-media&quot;&gt;(Anti)Social Media&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Sunday, 17th December 2017 (9:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of 2018 I will delete my account and all associated content
from &lt;a href=&quot;http://facebook.com/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined Facebook to work with their public API as part of my work at
Fluidinfo. After a while people started to find me (with a surname like
&quot;Tollervey&quot; I&#x27;m easy to find online). As a result, I&#x27;ve reconnected with many
friends. This has been a lovely and positive experience: anything that brings
people together in friendship is to be applauded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Facebook makes me uncomfortable: it makes it easy to bring
people together, yet drives a wedge between friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Posts and responses may appear like conversations between people, but they
introduce a layer of indirection -- they are always done via Facebook rather
than directly between friends. To analogise, it would be like going to a bar
where all interactions between the patrons were made via the bar tender.
Facebook acts like a really efficient and multi-media aware version of the bar
tender from my analogy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is problematic for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our socialising on Facebook is reduced to interactions that
standardise, process and normalise our lives into a digital production line of
uniform social outputs (&quot;like&quot; something, post a picture, reply with a comment,
set your mood). The messy, complicated and raw aspects of life, which I would
argue are the most valuable, fun and interesting are lost or have no way to
manifest themselves. We commoditize ourselves into a dribble of systematized
digital assets (photos, posts, likes etc...).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once commoditized, Facebook insinuates itself into our friendships. For
example, after chatting with a particular friend (let&#x27;s call them &quot;X&quot;) you
appear to see more &quot;X likes Y&quot; content interleved into your timeline. Facebook
even tries to guess things about your background (where did you go to school? X
attended Y university). Our commoditzation makes it easy to be measured and
analysed which, in turn, allows Facebook to work out who we are from the way we
behave on the website. Remember, the bar tender in my analogy knows the
content of all the conversations between the customers as well as everyone&#x27;s
drink and snack preferences, favourite seat and usual arrival time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/business/overview&quot;&gt;Facebook
are up front&lt;/a&gt; about how they make money: they sell access to our accounts
to the highest bidder who wants to advertise at us. As
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/business/products/ads&quot;&gt;their website
explains&lt;/a&gt;: &quot;&lt;em&gt;Find people easily; you can choose your audience based on
demographics, behaviours or contact information. Get their attention; our
advert formats are eye-catching, flexible and work on every device and
connection speed. See the results; our advert reporting tools show you how
your adverts have impacted your business in visual, easy-to-read reports.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;
It&#x27;s obvious that their customers find this a valuable service (note: as users,
we are not their customers, but, as is often pointed out, the product on
offer): &quot;&lt;em&gt;We can target adverts to people based on how and when they
engaged, and create an experience that is relevant to where they are in the
process of investigating our products.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here&#x27;s why I&#x27;m leaving Facebook: I don&#x27;t want my friendships reduced to
pre-canned types of interaction. I want to look my friends in the eye, smile
at them, make music, laugh and give them a hug or shoulder to cry on. I want to
welcome them to my home, make them a meal, share a drink and get lost in
conversation. I want to shake their hands, listen to their tone of voice, raise
my eyebrow at a silly comment or make a joke so we laugh together. Put simply,
I want to spend quality time with my friends in real life, rather than watch a
stream of mediated content in a sterilised digital life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I don&#x27;t want to be measured, analysed, prodded and poked for
the purpose of brand engagement. I don&#x27;t want my friendships interrupted
for the sake of a commercial break in my timeline. It&#x27;s troubling to be reduced
to a means to an end by virtue of simply being me (my friendships make me a way
for Facebook to make money). Put simply, I find Facebook&#x27;s openly Orwellian
platform troubling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people, including maybe even you, don&#x27;t have a problem with such a
state of affairs. I completely respect that, as I hope you respect my
discomfort with Facebook and my decision to leave. Facebook is, after all, an
opt-in personal choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what will I do post-Facebook?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll concentrate on fostering friendships unmediated by Facebook. That will
take time as I try to stay in touch via email, phone calls or face-to-face,
but I&#x27;m confident such efforts will be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if we are friends on Facebook and Facebook is the only way we
interact, please don&#x27;t lose touch.
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:ntoll@ntoll.org?Subject=Hello%2C%20Nicholas..%21&amp;Body=Hi%20Nicholas%2C%0A%0AType%20your%20message%20here...%20%3A-%29%0A%0ALots%20of%20love%2C%0A%0AInsert%20your%20name%20here&quot;&gt;Drop me an email&lt;/a&gt;
and never doubt that I&#x27;ll be pleased to hear from you. If you
find yourself wondering if you should get in touch with me, the answer is
always, &quot;yes, you should definitely get in touch&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to hearing from you soon... :-)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 21:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Advice for a Beginner Coder</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/advice</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/advice</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/advice&quot;&gt;Advice for a Beginner Coder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Wednesday 1st November 2017 (12:30pm)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week was &lt;a href=&quot;http://2017.pyconuk.org/&quot;&gt;PyCon UK 2017&lt;/a&gt;. It was
perhaps the best PyCon yet and, as usual, I met many old friends and made
plenty of new ones. Many thanks to Peter Inglesby (chair) and the other
volunteers who put so much work into making this such a wonderful space for
bringing together a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A highlight of the conference for me was the number of young people who were
&lt;strong&gt;not part of the young coders&#x27; day&lt;/strong&gt; but who were attending the
conference as regular attendees (and accompanied by ever-supportive
parents). I got chatting to one such combination of young person and
accompanying parent and they asked for advice on how to develop as
a beginner programmer in the Python community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows is based upon my response:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you get out of the Python community is directly related to how
much you put in. The Python community has a huge number of interesting projects
with which you could engage and learn from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, look for a project that you find interesting and start to
contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&#x27;t dive in and submit thousands of lines of code - rather, do something
small, easy and/or trivial. It&#x27;ll introduce you to the current maintainers of
the project and demonstrate you&#x27;re competent while allowing you to get used to
their modus operandi. Be polite and ask questions that demonstrate you&#x27;ve read
their documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&#x27;t be afraid to ask questions - good developers are
always asking questions. Knowing how to ask and what the right questions are is
an essential skill to develop. &lt;strong&gt;Asking questions is NOT a sign you
don&#x27;t know what you&#x27;re doing&lt;/strong&gt;. To good developers it&#x27;s evidence
that you&#x27;re exploring the problem and a signal that you&#x27;re engaged and
interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear, it takes time to get involved in a project and the quickest
way is often to take small (but secure) steps. Your collaborators, if they&#x27;re
any good, will provide advice about your contributions. This is invaluable
mentorship and it also means you&#x27;ll get to know people in the community. When
you go to conferences, you&#x27;ll have allies and colleagues!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful to separate criticism of your code from criticism of you. The
very best developers are humble, listen to advice and understand that code can
always be improved. Sometimes it&#x27;s hard to hear that your code is not very
good, but this also helps us to appreciate how to give good (constructive)
advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, if you don&#x27;t get support, if people are rude or there&#x27;s a bad
smell around the project, just leave. Life is too short to have to deal with
idiots, and if you have no choice, find experienced, thoughtful and
conscientious allies to help support you (you&#x27;ll find plenty of them in the
Python community).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good project will have a code of conduct that sets expectations of how
collaborators are to interact. &lt;strong&gt;This is far more important than
you may at first realise&lt;/strong&gt; and, happily, many in the Python community
take this aspect of programming very seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, one of the best activities to help you learn new things
is to teach. Being able to explain things indicates you know the craft of
programming at a deep level. For example, you appreciate what to leave in or
how much to leave out of an explanation. You have clear enough mental models
of the concepts of programming that you can accurately analogize and
summarise. Furthermore, to explain yourself in simple and easy-to-understand
language demonstrates your own clarity of thought. Perhaps most importantly,
finding the opportunities to practice the skill of teaching is a sign of
moral and professional value: you&#x27;re putting something back into the wider
community and you have shown initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our community is at its best when people take the time to create a space
where others, no matter their background or differences, can flourish
together. You should endeavour to follow this example. Why? Because inclusion
that celebrates difference and diversity exercises our capacity for empathy
and understanding of others&#x27; lives, problems and interests. As a developer,
how can you be sure what people need from your software? Only by listening to
others, reflecting, evaluating and experimenting is such valuable knowledge
revealed. Only then will you know what important problems to solve.
&lt;strong&gt;This is (also) far more important than you may at first
realise&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, make sure you&#x27;re having fun. Writing code is often a very
frustrating activity, but when you make something work, the elation at seeing
something you&#x27;ve created solve a problem makes all the hours of frustration
worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 12:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>