<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>Program a Pacifist Tyranny</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/program-pacifist-tyranny</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/program-pacifist-tyranny</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/program-pacifist-tyranny&quot;&gt;Program a Pacifist Tyranny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Tuesday 5th May 2015 (19:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit #1 (6th May 2015):&lt;/strong&gt; Upon re-reading this article with
fresh eyes I realise it&#x27;s very &quot;raw&quot;. This is merely a reflection of the
underdeveloped nature of the ideas expressed herein. Put simply, I&#x27;m interested
in &lt;em&gt;how programming relates to the exercise of power&lt;/em&gt;. Keep that in
mind as you read on. Finally, I welcome feedback, constructive critique and
ideas - it helps these ideas to develop. I will ignore vacuous comments
that state some variation of &quot;you&#x27;re wrong because I&#x27;m right and I know what
I&#x27;m talking about&quot;. Thoughtful, respectful yet robust argument is always
most welcome! :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit #2 (9th May 2015):&lt;/strong&gt; I&#x27;ve made minor changes to
simplify and clarify several points. I&#x27;ve also improved the flow by correcting
clunky prose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violence is a forced curtailment of one&#x27;s well-being and autonomy, usually
via unwanted physical intervention by a third party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be blunt, the threat and eventual use of violence is how government
imposes itself on citizens. In places like the UK, the Government derives its
authority to use such onerous power from its legitimacy as a democratic
institution: the citizens get a say in who is in charge. Laws created by the
legislative and judicial elements of government define the scope of the threat
and use of state-sanctioned violence towards citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually violence is not required - the threat suffices. Most people
pay fines associated with a traffic ticket: they understand failure to do so
would end badly for them (arrest followed by prison). Obeying the law is so
ingrained and unquestioningly assumed that it is a habitually formed behaviour
- violence is not even appreciated as part of the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any reasonably intelligent person understands why we have laws:
they help people live together peacefully and, one would hope, in a way that
is consistently equitable and fair. The figure of Lady Justice atop the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Bailey&quot;&gt;Old Bailey&lt;/a&gt; is the
personification of law as an impartial, objective process without fear nor
favour. Put simply, the law and the veiled threat of violence applies equally
to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that it obviously doesn&#x27;t and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/the-law-is-an-ass.html&quot;&gt;the law is
an ass&lt;/a&gt; on so many occasions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are any number of examples I could use to illustrate bad laws
misapplied in an unequal, prejudicial and discriminatory way. So common is this
unfortunate turn of events that I imagine you could think of your own examples.
As a result, I&#x27;m merely going to bring to your attention the case of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Swartz&quot;&gt;Aaron Swartz&lt;/a&gt;, a gifted
coder and activist who was hounded by legal authorities in the US until he
committed suicide. I strongly recommend you watch the rather excellent
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.takepart.com/internets-own-boy&quot;&gt;The Internet&#x27;s Own Boy&lt;/a&gt;
(embedded below), a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/&quot;&gt;creative commons&lt;/a&gt;
licensed film about these tragic events:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/vXr-2hwTk58?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do such cases tell us? While the spirit of the law is &quot;blind&quot; and
impartial, the practice and application of the law isn&#x27;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authorities understand this and realise that technology can help both
in terms of law enforcement and impartiality. For example, in the UK speed
limits on roads are often measured by average-speed-check cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/average_speed.jpeg&quot;
    alt=&quot;Average speed check sign&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At certain points along a road (and at known distances apart) cameras are
positioned to read car registration number plates. If you average a speed
greater than the advertised limit then you are automatically sent a speeding
ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At no point in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.speedcamerasuk.com/specs.htm&quot;&gt;this
process&lt;/a&gt; is a human actually involved. The cameras
never tire, they work without prejudice and they apply their machinations to
everyone. Such co-opting of automated computing technology for law
enforcement appears to be on the rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What could possibly go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_surveillance_disclosures_%282013%E2%80%93present%29&quot;&gt;Snowden revelations&lt;/a&gt;
we know that everything we do online is open
to the government. If you&#x27;re technically savvy enough to correctly use
encryption, such innocent countermeasures become an automatic marker
for the authorities to investigate further. More worryingly, lethal force is
becoming automated through the use of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/drew-f-cohen/autonomous-drones-and-the_b_4428112.html&quot;&gt;autonomous drones&lt;/a&gt;
and other similar technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This raises an important question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who defines the machinations of such autonomous computing enforcement
devices?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, programmers do. The code they design and write encapsulates the
behaviour of the speed camera or autonomous drone. Furthermore, with the
increased connectivity and programmability of &quot;stuff&quot; (the so called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_of_Things&quot;&gt;Internet of
Things&lt;/a&gt;) our tools, belongings and infrastructure are increasingly dependent
on code. Our world (more accurately, the things we create in it that make it
comfortable, pleasant and interesting) is becoming programmable. Ergo,
governments have a new mechanism for imposing upon citizens: software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sanction to force compliance is no longer violence - the government
can pass laws to program the world to automatically coerce you,
nudge you or persuade you. For instance, imagine a situation where the
car of a flagged suspect is automatically and remotely deactivated until
certain conditions are met (not dissimilar to the Police intervention in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.schnews.org.uk/archive/news6252.htm&quot;&gt;this case&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments can legislate to program a pacifist tyranny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why pacifist? Because the traditional threat of violence is replaced by a
threat of non-action or (worse) counter-action on the part of your
belongings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why tyranny? Because citizens
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/2015/04/dmca-ownership-john-deere/&quot;&gt;no longer
control or own their belongings&lt;/a&gt;. They can&#x27;t argue with code if it refuses
to start their car, nor can they change such code so it more closely fits their
requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most people don&#x27;t understand code in much the same way
that medieval serfs couldn&#x27;t read the Bible (so couldn&#x27;t question the authority
of the church). It&#x27;s not that programming is hard, it is simply not a widely
practised skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why programming is such an essential skill to promote
in education. In order to lead a flourishing self directed life in such a
digitally dominated world we must have control over our digital devices both
in a physical and programmable sense. The alternative is to allow others,
through the code they write, intimate control over our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, it&#x27;s not just governments that exercise this power: any
service that helps you organise your life can do the same. Facebook, Google
and the rest are already trying to modify your behaviour (except they&#x27;re
trying to get you to spend money rather than obey the law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can such a morally suspect state of affairs be foiled?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our digital world is dominated by centralised entities that hold power and
control over our data and devices. Only by decentralising (to avoid points of
control and coercion) and engaging humanity to learn about and take control of
the computational world will a tyranny of software be averted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schneier.com/&quot;&gt;Bruce Schneier&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20141103-everybody-spies-or-nobody-does&quot;&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt;,
software itself does not
distinguish morality from legality - it&#x27;s merely &quot;capability&quot;. Yet capability
permits certain forms of behaviour that in turn pose moral, legal and political
questions, requirements and possibilities. Furthermore, we&#x27;re engineering a
digital world from a certain point of view that is reflected in the
capabilities of the code we create. It is for this reason that writing
software is both an ethical and political activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&#x27;re a coder, ask yourself about your own project&#x27;s capabilities. Work
out how it influences, empowers or diminishes your users. If at all possible,
promote users&#x27; &lt;a href=&quot;/article/autonomy&quot;&gt;personal autonomy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology should help humanity flourish (rather than constrain).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>TransCode</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/transcode</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/transcode</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/transcode&quot;&gt;TransCode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Monday 30th March 2015 (14:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/transcode.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TransCode logo&quot;/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend I had the privilege of attending the world&#x27;s first
&lt;a href=&quot;http://trans-code.org/&quot;&gt;Trans*code&lt;/a&gt; event in London. Trans*code is
a hack-day for transgender persons and trans-allies (like me).
We came together to create software that addresses transgender issues and
participate in introductory programming workshops for people not currently
familiar with the world of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hack-day is usually a community organised event centred around some form
of civic or community good. For example, I participate in and sometimes help
to organise the health-care related
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nhshackday.com/&quot;&gt;NHS Hackdays&lt;/a&gt;, I organise the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/education&quot;&gt;education track&lt;/a&gt; at PyconUK where we
run hack-day like workshops for teachers and developers for generating
educational resources and I&#x27;ve taken part in many post-conference
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.net/Sprints&quot;&gt;sprints&lt;/a&gt; where members of the
free-software community get together to plan and hack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that wonderful things happen when diverse groups of
people get together to collaborate and solve problems: any cooperation that
brings about a cosmopolitan, tolerant and receptive world view should be
encouraged. After all, what&#x27;s the alternative? I&#x27;d argue its an
obviously undesirable small-minded, prejudiced and unimaginative world view. I
also passionately believe that programming is a vehicle for empowerment and
emancipation. Our world is increasingly influenced and controlled by
computing so it is important that &lt;strong&gt;everyone&lt;/strong&gt; has the
opportunity to take control of technology and make it &lt;em&gt;work for
them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the majority of such hack-days are attended by people like me -
white straight dudes who already write code. Therefore I have no hesitation
in supporting any effort that will increase diversity, participation and
understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did I find out about Trans*code? My main programming language
is Python, I&#x27;m a former teacher and I&#x27;m interested in education. I have
a buddy called &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NaomiCeder&quot;&gt;Naomi&lt;/a&gt; who is also
a Python programmer, former teacher and has an interest in education. She&#x27;s
the organiser and force-of-nature behind Trans*code. Naomi put out the word
via various UK based Python channels and I was one of several Pythonists
attending as a trans-ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, here are my impressions of the day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transgender people I chatted with are brave. From my position of
ignorance I had no idea about some of the situations trans-folk have to deal
with and overcome on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a really friendly event. When there were disagreements people were
sympathetic and respectful. It&#x27;s refreshing to encounter this sort of
deliberation rather than a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pissing_contest&quot;&gt;pissing
contest&lt;/a&gt; between silverback alpha-geeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m a naturally enthusiastic person and given only half a chance will talk
the hind-leg off a proverbial donkey, organise people and &quot;get stuff
done&amp;#0153;&quot;. It&#x27;s important to listen, especially given my position of
ignorance. I learned to frame my contributions as &quot;have you thought
about X..?&quot; type questions. I should do this more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My group were a lot of fun to work with. The idea was an application called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cmantito/transflare&quot;&gt;TransFlare&lt;/a&gt; a sort of
&quot;bat signal&quot; or &quot;flare&quot; mobile app for the trans community: in case of
trouble, use the application to call for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/AaAmB.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bat signal&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I could tell, the most valuable part of the day was the debate,
idea generation and discussion we had rather than any coding we got done
(truth be told, I didn&#x27;t do a lot of coding). We ended up thinking about a
lot of different things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Identity verification - we investigated the
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://openname.org/&quot;&gt;OpenName&lt;/a&gt; protocol to allow people to
    indicate the provenance of their identity online in a manner that wasn&#x27;t
    controlled by some third party that may change its terms and conditions or
    decide to push some non-friendly agenda.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Web of trust - a humane peer-to-peer community driven mechanism to
    verify that people were of good standing and appropriately qualified to
    be helpers (who ultimately see the flares that are generated).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Appropriate technology - mobile, geo-enabled, encrypted and, where
    possible, peer-to-peer (so there is no single point of failure where
    sensitive details could be hacked).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a technical person, these are &lt;em&gt;really interesting problems&lt;/em&gt; to
solve but with the advantage of having real use-cases to flesh out what can
sometimes be quite abstract problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun and I hope my contribution was helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Naomi and the other organisers, the sponsors
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://salesforce.com&quot;&gt;Salesforce.com&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gocardless.com/&quot;&gt;Go Cardless&lt;/a&gt;) and the other attendees who
made the event such an interesting and stimulating occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plans afoot to run another Trans*code
related event at this year&#x27;s PyconUK in September in Coventry. I&#x27;d encourage
you to join in and support in any way that you can.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Thought in Motion</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/thought-in-motion</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/thought-in-motion</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/thought-in-motion&quot;&gt;Thought in Motion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Sunday 30th November 2014 (2:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had the opportunity to dip into the book,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/a_history_of_the_world.aspx&quot;&gt;A
History of the World in 100 Objects&lt;/a&gt;. It mentions one of my
favourite objects in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/&quot;&gt;British Museum&lt;/a&gt;: a 5100 year old
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/highlight_objects/me/t/tablet,_allocation_of_beer.aspx&quot;&gt;Mesopotamian clay tablet&lt;/a&gt;
that records the allocation of beer by administrators in the city
of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uruk&quot;&gt;Uruk&lt;/a&gt; (I&#x27;ve written about
this object &lt;a href=&quot;/article/long-term-view&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/15_writingtablet_l.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mesopotamian tablet&quot;/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chapter about this tablet explains how literacy was a catalyst for a
fundamental change in human civilization. For the first time complex
information could be recorded, checked and stored outside the human mind. It
concludes with the following quote from the American philosopher
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Searle&quot;&gt;John Searle&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Writing is essential for the creation of what we think of as
human civilization. It has a creative capacity that may not even have been
intended. I think you don&#x27;t understand the full import of the revolution
brought by writing if you think of it just as preserving information into the
future. There are two areas where it makes an absolutely decisive difference
to the whole history of the human species. One is complex thought. There&#x27;s a
limit to what you can do with the spoken word. You cannot really do higher
mathematics or even more complex forms of philosophical argument unless you
have some way of writing it down and scanning it. So it&#x27;s not adequate to
think of writing just as a way of recording, for the future, facts about the
past and the present. On the contrary, it is immensely creative. But there&#x27;s a
second thing about writing which is just as important: when you write down
you don&#x27;t just record what already exists, you create new entities - money,
corporations, governments, complex forms of society. Writing is essential for
all of them.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does Searle mean when he states that writing creates new entities
essential for complex society?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try this example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am married to Mary and we have a piece of paper called a marriage
certificate that proves we are. Somewhere else is written down an
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Geo6/12-13-14/76&quot;&gt;act of
Parliament&lt;/a&gt; explaining how one obtains such a proof of matrimonial status
along with definitions of terminology, responsibilities and activities in
accordance with the custom of &quot;marriage&quot; in England and Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary and I had to make vows (that are written down somewhere)
in front of witnesses. Since neither of us is religious we had a civil
marriage so a licensed registrar then spoke the specified words (that are also
written down somewhere), &quot;I now pronounce you husband and wife&quot;. It was only
until these words were spoken by such a licensed person in accordance with
the practices written down in the afore mentioned act of Parliament that Mary
and I were married.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6vBadGJp1hQ?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately afterwards, we signed our names in a special register to
record our marriage and duly received our marriage certificate. Sometimes
we show the certificate to people in accordance with the practices and customs
written down in other acts of Parliament to prove that we are, indeed,
married.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the &lt;strong&gt;physical world&lt;/strong&gt;, not a lot happened that
was of great interest. An alien observer from another planet might describe
the occasion as a group of hairless apes making sounds then scrawling marks
on flattened dead tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new entities and aspects of complex society that Searle is thinking of
are, of course, those things that only exist in our human, &lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt;
world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &quot;truthiness&quot; of my marriage, a certain act of Parliament or other such
things does not come about in the same way that it is true to say
that water boils at a certain temperature. Importantly, this doesn&#x27;t make
such things less true (I&#x27;m still married).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanism for creating the truth of such social states of affairs is
not the result of observing a natural phenomena (as a scientist might do in
the case of the boiling point of water), rather, it is merely
&lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; expressing &lt;em&gt;some thing&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;some context&lt;/em&gt;. The
registrar (someone) saying &quot;I now pronounce you husband and wife&quot; (some thing)
at a wedding ceremony (some context) &lt;strong&gt;is how&lt;/strong&gt; we became husband
and wife. It is a &lt;em&gt;special incantation&lt;/em&gt;. That it lacks physical
properties or side effects is overcome by bureaucratic overhead (writing of a
certificate to record our married state and other activities in accordance
with written down laws - as I describe above). This is how writing creates
complex forms of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such performative statements (simply expressing them makes them true)
don&#x27;t have to be spoken by some official person as is the case at a wedding.
Simply by writing them down can be enough. For example, the United States&#x27;
twenty dollar bill has written on it, &quot;This note is legal tender for all
debts public and private&quot;. This makes it money! (Although I can&#x27;t just write
this on any old piece of paper and expect to get away with purchasing things
with it - the &quot;someone&quot; making the statement and &quot;context&quot; of the statement
are both wrong according to the terms set out by some other performative
statement written down as a US law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put another way, it would seem bizarre to use this mechanism in the
context of the physical world: I simply can&#x27;t decree that water boils at a
certain temperature &lt;strong&gt;because I say so&lt;/strong&gt; and then issue a
certificate to prove it! This mechanism only works when constructing facts in
the &lt;em&gt;human social world&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the social world have any effect on the physical world? Of course it
does: the rules of football are social constructs yet govern how
people should run around a field kicking a ball in a physical sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We share a culture, a form of life, a social world that exists by virtue of
us being human and doing things humans do. This includes creating social
constructs that only exist in such a social world via performative statements.
It is only through our behaviour that evidence of such social constructs is
manifested in the physical world (we run around a pitch kicking a ball in
accordance with the socially constructed rules of football).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a key aspect Searle&#x27;s argument: it requires humans to work.
Someone must have written down such statements and others, collectively, need
to have read, understood and acted as a result of comprehending such writing.
This is, in a sense, is a movement of thought or intent between minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, intentions and information can be shared via speech. Yet I
believe Searle is correct to point out that literacy both records and creates
such social entities that shape our collective behaviour that would be
otherwise difficult or impossible to work with in a pre-literate society. Just
imagine how hard it would be to keep track of the arguments in this blog
post without the convenience of being able to re-read them. How would we keep
track of complex laws? There&#x27;s only &lt;em&gt;so much&lt;/em&gt; anyone can commit to
memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s important to note that such movement of thought between minds is not
just textual in nature: for example, it works when writing symbols in the
musical and mathematical realms. I find it remarkable that I can enjoy the
musical thoughts of a genius such as Beethoven almost 200 years after his
death - I consider it a privilege when I think about the amount of effort
spent to bring about such aural experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it is possible to follow mathematical thought processes so
long as you understand what the symbols represent and how they are to be
manipulated. Take, 2+3=5 for instance. As any child will tell you, the
&quot;=&quot; (equals) symbol means that what&#x27;s written on its left is of equal quantity
to what&#x27;s written on its right. Furthermore, the &quot;+&quot; (sum) symbol indicates
the quantities adjacent to its left and right should be added together (start
at the highest quantity and count up the other-quantity-number-of-steps to find
the result). Such mathematical literacy symbolically records thought processes
that unfold in a deterministic manner (it&#x27;s a formal system: if you understand
the symbols, 2+3 &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; equal 5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we get to the nub of this blog post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like us, Computers process symbols. These symbols are a sort of literacy
(we write them down as code). Such symbols record our thoughts as
&lt;a href=&quot;/article/programming-concise-and-simple&quot;&gt;algorithms&lt;/a&gt;
(instructions used to achieve some useful end) or
&lt;a href=&quot;/article/databases-concise-and-simple&quot;&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; (representation of
information that can be easily manipulated by the computer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To execute such algorithms or manipulate such data does not require a human
- a computer will do. Computers are designed, created and operated by humans
but the execution of the algorithm and manipulation of data is most definitely
within the digital realm. This is, in a sense, a movement of thought, intent
or information between (human) minds: I want to do X, so execute a program
(written by another human) that brings about X but get a computer to do it
for me (rather than a human).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I want to buy a ticket to travel on the train to London. I used
to have to ask a ticket clerk at the station to bring this about (assuming we
both followed the conventions required for the purchase of a ticket). Today I
can book online, print my tickets or even pick them up from an automated ticket
machine with no human intervention at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying computers are minds (more on this in a later blog post).
Merely, computers are a medium for the transmission of thought, intent or
information (expressed as algorithms or data) in a similar way to how clay
tablets or pen and paper are also a medium for the transmission of thought,
intent or information (expressed as writing). The important distinction is
that computers are active (they can execute the algorithm or manipulate the
data) and clay tablets or pen and paper are passive (a human is required to
act upon their content).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is the fundamental change of &lt;em&gt;our time&lt;/em&gt;. We live in a
&lt;em&gt;social&lt;/em&gt; world where I can record my thoughts and not require a human
for their content to be acted upon (for example, as a programmer I can write
a train-ticket purchasing program for other people to use). The computer, in
some sense, is the performative actor (rather than, say, the registrar at my
wedding). In Searle&#x27;s terms, the software is the &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; expressing
some thing (&quot;you have a valid ticket to travel on such-and-such a train&quot;) in
a &lt;em&gt;computational&lt;/em&gt; context that we humans accept as valid (in the same
way we accept a wedding as a valid context for a registrar to perform their
duties).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I need to think about this further simply because I believe
we (humanity) have not lived with computers long enough to comprehensively
understand their role in our daily (social) lives. You might say that we&#x27;re
at the same stage with computers as the Mesopotamians were with writing when
they created the clay tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting times ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Image credits: Mesopotamian tablet
&amp;copy; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishmuseum.org/&quot;&gt;Trustees of the British Museum&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>