<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>Sponsorship</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/sponsorship&quot;&gt;Sponsorship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Thursday, 23rd January 2020 (08:30AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the code I write is given away for free for the benefit of
others. This is unsustainable so I often think about how such voluntary work
could be supported. One solution is related to my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://codegrades.com/&quot;&gt;CodeGrades&lt;/a&gt; idea. But this is a slow
burn project that has involved, and continues to demand, a huge amount of
time, effort and money before I&#x27;ll have anything to show for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another solution is simply to ask folks for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been a musician, I&#x27;m used to this feeling. I used to busk with some
buddies as a way of trying to make ends meet. However, as my grandmother once
pointed out, it&#x27;s a form of begging. In one sense, this is a tragedy: begging
is a last resort because nothing else you do is of value. You&#x27;re forced to
rely on the compassion and generosity of others. Yet in another sense it&#x27;s like
the activity of a mendicant asking for alms for their service or contributions
to society. In any case, no matter how you &quot;spin&quot; it, it&#x27;s a precarious
situation to find oneself in ~ be you a musician or free software developer
(and I&#x27;m both!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are some kind hearted individuals and (even rarer) companies or
organisations who are happy to help support such work, most think, &quot;meh, I&#x27;ll
just use the software&quot; (without so much as a thank you). Even worse (and I have
personal experience of this) some folks will pass off such voluntary work as
their own and reap the rewards for such a lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it was with some interest that I noticed GitHub had created what
they describe as account sponsorship. &quot;Sponsorship&quot; is an interesting word
to use because it makes the begging / mendicant aspect of the situation more
palatable. It also cheerfully suggests that the free/open-source software world
is full of generous hearted folks or organisations just waiting to give back to
the selfless volunteers who make all this code available via their GitHub
account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, of course, a fiction. It&#x27;s also normalising begging as a solution
to funding free software volunteers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&#x27;m open minded and willing to give anything a go, especially if it
means it&#x27;ll cover my costs. So I&#x27;ve signed up and now &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can give me
money for my efforts. As of the time of writing, and after tweeting about this
to my 3,000+ followers, this is what my account looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/github_sponsors.png&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&#x27;t help but think that in six months time, it&#x27;ll still look the same.
But at least I can say I gave it a go. Despite my misgivings, I feel it
important to give ideas a chance to flower and I&#x27;m trying very hard (yet
failing) to view this as a mendicant rather than beggar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you&#x27;ve ever found my work or activities useful, beneficial or
supportive, please consider helping me sustain my efforts. You can do so by
visiting my &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sponsors/ntoll&quot;&gt;sponsorship&lt;/a&gt;&quot;
page to find out more about what I do and how to give &quot;alms&quot;. The summary is
that I focus on education: I develop software that helps folks learn the
skills and knowledge they need to imagine, develop and program the stuff they
want. If you believe this is important work, sponsor me with a monthly
contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, and many thanks to the small number of you who have already
done this, you can send me a virtual hug-as-a-book by buying me
something from my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/hz/wishlist/ls/3B63FUSVDIJJS&quot;&gt;Amazon wish list&lt;/a&gt;
(none of the items are particularly expensive). Small gestures, such as gifting
books or music with a supportive message, can actually mean a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll report back in a few months to let you know how I get on. I have to
admit, I don&#x27;t hold out much hope. Best knuckle down on CodeGrades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well... what are you waiting for..? Go on... get your wallets out. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Honestly, I quite understand if you don&#x27;t. I have the same misgivings
you&#x27;re probably having after reading the sentence above. Such a feeling is the
nub of what I want to demonstrate in this blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 08:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>CircuitPython 2020</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-2020&quot;&gt;CircuitPython 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 7th January 2020 (05:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/blinka-computer.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My buddy &lt;a href=&quot;http://tannewt.org/&quot;&gt;Scott&lt;/a&gt;, one of the wonderful
people at &lt;a href=&quot;https://adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, recently asked folks
in the wider CircuitPython community to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.adafruit.com/2020/01/01/what-do-you-want-from-circuitpython-in-2020-circuitpython2020-circuitpython/&quot;&gt;share their thoughts&lt;/a&gt;
about what they&#x27;d like to see for the project and community during 2020. This
is my contribution to the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three aspects to my hopes for CircuitPython in 2020:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Things I hope will continue,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Developments I hope to happen,&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&quot;Moon on a stick&quot; wishes for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to start by reaffirming my belief that Adafruit, and those
involved with CircuitPython in particular, do inspiring stuff when it
comes to fostering an open, welcoming, supportive and collaborative tech
community. This is an extraordinary achievement. My own experience in the
wider Python community is that it takes a huge amount of effort, patience,
compassion and thoughtfulness to grow and sustain such a
&quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/2008/06/scenius-or-comm/&quot;&gt;scenius&lt;/a&gt;&quot;
(and, sadly, this can be destroyed very quickly by only a few bad actors). So
my wish for continuation in 2020 is that everyone involved in the
CircuitPython community grasp opportunities to enlarge positive aspects of
ourselves such as mutual appreciation, the sharing of tools and techniques,
latent network effects, and a spirit of tolerance, compassion and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I hope happens this year is a broadening of CircuitPython&#x27;s horizons.
My passion for tech can be summed up by a quote from David Allen, the producer
on the original BBC micro from the 1980s -- my first computer. He
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nesta.org.uk/report/the-legacy-of-bbc-micro/&quot;&gt;explained&lt;/a&gt;
that, &quot;[t]he aim was to democratise computing. We didn&#x27;t want people to be
controlled by it, but to control it.&quot; CircuitPython feels to me like it sits
very much in the hobbyist / enthusiast &quot;segment&quot; of users who already know
something of programming. I&#x27;d love CircuitPython to make inroads into
beginner related education. This probably involves a focus on
learning what teachers would like from a coding platform, honest appraisals of
how beginner coders (no matter their age or background) find their first steps
with CircuitPython and Adafruit boards, as well as making the results of such
findings accessible to all. This final point is important. Learning to code
shouldn&#x27;t just be an option for English speaking, able bodied folk from a
cultural background that means examples and cultural assumptions are
easily understood. I hope you agree that education should be an inclusive
endeavour, and this takes concerted and conscientious effort. I hope the
CircuitPython community find the time and space to invest in the (never
finished) work such a focus entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/moon_stick.png&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &quot;moon on a stick&quot; is a CircuitPython based mobile phone with a touch
screen and a simple
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypercard.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;PyperCard&lt;/a&gt; like?)
Python UI that&#x27;s easily hackable. Think
of it as the open, easy-to-assemble, relatively cheap and &quot;hack friendly&quot;
version of something like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelightphone.com/&quot;&gt;Light Phone&lt;/a&gt; with all the
schematics and design assets (e.g. files for 3d printing the case) available
under open source licenses so folks can go mod-crazy. Now wouldn&#x27;t that
be a turn up for the books..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll finish by wishing everyone in the CircuitPython a flourishing and
happy new year. Here&#x27;s to wonderful things in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s go..!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>A Classical Playlist of Love</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/playlist-love&quot;&gt;A Classical Playlist of Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Thursday, 28th November 2019 (02:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my Canadian buddies &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AndreaMcInnes21&quot;&gt;Andrea&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://snarky.ca/&quot;&gt;Brett&lt;/a&gt; visited the UK in
the summer, we visited the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Albert_Hall&quot;&gt;Royal Albert Hall&lt;/a&gt; to hear a classical music
concert that was part of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Proms&quot;&gt;the Proms&lt;/a&gt; -- the world&#x27;s largest
classical music festival. I think they must have enjoyed themselves because
they recently got in touch asking me to suggest a playlist of
classical music. What follows is my response along with videos of performances
of the pieces I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than put together a playlist of apparently random
choices, I decided it would be interesting to assemble a set of pieces
related to a particular feeling. In this case, I chose love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because love is complicated, tragic, happy, joyful, funny, raunchy and many
more aspects too numerous to list here. The western classical
tradition has around 900 years of musical reactions, settings and descriptions
of love -- plenty of opportunity to reveal a breadth and depth of music. So,
I&#x27;m going to associate each piece with some aspect of love, provide
a short commentary and embedded a video of a performance of
the selected piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to draw your attention to my sharing videos of performances. Ideally,
you&#x27;d listen to these pieces in person at a concert. Only in such a live
situation can you really experience the fleeting moment of the performance,
executed by highly trained musicians and feel that sense of being in a
particular unique moment, together with all the others in attendance. The
videos are a less than perfect replacement, yet still have the potential to
move you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For convenience I&#x27;ve put them into a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yjz2TvC2TT4&amp;list=PLzCYc445IVNTPApt_F6PkGCRRPNfG-JmA&quot;&gt;playlist on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is classical music, it may sound strange to modern ears not
familiar with styles and mannerisms from hundreds of years ago or it uses sung
or instrumental techniques that sound odd because they&#x27;re not used much in
contemporary popular music. If classical music isn&#x27;t your thing, consider
this an invitation to explore a new musical world -- a world that rewards
repeated engagement, an open mind and long term listening. This is music that
makes demands of the listener, but will reveal depths one cannot even imagine
until you experience them for yourself. For those of you who are already
immersed in classical music you&#x27;ll find none of my choices particularly
challenging. In fact, you may even roll your eyes and think, &quot;oh, not that old
chestnut again&quot;. Please remember, this is an introductory playlist, but know
that I&#x27;m open to suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sincerely hope you are moved by the pieces I&#x27;ve selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tender Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gustav Mahler - Adagietto from Symphony No. 5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical representation of Mahler&#x27;s love for his wife Alma. Their
friend Wilem Engelberg recollects, &quot;In place of a letter, he sent her this in
manuscript form, not adding a further word. She understood and wrote to him
telling him to come!!! They both told me this.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alma later revealed Gustav left her the following poem with the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;In which way I love you, my sunbeam,&lt;br/&gt;
I cannot tell you with words.&lt;br/&gt;
Only my longing, my love and my bliss&lt;br/&gt;
can I with anguish declare.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yjz2TvC2TT4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tragic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky - Fantasy Overture to Romeo and Juliet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tchaikovsky was well acquainted with tragic love: he was a gay man in 19th
century Russia (a time and place full of prejudice towards someone such as
himself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such tragedy and pain as well as an overflowing sense of passion are
skilfully captured in this piece or &quot;musical impressions&quot; loosely assembled to
follow the story of Romeo and Juliet. Listen out for the overwhelming &quot;love
theme&quot; which has become a musical cliché for inevitably doomed lovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3x69wuewkJM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Romantic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sergei Rachmaninoff - Piano Concerto No.2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachmaninoff, another Russian, is widely considered one of the greatest
pianists of all time, as well as one of the greatest composers for the
piano. This piano concerto is full of yearning melodies, gushing outpourings of
emotion, tender moments and joyful exuberance. Just like falling in love!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was effectively used in the David Lean romance from 1945, &quot;Brief
Encounters&quot;, thus cementing it as a &quot;romantic&quot; classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rEGOihjqO9w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Denied&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puccini - O Mio Babbino Caro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aria, from Puccini&#x27;s opera &quot;Gianni Schicchi&quot;, comes at the moment where
the daughter of Gianni tells him that she&#x27;s fallen in love, wants to get
married, and if he won&#x27;t let her go to her true love, she&#x27;ll throw herself off
the Ponte Vecchio bridge in Florence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you imagine this sounds like a musical tantrum in the making, get ready
with the hankies and prepare for something absolutely not tantrum like at
all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soprano singer in the video, Montserrat Caballé, is simply stunning. Her
charisma, presence, musicianship and vocal control is awe inspiring. Yes, she&#x27;s
the one who sang with Freddie Mercury on his single &quot;Barcelona&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RxZSP1Dc78Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Platonic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms - Intermezzo Op. 118 No. 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brahms wrote this beautiful piece for his friend Clara Schumann (Clara is
another musician considered one of the greatest pianists of all time and a
wonderful composer in her own right). I describe it as &quot;Platonic&quot; because Clara
was married to Brahms&#x27;s mentor and friend Robert Schumann, who eventually
succumbed to mental health issues. Brahms and Clara were undoubtedly close and
shared a deep love for each other, but it was only ever a love between dear
friends. Imagine how you&#x27;d feel if you had been gifted such a piece of
music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/78OO5v0lNtI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Fantastical Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berlioz - Symphonie Fantastique&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is sex, drugs and classical music with an added dose of musical story
telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is of the concert Andrea, Brett and I attended. I won&#x27;t
say any more, since the performers do a fantastic job of explaining what&#x27;s
going on. It&#x27;s quite a spectacle (and watch out for the mirror balls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FqTU8m8BJwQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Transformed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg - Verklärte Nacht&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schoenberg wrote this piece to closely follow the structure of the poem upon
which it is based, to the extent that the different sections in the musical
score map directly to lines in the poem. The poem, by Richard Dehmel, whose
title is translated as &quot;Transfigured Night&quot;, tells of two lovers walking in the
woods. The woman opens up about a terrible burden she carries. Her lover is
full of compassion, love and support which transforms her burden into a shared
aspect of their life together. I&#x27;m being necessarily vague here so I don&#x27;t
spoil the poem for you... just read it as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://allpoetry.com/Transfigured-Night-(Verklrte-Nacht)&quot;&gt;translated here&lt;/a&gt;
and then listen to the piece. My favourite lines (and part of the piece)
are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Just see how brightly the universe is gleaming!&lt;br/&gt;
There’s a glow around everything;&lt;br/&gt;
You are floating with me on a cold ocean,&lt;br/&gt;
But a special warmth flickers&lt;br/&gt;
From you into me, from me into you.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the music sounds as if it&#x27;s gleaming..! One other thing you
may hear, the violin (a high instrument) is prominent in the sections
representing the woman speaking, whereas the cello (a low instrument) is
prominent in the sections representing the man speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yzSaOWPBFqA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love&#x27;s Dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fauré - Après un rêve&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is simply a song about a dream of the poet&#x27;s beloved. The words of the
poem (and their English translation) can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxfordlieder.co.uk/song/15&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/FlT1QhK4Wto&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Erotic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner - Prelude and Liebestod from &#x27;Tristan Und Isolde&#x27;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where do I start with this one..? This is erotic music. I don&#x27;t mean humping
or &quot;having a shag&quot;. Rather, it&#x27;s a musical version of a passionate embrace
(between the protagonists, Tristan and Isolde).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In music theory we use the term &quot;climax&quot; to describe the point at which all
the tension in the music is released. There&#x27;s a reason we call it a climax.
This piece has a famously ecstatic climax that takes a while to build, after
lots of tender pauses, gradually intensifying musical moments, soaring strings
and throbbing horns (no pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m sure you&#x27;ll hear what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/W8EQcMurhAI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Orgasmic Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orff - Dulcissime (from Carmina Burana)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just watch and listen. No further explanation needed.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/BFq8vH7tPxs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mendelssohn - Wedding March from A Midsummer Night&#x27;s Dream&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&#x27;ll hear this in pretty much every church wedding you ever attend - and
quite rightly, it&#x27;s very uplifting, celebratory and joyful music. Just what you
need for such an occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rIM5cWB2wmM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;A Moment of Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vaughan Williams - Silent Noon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dante Gabriel Rossetti&#x27;s poem &quot;Silent Noon&quot; recollects an intimate shared
moment of love that was both fleeting and intense. Vaughan Williams music
beautifully complements the nostalgic, thoughtful and timeless nature of the
moment in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Your hands lie open in the long fresh grass,--&lt;br/&gt;
The finger-points look through like rosy blooms:&lt;br/&gt;
Your eyes smile peace. The pasture gleams and glooms&lt;br/&gt;
&#x27;Neath billowing skies that scatter and amass.&lt;br/&gt;
All round our nest, far as the eye can pass,&lt;br/&gt;
Are golden kingcup-fields with silver edge&lt;br/&gt;
Where the cow-parsley skirts the hawthorn-hedge.&lt;br/&gt;
&#x27;Tis visible silence, still as the hour-glass.&lt;br/&gt;
Deep in the sun-searched growths the dragon-fly&lt;br/&gt;
Hangs like a blue thread loosened from the sky:--&lt;br/&gt;
So this wing&#x27;d hour is dropt to us from above.&lt;br/&gt;
Oh! clasp we to our hearts, for deathless dower,&lt;br/&gt;
This close-companioned inarticulate hour&lt;br/&gt;
When twofold silence was the song of love.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rvl4Qo-z_KM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love&#x27;s Yearning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gluck - Che farò senza Euridice&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of Orfeo and Euridice is popular among composers. The hero,
Orpheus, is a master musician who can tame nature with his music. His beloved
Euridice dies and is taken to the Greek underworld. Missing his lover,
Orpheus travels into the underworld and charms Hades, the god of the
dead, with his music. As a result, Hades promises that Euridice can live and
return to the world of the living so long as Orpheus doesn&#x27;t look back to see
if she follows him on the way home. Inevitably, Orpheus looks back and Euridice
is, once again, struck dead. It&#x27;s at this point in the opera that we hear the
following aria for counter-tenor (the highest natural voice for a man to
sing). The title means, &quot;What shall I do without Euridice?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What will I do without Euridice&lt;br/&gt;
Where will I go without my wonderul one.&lt;br/&gt;
Euridice, oh God, answer&lt;br/&gt;
I am entirely your loyal one.&lt;br/&gt;
Euridice! Ah, it doesn´t give me&lt;br/&gt;
any help, any hope&lt;br/&gt;
neither this world, neither heaven.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll leave you to work out what happens next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0mEKeaXST2s&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love&#x27;s Pain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strozzi - Che si può fare&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Strozzi was a remarkable woman. Born in Venice in 1619, she was one
of the most well known musicians of her age. It is claimed she had more music
in print than any other composer of the era. This success was of her own doing
since she had no support from the usual sources of the church or nobility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine that if Bridget Jones were from Baroque era Venice, she&#x27;d be
listening to this instead of Céline Dion&#x27;s &quot;All By Myself&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What can I do?&lt;br/&gt;
The stars have no pity and work against me;&lt;br/&gt;
If heaven will give me no gesture&lt;br/&gt;
Of peace for my pain,&lt;br/&gt;
What can I do?&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
What can I say?&lt;br/&gt;
The heavens are raining disasters on me;&lt;br/&gt;
If Love will not grant me a moment of breath,&lt;br/&gt;
to relieve all my suffering,&lt;br/&gt;
What can I say?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/1F458aC_FUM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smetana - Vltava (The Moldau) from Má vlast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the musical antidote to nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Czech composer Smetana uses music to represent the river Moldau as it
runs through his country in a celebration of the landscape, activity, folk
music, dance and industry of the people of the Czech republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works well as a musical metaphor, starting with the trickle of notes
from the opening flutes and building up to a flowing melody surrounded by
melodic eddys and currents in the strings. The river music keeps returning
throughout the piece as different musical interludes interject to describe
some aspect of where the river flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/l6kqu2mk-Kw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Nature&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Pastoral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is an old friend of mine. Forget the Disney version from the
animated film &quot;Fantasia&quot; -- this is Beethoven musically representing a visit to
the country and the emotional impact that has on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the latter part of the work he paints a picture of a country dance
interrupted by a storm which he concludes with a hymn to nature. Beethoven
wasn&#x27;t conventionally religious, but this is a certainly a spiritual reaction
to nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iQGm0H9l9I4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love of Humanity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven - Choral Symphony&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven&#x27;s 9th is full of different emotions and a real journey of the soul
in musical form. But the part I want to particularly highlight is the finale,
the &quot;Ode to Joy&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beethoven was famously misanthropic and that&#x27;s how the finale starts with
the rather annoyed sounding cellos and double basses. But once the &quot;joy&quot; theme
is found the instruments try their hardest to make something of it. Yet
Beethoven&#x27;s genius is to interrupt the finale at this point, and start again
with human voices. Schiller&#x27;s words are a celebration of brotherhood,
togetherness and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, it really does have the line, &quot;here&#x27;s a giant kiss for all&quot; sung by the
massed choir. Thank you Ludwig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/-suf9BL9xRA?start=2663&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Parental Love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shostakovich - Piano Concerto No.2 (Second Movement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dimitri Shostakovich wrote this concerto for his son Maxim. Maxim used it as
an audition piece for music conservatoire when he was a teenager. This second
movement is both sad yet hopeful, as a parent lets go and reflects on the child
leaving and growing into adulthood. The music full of love and sadness. Perhaps
if the orchestra is Dimitri, then Maxim is the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/TPqMvoR2Buo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Ending&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strauss - &quot;Im Abendrot&quot; from Four Last Songs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a musical and poetic meditation on two lovers coming to the end of
their long life together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Through sorrow and joy&lt;br/&gt;
we have gone hand in hand;&lt;br/&gt;
we are both at rest from our wanderings&lt;br/&gt;
now above the quiet land.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Around us, the valleys bow,&lt;br/&gt;
the air already darkens.&lt;br/&gt;
Only two larks soar&lt;br/&gt;
musingly into the haze.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Come close, and let them flutter,&lt;br/&gt;
soon it will be time to sleep -&lt;br/&gt;
so that we don&#x27;t get lost&lt;br/&gt;
in this solitude.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
O vast, tranquil peace,&lt;br/&gt;
so deep in the afterglow!&lt;br/&gt;
How weary we are of wandering--&lt;br/&gt;
Is this perhaps death?&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Giaf3qSqDHM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Love Lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar - Cello Concerto&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife, Mary, once played this in a concerto competition (and won).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elgar wrote the piece soon after his wife, Alice, passed away. The cello is,
of course, Alice and the music Elgar creates reflects all the different
feelings he has now that she is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This very old performance, by Jacqueline du Pré on cello and Daniel
Barenboim conducting, is poignant. They were married but Jackie&#x27;s playing
succumbed to multiple sclerosis soon after this recording was made. The MS
eventually killed her around a decade or so later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OPhkZW_jwc0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 14:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>