<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>PyconUK 2014 and the Education Track</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-edu-2014</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-edu-2014</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/pyconuk-edu-2014&quot;&gt;PyconUK 2014 and the Education Track&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Saturday 21st June (02:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write software. I use a programming language called
&lt;a href=&quot;http://python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;. As well as being very easy to learn
and fun to use Python is an amazingly powerful language that&#x27;s used by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/about/success/&quot;&gt;thousands of organisations&lt;/a&gt;
the world over - from the likes of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://google.com/&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://corp.bankofamerica.com/&quot;&gt;Bank of America / Merrill Lynch&lt;/a&gt;,
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nasa.gov/&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt; to small start-ups and scrappy little
websites such as this one. Every day, &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; inadvertently encounter
thousands of digital creations made with Python. By any measure of technical
success Python, it seems, is a triumph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all Python&#x27;s technical prestige, I believe the most important aspect of
Python is the community that has evolved around the language. Perhaps
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/~guido/&quot;&gt;Guido&lt;/a&gt;&#x27;s desire for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/doc/essays/cp4e/&quot;&gt;computer programming for
everyone&lt;/a&gt; set the seeds for the growth of such a community. Of course,
the development of Python is an entirely voluntary affair and inevitably
attracts the sort of person who likely wants to contribute to the wider public
good. Maybe it&#x27;s because the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf-landing/&quot;&gt;Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
(the charitable organisation that promotes Python and coordinates its
development) is not just &lt;em&gt;sympathetic to&lt;/em&gt; but
&lt;em&gt;proactive in&lt;/em&gt; encouraging engagement in Python programming
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/community/diversity/&quot;&gt;no matter your
background&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;em&gt;especially if you belong to an underrepresented group
of nascent programmers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, the UK&#x27;s Python community are a diverse bunch who maintain a
reputation as a friendly, welcoming and dynamic group. Every year we meet
for our community organised &lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/&quot;&gt;PyconUK&lt;/a&gt;
conference. We come together in a way that reflects the widely held view that
diversity and friendliness are strengths of our community to be celebrated
and fostered (to paraphrase PyconUK&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.net/CodeOfConduct&quot;&gt;statement on diversity and
conduct&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past three years we have welcomed colleagues who are teachers of
Python in UK schools. For the past two years we have put on a special
education track to promote programmer / teacher collaboration and mutual
learning. Last year we ran a kids&#x27; day where the proto-programmers of tomorrow
explored Python with the technologists of today. The following videos give
you a flavour of what we got up to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/qOya5R9g1T8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/uPq1VJpMEgw?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/yerWCR3mppk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/u4IMlpmjbYg?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/PXPoc9HCTlo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RZJFdeDpo8w?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to be running an education track at this year&#x27;s
PyconUK (to be held on 19th-22nd September in Coventry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosophy of the education track is simple: wonderful things happen
when diverse groups of people come together to learn about and explore
empowering technology such as Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a teacher, parent, programmer or young person interested in
exploring technology then the education track has something for you. We have
secured some very generous support for teachers, parents and young people to
attend at little or no cost. Kudos to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://corp.bankofamerica.com/&quot;&gt;Bank of America&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.python.org/psf-landing/&quot;&gt;The Python Software Foundation&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hp.com/&quot;&gt;Hewlett Packard&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raspberrypi.org/&quot;&gt;The Raspberry Pi Foundation&lt;/a&gt;
and our very own
&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/&quot;&gt;PyconUK Society&lt;/a&gt; for their extraordinarily
abundant support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full details can be found here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pyconuk.org/education&quot;&gt;http://pyconuk.org/education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Book now because places are limited!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2014 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>The Experience of Music</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/experience-of-music</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/experience-of-music</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/experience-of-music&quot;&gt;The Experience of Music&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Saturday 24th May (11:30AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a second blog post resulting from emails about music exchanged with
my buddy &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flourish.org&quot;&gt;Francis&lt;/a&gt; (the first one
can be &lt;a href=&quot;/article/pachelbel-canon&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;). I also felt
compelled to write because of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ntoll/statuses/469237873469038592&quot;&gt;this recent
fragment of conversation&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter with another collaborator and buddy,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://drlj.me/&quot;&gt;Dr. Laura-Jane Smith&lt;/a&gt;, concerning how one
measures the efficacy or effect of an artistic encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interesting article: what evidence is appropriate to support/justify &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23arts&amp;amp;src=hash&quot;&gt;#arts&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23health&amp;amp;src=hash&quot;&gt;#health&lt;/a&gt;? Are clinicians too positivist? &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/tTj1hqQYoc&quot;&gt;http://t.co/tTj1hqQYoc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr LJ (@drlaurajane) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drlaurajane/statuses/469144660993384448&quot;&gt;May 21, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows are personal reflections. Please take them with a large pinch
of salt. I&#x27;m merely creating a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/wlg/2982&quot;&gt;context in which &lt;em&gt;&lt;u&gt;you&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
may think&lt;/a&gt; about music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/54763818?badge=0&quot; width=&quot;712&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video (by &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/finallystudio&quot;&gt;FinallyStudio&lt;/a&gt;)
claims there are lots of ways to understand music because
there are lots of aspects of music to consider (and you don&#x27;t have to know
about any of them to enjoy music). The evidence for this argument is all
around us: people with no musical training enjoy music all the time. Be it
listening to the radio, singing in the shower or picking out melodies on a
self-taught instrument, music is somehow an innate part of the human
experience, no matter your level of education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Francis&#x27;s emails and Laura-Jane&#x27;s question about
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positivism&quot;&gt;positivism&lt;/a&gt; struck me
as overtly intellectual in outlook: there had to be some &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; to be
identified, processed and (in LJ&#x27;s case) measured and interpreted. As Francis
explained,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I think I&#x27;m *so bad* at this particular music, I&#x27;m just not
noticing any patterns.

My instinctive feeling is it is just a whiney, drifty noise.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these two sentences Francis identifies the nub of the matter (and
the title of this post): the &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does music feel? What are the sensations that music arouses in you?
What do you think when you encounter music?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reading this post I want you to wonder about your raw, intuitive or
instinctive reactions to music rather than any higher order thinking about
music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe there is a danger to over-think music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell,
there&#x27;s no need to identify patterns to appreciate music that is otherwise
unenjoyable. Perhaps the composer wanted to create whiney, drifty noise. Even
if this is not the case, who&#x27;s to say Francis&#x27;s reaction is wrong? I find
plenty of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g5TVKhjEVtQ&quot;&gt;well loved music&lt;/a&gt;
hard to enjoy (or even to listen to).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of health,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetic_resonance_imaging&quot;&gt;MRI scanners&lt;/a&gt;
can&#x27;t measure &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qualia&quot;&gt;qualia&lt;/a&gt; to
provide evidence of music&#x27;s efficacy or influence. Surely, enjoyment of the
sensation is evidence enough? (After all, from a utilitarian perspective, the
net sum of &quot;happiness&quot; in the world grows because of music.) Nevertheless, I&#x27;m
reminded of an episode of the  BBC programme
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagine_%28TV_series%29&quot;&gt;Imagine&lt;/a&gt;
from 2008 where
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Yentob&quot;&gt;Alan Yentob&lt;/a&gt; subjected
himself to an MRI scan while listening to music. Upon hearing
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jessye_Norman&quot;&gt;Jessye Norman&lt;/a&gt;
perform one of Strauss&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Last_Songs&quot;&gt;Four Last Songs&lt;/a&gt; -
music to which he acknowledged he had a special emotional attachment - his
brain was suffused with blood. As one reviewer
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/tv/reviews/last-nights-tv-when-a-bit-of-rhythm-beats-the-blues-839437.html&quot;&gt;put it&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;He listened to her and his mind blushed.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the MRI scanner allowed viewers to watch Yentob&#x27;s apparent physical
reaction to Norman&#x27;s performance it didn&#x27;t give us a sense of Yentob&#x27;s
obvious emotional reaction (obvious because he talks about how the music
makes him feel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, each of us has a different, very personal reaction
to music. What may seem like a heavenly performance to one person is a turgid
noise to another. The infant school recorder ensemble may bring tears to the
eyes for very different reasons, depending on who is listening. Some people
love to play certain pieces while others can&#x27;t stand the thought of another
damn performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of these reasons, attempting to pin down the experience of &quot;music&quot;
feels like an impossible task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even generalisations don&#x27;t work. For example, we may assert that music is
just a particular sort of sound; but then we&#x27;d need to explain
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_van_Beethoven&quot;&gt;Beethoven&lt;/a&gt;&#x27;s
composition technique. His deafness forced him to compose his later works
solely in his head - no actual sound was involved in the process despite it
being fundamentally musical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, some musicians disagree with the sentiment that music is in some
way a sub-set of sound. Take the renegade American composer
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Ives&quot;&gt;Charles Ives&lt;/a&gt; who
famously asked,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What has sound got to do with music!?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ives believed that music is in some way the underlying &quot;spirit&quot; of the
composer and (especially) the performer expressed through sound rather than
the sound itself. An alternative way to answer his question is to claim that
music is the feeling you get from sounds rather than the sounds
themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; rewarding to &quot;understand&quot; music and
&lt;a href=&quot;/article/pachelbel-canon&quot;&gt;know what&#x27;s going on&lt;/a&gt;. Discovering,
interpreting and describing the conceptual world of music is an interesting,
enhancing and intensifying experience. But there is a danger that we become
distracted by such intellectual diversions in a similar way that one might
become fixated by the form of a Sonnet while missing its meaning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Silent Noon&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
Your hands lie open in the long fresh grass, --&lt;/br&gt;
The finger-points look through like rosy blooms:&lt;/br&gt;
Your eyes smile peace. The pasture gleams and glooms&lt;/br&gt;
&#x27;Neath billowing skies that scatter and amass.&lt;/br&gt;
All round our nest, far as the eye can pass,&lt;/br&gt;
Are golden kingcup-fields with silver edge&lt;/br&gt;
Where the cow-parsley skirts the hawthorn-hedge.&lt;/br&gt;
&#x27;Tis visible silence, still as the hour-glass.&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
Deep in the sun-searched growths the dragon-fly&lt;/br&gt;
Hangs like a blue thread loosened from the sky: --&lt;/br&gt;
So this wing&#x27;d hour is dropt to us from above.&lt;/br&gt;
Oh! clasp we to our hearts, for deathless dower,&lt;/br&gt;
This close-companioned inarticulate hour&lt;/br&gt;
When twofold silence was the song of love.&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
~ Christina Rossetti
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christina_Rossetti&quot;&gt;Rosetti&lt;/a&gt;&#x27;s
poem was beautifully set to music by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ralph_Vaughan_Williams&quot;&gt;Ralph Vaughan-Williams&lt;/a&gt;
(my wife and I enjoy playing it together ~ me on piano, Mary on &#x27;cello).
Listen to the recording below; sit back, let the music and words wash over
you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/XgJfv_3p9uU?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I challenge you to be unmoved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 11:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Nothing to hide..?</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/hide</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/hide</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/hide&quot;&gt;Nothing to hide..?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Monday 19th May, 2014 (06:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On several occasions I have had to explain my position on privacy and
surveillance (especially in a digital context). To save me the task of
repeating myself, here it is in as simple a form as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;If you have nothing to hide, you have nothing to fear&quot; is a common
argument in support of the mass surveillance of citizens by the government or
the harvesting of user data by private corporations. Often it is made in a
reassuring manner, as demonstrated by
&lt;a href=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Hague&quot;&gt;William Hague&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/lWam4EWI48M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common re-statement of the argument goes, &quot;only if you&#x27;re doing something
wrong should you worry, and then you don&#x27;t deserve to keep it private&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m guessing many people will immediately sympathise with these sentiments.
After all, we don&#x27;t want the bad guys to gain the upper hand, you&#x27;re probably
a fine upstanding citizen and we should be happy that innocents are protected
from the evil-doers that such a drag net will identify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I beg to differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a start, this position is a classic
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_dilemma&quot;&gt;false dichotomy&lt;/a&gt;:
two seemingly black and white choices are given yet there are many ways to
address the subject. Such either/or thinking excludes the potential for
a more nuanced and subtle debate. Furthermore, such false dichotomies are a
favourite tactic in argument and, unless you know what you&#x27;re looking for,
can hoodwink many who take things at face value and stifle debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving this aside, the actual choices presented in the argument hide
various nasty &quot;home truths&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&#x27;s not you who determines if you have anything to hide&lt;/em&gt;.
    It doesn&#x27;t matter how upstanding a citizen you think
    &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; are; your point of view doesn&#x27;t matter in this context since
    it&#x27;s the law or (more dangerously) public opinion that judges you (viz.
    misjudged attacks on paediatricians). For example, teenagers growing up
    in the
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eastern_Bloc&quot;&gt;Eastern Bloc&lt;/a&gt; had
    to hide their enjoyment of &quot;corrupting capitalist music&quot; (such as Rock and
    Roll). While one&#x27;s taste in music is a relatively harmless attribute
    please consider the plight of
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT_rights_in_Singapore&quot;&gt;LGBT&lt;/a&gt;
    persons living in Singapore and elsewhere who risk legal challenges and
    remember the many curtailments of religious freedoms throughout
    history.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;It assumes surveillance results in correct data and sound
    judgement.&lt;/em&gt; People make mistakes and sometimes agents of the state
    or employees of corporations are &lt;em&gt;really stupid&lt;/em&gt; and don&#x27;t act in
    the public or customer&#x27;s interest. For example, remember the
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twitter_Joke_Trial&quot;&gt;Twitter joke
    trial&lt;/a&gt;? Given the context of the tweet it was obviously a joke, but
    the Police interpreted it differently. Is demonstrating a sense of humour
    a crime? I&#x27;d argue it&#x27;s a healthy sign of a liberal tradition of free
    speech.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rules change.&lt;/em&gt; For example, the UK&#x27;s
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regulation_of_Investigatory_Powers_Act_2000&quot;&gt;RIPA&lt;/a&gt;
    law gives the government powers to investigate and intercept
    communications on the grounds of &lt;em&gt;national security&lt;/em&gt;. Sounds
    reasonable. Yet the number of public authorities empowered to use this
    legislation has increased four times (in 2003, 2005, 2006 and 2010) and
    many such bodies use their powers for totally unintended things (such as
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1584808/Council-spy-cases-hit-1000-a-month.html&quot;&gt;tracking dog fouling&lt;/a&gt;).
    The result is supposedly water-tight legislation being subverted by local
    councils (I hardly think dog shit is an issue of national security).&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Breaking the law isn&#x27;t necessarily bad.&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gandhi&quot;&gt;Mohandas Ghandi&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmeline_Pankhurst&quot;&gt;Emmeline Pankhurst&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jesus&quot;&gt;Jesus&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nelson_Mandela&quot;&gt;Nelson Mandela&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socrates&quot;&gt;Socrates&lt;/a&gt;, and
    [insert any well known and well respected historical person who many
    believe have been a beacon of hope, progress and morality] all broke the
    law.  The law is often an Ass and breaking it is often the only way in
    which &quot;progress&quot; is made. Imagine how such persons and the causes they
    represent would have thrived in a digital
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Panopticon&quot;&gt;panopticon&lt;/a&gt;.
    (They wouldn&#x27;t.)&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Those who say privacy is dead are the ones that gain the most from
    surveillance.&lt;/em&gt; This one&#x27;s rather obvious but worth re-stating. Perhaps
    I&#x27;m being cynical, but when the CEOs of Facebook and Google both state
    &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.switched.com/2010/01/11/facebooks-mark-zuckerberg-claims-privacy-is-dead/&quot;&gt;privacy is dead&lt;/a&gt;
    you&#x27;ve got to wonder if this has something to do with their business
    interests (where they sell your data through targeted advertising).&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Privacy is a fundamental human right.&lt;/em&gt; Yes, I realise this is
    an argument from authority - specifically, the UN&#x27;s
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/documents/udhr/&quot;&gt;universal declaration of
    human rights&lt;/a&gt; - but I believe (and I&#x27;m guessing you do too) that
    intimate declarations of love, doctors discussing a patient, engineers
    developing a new top secret world changing product and journalists
    planning an expos&amp;eacute; of government corruption are just a few scenarios
    where privacy is both a reasonable and legitimate requirement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I suggesting &lt;em&gt;privacy trumps all&lt;/em&gt;? No. I would strongly argue
for openness when it comes to public institutions, the machinations of
government, our political representatives and corporations that deal with
personal data. How else are we to hold such entities to account?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am I saying there should be &lt;em&gt;no surveillance&lt;/em&gt;? Of course not, that
would be silly: I can think of plenty of legitimate reasons for surveillance
but &lt;strong&gt;none of them legitimise the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRISM_%28surveillance_program%29&quot;&gt;blanket surveillance of everyone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.
Furthermore, I&#x27;m not the only one who
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution&quot;&gt;believes this&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses,
papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be
violated, and no Warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by
Oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched,
and the persons or things to be seized.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know, the irony isn&#x27;t lost on me either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article was written in haste over lunch and tidied up after
work. Think of it as a first draft and please feel free to take pot shots -
&lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;I welcome&lt;/a&gt; constructive comments, critique and
ideas. ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT #1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A detective I know has pointed out that,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Ripa isn&#x27;t (and never was) just for national security, that is only one part of the act.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stand corrected! :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was trying to demonstrate how laws can suffer from &quot;scope creep&quot;:
once legitimate and sensible legislation being used in quite unintended and
nefarious ways. My detective buddy (who also happens to have a
philosophy degree and is exactly the sort of ethical, thoughtful and smart
person you&#x27;d hope would be working as a detective) understood exactly what I
was getting at so pointed out that,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Law creep might be better with terrorism stop and search powers
where more people are stopped and searched without any actual individual
justification. That seems a more clean cut issue to my mind; specific powers
being used to blanket cover areas.

Or laws set up to manage serious sex offenders also catching idiots - the guy
who drops his trousers while drunk on a night out in town now has to notify
any change of address and register as a sex offender!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great stuff!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>