<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>Testing CircuitPython Modules</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/circuitpython-tests&quot;&gt;Testing CircuitPython Modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Monday, 25th November 2019 (1:30PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://micropython.org/&quot;&gt;MicroPython&lt;/a&gt;, a project by my
buddy &lt;a href=&quot;http://dpgeorge.net/&quot;&gt;Damien George&lt;/a&gt;, is a
complete reimplementation of the Python programming language for
microcontrollers and embedded systems. Put simply, it&#x27;s Python for extremely
small computers (and I once
&lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920056515.do&quot;&gt;wrote a book about it&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;a href=&quot;https://circuitpython.org/&quot;&gt;CircuitPython&lt;/a&gt;, a friendly fork of
MicroPython, is sponsored by the fantastic folks
at &lt;a href=&quot;https://adafruit.com/&quot;&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;, a company who make playful and
easy-to-use &quot;hackable&quot; technology while promoting a welcoming, friendly and
diverse community of makers. They are led by legendary founder and electrical
engineer extraordinaire, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ladyada.net/&quot;&gt;Limor &quot;ladyada&quot; Fried&lt;/a&gt;.
CircuitPython is MicroPython for Adafruit&#x27;s line of boards and with a
consistent API for accessing the numerous bits of cool hardware you can use
with such devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was privileged to recently complete a block of work for Adafruit: I&#x27;ve
written a CircuitPython module called &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; that makes it
easy for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth&quot;&gt;Bluetooth&lt;/a&gt; enabled
Adafruit boards to communicate with each other. The API is
a simplified version of the work myself and a number of other volunteers did on
the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://microbit-micropython.readthedocs.io/en/v1.0.1/radio.html&quot;&gt;equivalent functionality&lt;/a&gt;
for the BBC micro:bit (&lt;a href=&quot;https://microbit-micropython.readthedocs.io/en/v1.0.1/tutorials/radio.html&quot;&gt;here&#x27;s a tutorial I wrote for the micro:bit
radio&lt;/a&gt;, to make electronic &quot;fireflies&quot; blink at each other over
Bluetooth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new Adafruit module, sending a message is as simple as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()
r.send(&quot;Hello&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving requires a loop (to allow the device to keep checking for
messages), but is equally as simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()

while True:
    message = r.receive()
    if message:
        # Do something useful with the message.
        print(message)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best model for thinking about this module is that of kids&#x27;
walkie-talkies. Each
radio is tuned to a certain channel upon which it broadcasts and receives.
If you send a message, anyone else listening in on that channel and within
range will receive it. You&#x27;ll also receive messages broadcast on that
channel from others within range. 
This is an ideal network topology because it&#x27;s both familiar
yet capable since other, more specialised, network topologies can be built on
top of it. There is potential for users to grow from a simple &quot;walkie-talkie&quot;
model of networking to something more sophisticated and of their own
devising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/walkie-talkie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kids on walkie-talkies&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The channels in the module are numbered between 0-255 and can be set when
creating a &lt;code&gt;Radio&lt;/code&gt; object (the default channel number is 42 in
honour of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_Adams&quot;&gt;Douglas Adams&lt;/a&gt;, who
saw so much humane potential in new technology yet mischievously warned of the
polluting effect of technology for technology&#x27;s sake via the inept
work of the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technology_in_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Sirius_Cybernetics_Corporation&quot;&gt;Sirius Cybernetics Corporation&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio(channel=123)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can change channel at any time via the &lt;code&gt;Radio&lt;/code&gt;
object&#x27;s &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; method (continuing the example above):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;r.configure(channel=7)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in addition to sending strings of characters it&#x27;s also possible to
send and receive arbitrary bytes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from adafruit_radio import Radio
r = Radio()
r.send_bytes(b&quot;Hello&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving bytes gives you the full context of the message expressed as a
Python tuple consisting of three values: the raw bytes, the RSSI reading (i.e.
strength of the signal, from 0 [max] to -255 [min]), and a timestamp
representing the number (and fraction of) seconds since the device powered up,
as demonstrated in the following REPL based example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; from adafruit_radio import Radio
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r = Radio()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; r.receive_full()
(b&#x27;Hello&#x27;, -40, 3245.155408037)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&#x27;s it! You can find the code in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntoll/Adafruit_CircuitPython_Radio&quot;&gt;this GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.
Special mention and thanks must be made to Adafruit&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://tannewt.org/&quot;&gt;Scott Shawcroft&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://danhalbert.org/&quot;&gt;Dan Halbert&lt;/a&gt; who
wrote the Bluetooth API I used. Because of their
work I was able to create my module with less than a hundred lines of Python
(at time of writing). Thanks chaps!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this context, I&#x27;m going to explain why and how I created a
comprehensive test suite for the &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d summarise my approach to testing as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Testing is fundamental for creating and maintaining well designed
    software. My experience is that it tends to produce code that is both
    simple and easy to understand because nobody wants to write complicated
    tests to exercise equally complicated code. The process of exercising code
    through tests forces a developer to think carefully about how their code
    is written while having the added benefit of demonstrating it works as
    expected. Simplicity and ease of understanding are
    desirable properties because such code is easier to read, correct and
    maintain and also indicates the author&#x27;s own clarity of thought (a good
    sign). I also believe it helpful and friendly to write code that&#x27;s easy
    for others to read and understand (I often imagine my code will be read by
    an intelligent beginner coder, because it forces me to explain and address
    my own assumptions about my code).&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;I personally don&#x27;t practice strict test-driven development, where one
    writes tests before writing the implementation. I prefer to explore,
    improvise, extemporise and play at first. I often try various different
    approaches to the task in hand and regularly re-draft. I&#x27;ll often seek
    advice and comments from collaborators, colleagues and potential users of
    my code as soon as possible. Therefore, my highest priority when I start a
    new project is making my code simple enough so that it is very easy to
    change. Often this step in the coding process is called a &quot;spike&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Only when a project settles on a certain architecture, implementation
    or foundation of code do I add tests. I think of this as a sort of
    &quot;hardening&quot; process. When I&#x27;m happy with an approach I&#x27;ll often re-draft
    the exploratory code I&#x27;ve already written, alongside writing tests to
    exercise that specific piece of code. I aim for, and often achieve, 100%
    test coverage (every line of my code is exercised in some way by a test).
    This process allows me to get a feel for how my API works from the point of
    view of a fellow coder encountering it for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;The hardening has another effect: I&#x27;ve baked in an expectation for how
    the code should behave via the tests. I also make sure my tests are
    commented in such a way that a meaningful intention behind the test is
    revealed. They&#x27;re also a useful source of information for future users
    and/or maintainers of my code. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, they
    help manage change.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;No useful software is ever finished simply because the universe changes
    (and so must software). Despite our best efforts, software is often
    complicated and it&#x27;s easy to forget something or not realise how a change
    in one part of the
    code may break another apparently unrelated part. Having a suite of
    tests to check all the aspects of a codebase helps future maintainers make
    changes with confidence.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;Being pragmatic, I sometimes don&#x27;t follow the playful explorations
    outlined above. If I&#x27;m dealing with a well defined or mature protocol
    (for example), I&#x27;ll quickly settle on an approach, usually based upon
    research into how other folks have solved the same problem, and proceed by
    writing tests based upon the protocol in order to measure the completeness,
    accuracy and progress of my resulting implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem for developers writing for CircuitPython is that such code is
usually to be run on microcontrollers with certain hardware capabilities. Yet
such code is invariably written on conventional computers running operating
systems such as Windows, OSX or Linux. The only way to know your code works is
to try it on the target device. This is, to say the least, laborious compared
to having the benefits of running an extensive test suite in a matter of
seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having written my small and simple &lt;code&gt;adafruit_radio&lt;/code&gt; module I
found myself missing the benefits of a comprehensive test suite. After asking
around, I found most Python modules for CircuitPython don&#x27;t have a test suite
and there hadn&#x27;t been much (if any) exploration for how to address this. Scott
suggested I add what I thought best in terms of testing to my module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted my solution to meet the following requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It works with existing Python testing tools so non-specialist Python
    developers feel at home and can bring their existing skills to
    CircuitPython with little effort.&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;It runs on a conventional computer, because that&#x27;s where developers do
    the majority of their work. (I&#x27;m constantly running and re-running my
    test-suite as I make changes to code.)&lt;/li&gt;

    &lt;li&gt;It handles the problem of using CircuitPython-only modules in a
    test-suite run on a conventional computer with standard Python.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to focus on using an existing, well known and mature Python
testing tool called &lt;a href=&quot;http://pytest.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;PyTest&lt;/a&gt; (the
creation of another friend of mine, the extraordinarily prolific and very
thoughtful &lt;a href=&quot;https://holgerkrekel.net/&quot;&gt;Holger Krekel&lt;/a&gt;). The
advantage of using PyTest is that it has a large number of plug-ins that are
both useful and familiar to a large number of Python programmers. One such
plug-in I use a lot is the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pytest-dev/pytest-cov&quot;&gt;Pytest coverage tool&lt;/a&gt;,
which makes it easy to spot areas of a code base that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; 
exercised by a test suite. PyTest also has a well defined mechanisms to extend
it to work in specialist testing situations (such as our own CircuitPython
based context).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I was concerned, using PyTest met the first two of my self-imposed
requirements. I was left with the final problem of dealing with CircuitPython
only modules that wouldn&#x27;t work on a conventional computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I need to introduce the concept of &quot;mocking&quot; in a test suite
(as in &quot;mocked up&quot; rather than poking fun). Mocking is a way to replace parts
of your system under test with &quot;mocked up&quot; objects and then make assertions
about how such objects have been used. Thanks to another friend of mine (the
huge hearted, funny and rather hairy
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.voidspace.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Michael Foord&lt;/a&gt;), mocking is built
right into Python&#x27;s standard library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My idea was simple: automatically mock away those parts of CircuitPython
that don&#x27;t work on a conventional computer. Such objects give the developer a
way to check and ensure the module under test is working as expected with
CircuitPython. It&#x27;s even possible to specify how such mock objects should
behave under certain conditions (such as when they may be the source of some
sort of data which the module under test will use). However, this aspect of
mocking should be used with great care -- more on which later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a developer creates a &lt;code&gt;conftest.py&lt;/code&gt; file in their test suite
PyTest will import it before running any of the test code and use various
functions found therein to configure the test suite. For example, if PyTest
finds a function called &lt;code&gt;pytest_runtest_setup&lt;/code&gt; in the
&lt;code&gt;conftest.py&lt;/code&gt; file, then this function will always be called
immediately prior to any test function. Just what we need!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntoll/Adafruit_CircuitPython_Radio/blob/master/tests/conftest.py&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;conftest.py file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
is very short and simply mocks away named aspects of CircuitPython which cannot
be run on a conventional computer immediately before any test is run, via the
aforementioned &lt;code&gt;pytest_runtest_setup&lt;/code&gt; convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means I can write conventional looking PyTest based unit tests like the
following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;def test_radio_receive_full_no_messages(radio):
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    If no messages are detected by receive_full then it returns None.
    &quot;&quot;&quot;
    radio.ble.start_scan.return_value = []
    assert radio.receive_full() is None
    radio.ble.start_scan.assert_called_once_with(
        adafruit_radio.AdafruitRadio, minimum_rssi=-255, timeout=1
    )
    radio.ble.stop_scan.assert_called_once_with()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things you should know: &lt;code&gt;radio.ble&lt;/code&gt; is a mocked away part of
CircuitPython. As a result, on the first line of my test function, I&#x27;ve been
able to tell the mock that the result of calling the &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt;
method is an empty list. Then I can assert that the method I want to test (the
&lt;code&gt;radio.receive_full&lt;/code&gt; method returns &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt; in this
context. Furthermore, I&#x27;m able to check in the final two statements of the
function that the &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt; method was called with the expected
arguments, and that an additional &lt;code&gt;stop_scan&lt;/code&gt; method was called
too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I run the test suite, I see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ pytest --cov-report term-missing --cov=adafruit_radio tests/
============================= test session starts ==============================
platform linux -- Python 3.7.5, pytest-5.3.0, py-1.8.0, pluggy-0.13.0
rootdir: /home/ntoll/src/adafruit_radio
plugins: cov-2.8.1
collected 12 items                                                             

tests/test_adafruit_radio.py ............                                [100%]

----------- coverage: platform linux, python 3.7.5-final-0 -----------
Name                Stmts   Miss  Cover   Missing
-------------------------------------------------
adafruit_radio.py      61      0   100%


============================== 12 passed in 0.09s ==============================
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note all the feedback about code coverage..! Neat, huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mock object, by its very nature, is a mock-up of something else... it&#x27;s
not the real thing..! So what happens when the real thing (that has been
mocked-up in the test suite) changes? For instance let&#x27;s imagine that the
result of a call to &lt;code&gt;start_scan&lt;/code&gt; is no longer an empty list, but
something else. The tests will still pass because the mocked-up object doesn&#x27;t
reflect the real object, yet when the module under test is used on a real
device with the changed version of CircuitPython then it won&#x27;t work
correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously not a good situation and why I mention mocks should be
used with great care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious solution is for the developer in charge of the test
suite to be careful and check API updates in the release notes of the modules
being mocked away. However, this becomes a burden if the test suite mocks away
a huge number of modules. It&#x27;s also open to human error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to mitigate this problem, but because it&#x27;s early days
I&#x27;ve not been able to investigate these potential solutions properly. The best
I can do at this point in time is shrug my shoulders, say things are under
construction and invite folks to dive in and help. Our community would
certainly be enriched by such collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I&#x27;m quite pleased with this first step in equipping
CircuitPython modules with comprehensive test suites. Yet there&#x27;s still plenty
to do -- most notably, ways to address the problems mentioned with mocking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, comments, constructive criticism and ideas expressed in a
friendly, collaborative and supportive manner are most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over to you... :-)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 13:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>PyWeek Retrospective</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/pyweek</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/pyweek</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/pyweek&quot;&gt;PyWeek Retrospective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Tuesday, 23rd April 2019 (4:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pyweek.org/&quot;&gt;PyWeek&lt;/a&gt; is a simple idea: write a game,
using the Python programming language, from scratch, on a given theme, within a
week. Take part as either an individual or a member of a team entry. At the end
of the week play, feedback and score each others&#x27; entries. After which, an
individual and team are crowned respective champions for their category of
entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have taken part in three different iterations of PyWeek. Each one has
been extraordinarily good fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first PyWeek was as an individual entry. The theme was &quot;two worlds&quot;, so
I imagined a paper based battle between the worlds of blue biros and red biros
(it felt like a good idea at the time...). I wanted to push the limits of my
&lt;a href=&quot;https://codewith.mu/&quot;&gt;Mu code editor&lt;/a&gt; for beginner programmers and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pygame-zero.readthedocs.io/en/stable/&quot;&gt;PyGameZero&lt;/a&gt; (a
gaming framework for beginner programmers integrated into Mu, developed by my
buddy [and organiser of PyWeek] &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;http://mauveweb.co.uk/&gt;Dan Pope&lt;/a&gt;).
The end result was a side-scrolling chase game called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntoll/paperchase&quot;&gt;PaperChase&lt;/a&gt;. This video shows
me testing the game with my (then) thirteen year old son... you&#x27;ll quickly
get the idea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/z_wGpJubVwI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next entry was as part of a team. I&#x27;d been helping author and
journalist
&lt;a href=&quot;https://andrewsmithauthor.com/&quot;&gt;Andrew Smith&lt;/a&gt; to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.1843magazine.com/features/code-to-joy&quot;&gt;take his
first steps into coding&lt;/a&gt;. Making a game seemed like a fun vehicle for
further learning. The theme was &quot;flow&quot; and so we devised a simple
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frogger&quot;&gt;Frogger&lt;/a&gt; clone
where you avoided traffic flow whilst being chased by lumbering zombies.
I did the code and Andrew did the sound and music. The end result
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ntoll/traffic_flowmageddon&quot;&gt;Trafficflowmageddon&lt;/a&gt;)
is, I feel, quite cute... as zombie relate games go...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/08mvNmhOVG4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so we come to the most recent PyWeek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, Andrew and I teamed up. We chatted before hand about the sort
of game we might want to make. Since we both have a love of the written word we
decided to go with a text-based (rather than graphical) game -- the theory
being it would play to our &quot;strengths&quot; with the written word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, this was (by far and away) my favourite PyWeek so far. Here&#x27;s
why...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphical games show, text based games describe. Graphical games have an
added cost of &quot;asset&quot; development (the graphical stuff shown on the screen)
whereas text based games only need typed characters. Graphical games tend to
focus on hand/eye skill to progress gameplay, whereas textual games necessarily
put narrative, meaning and intent at the centre of their process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, these are broad generalisations. But what I want to get to is
the idea of a player engaging with a game imaginatively, emotionally and
intellectually via the medium of words. If done properly, the depth of
engagement is potentially greater. I&#x27;m not saying one can&#x27;t be engaged in such
a way with graphical games, rather that textual games are perhaps a medium
which more easily lend themselves to this end. It&#x27;s similar to the difference
between a book and a film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear, I&#x27;m not saying one is better than the other, these are
very different ways to tell a story or play a game, but I can&#x27;t help but feel a
&quot;reader&quot; has to do more (and the reward is therefore greater) than a
&quot;viewer&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that text-based games are, in a sense, more egalitarian and
accessible. Again, to continue the book/film similarity, while no mean feat,
writing a book is within the realms of a single author armed with just a pen
and paper, whereas making a film requires a cast of collaborators and
specialists, equipment, facilities, locations and deep pockets. For similar
reasons, the generation and manipulation of textual game content is far simpler
and affordable than for graphical games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what sort of games are textual?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy! &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colossal_Cave_Adventure&quot;&gt;Adventure games&lt;/a&gt;!
If you&#x27;re interested in finding out more about this style of text-based game
you should watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o15itQ_EhRo&quot;&gt;GET LAMP&lt;/a&gt;,
a fascinating documentary about the genre. Alternatively, if you want to try
playing an example of such a game, I&#x27;ve embedded one of my favourites below
(just click on it and type some commands). It&#x27;s based on Douglas Adams&#x27;
&quot;Hitchhiker&#x27;s Guide to the Galaxy&quot; (the game itself was co-authored by
Adams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot; style=&quot;border: 1px #ccc solid !important;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://iplayif.com/?story=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.douglasadams.com%2Fcreations%2Fhhgg.z3&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s where it gets interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such games don&#x27;t have to be single player, solo efforts. While this is a fun
way to play, things get far more interesting if you can play with others. This
is not a new idea and I remember playing such games (commonly called
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MUD&quot;&gt;MUD&lt;/a&gt; &quot;Multi-User Dungeons&quot;) via
surreptitious use of my school&#x27;s single 1200 baud modem when the teacher wasn&#x27;t
looking. These were often Tolkien-esque fantasy themed virtual worlds where
players could wander about exploring, socialising and cooperating to achieve
some in-game outcome (usually a quest of some sort). Later, when I was at
university in the mid-1990s, I began using a type of multi-user textual world
called a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOO&quot;&gt;MOO&lt;/a&gt; (Multi-user Object
Oriented). The wonderful thing about MOO based textual worlds is that they are
programmable by users (I first got to grips with object-orientation via
learning to program MOO). In a sense the MOO is both the game and a platform
for creating textual games collaboratively. It was this sense of a creative
textual virtual world that Andrew and I wanted to recreate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Et voilà, &quot;TextSmith&quot; was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theme for this most recent PyWeek was announced as &quot;six&quot;. This
fitted our idea for an interactive textual platform. It could contain six
different literary worlds which players collaboratively create, inhabit and
explore together. The six literary worlds we &quot;seeded&quot; in our game were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jane Austen: Recreate Netherfield, go to a ball, affect regency period
    manners and etiquette.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Poetic Passions: Everything is a poem, haiku or rhymes, speak in
    riddles or chat in rhyming couplets.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Hardboiled Detectives: It was about eleven o&#x27;clock in the morning, with
    the sun not shining. The client asked, &quot;Well, will you take the case or
    not, bud?&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;J.R.R.Fantasy: Orcs! Elves! Wizards! Bleak locations! Ancient mystery!
    Quests! (And impenetrable prose.)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;SciFi and Future Worlds: As the service droids efficiently cleaned up
    the remains of the ship&#x27;s captain, I wondered how long it would take to
    make planet-fall on the alien world of Zaonce.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Parry Hotter: Inspired by everyone&#x27;s favourite boy wizard, but in such
    a way that Warner Brothers don&#x27;t go after us for copyright infringement.
    :-)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming the game was a lot of fun. I managed to build everything mostly
from scratch (except for the web based front-end which uses the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/pgjones/quart&quot;&gt;Quart&lt;/a&gt; web microframework).
Sadly, most of it was unfinished, broken and clunkily implemented. The
important thing is that it has &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt;. Below is a screenshot of
an early version of the game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/textsmith.png&quot; alt=&quot;The TextSmith client.&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily, despite the unfinished and rather shonky nature of the end result,
we placed 4th in the team category..! Our highest result..! The
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pyweek.org/e/CodeToJoy/ratings/&quot;&gt;feedback&lt;/a&gt;
from fellow PyWeekers was encouraging too and, as a result, I&#x27;ve decided to
continue to develop TextSmith. In the immediate term this will involve plugging
in the almost-finished scripting language I created and knock off some of the
hard edges. More importantly, once this aspect of the &quot;platform&quot; settles down,
I&#x27;m looking forward to creating and exploring interactive literary worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, programming, creating and playing with TextSmith has been a very
rich seam of reflection in terms of both technical and playful contexts. I&#x27;ve
had lots of fun thinking about the architecture and implementation of such a
platform while also doing a philosophical deep-dive into what on earth is going
on when &quot;players&quot; connect to, create within and interact with such a
platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows where this may lead..?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Make a Joyful Noise</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/joyful-noise</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/joyful-noise</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/joyful-noise&quot;&gt;Make a Joyful Noise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Wednesday, 13th February 2019 (4:00PM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a new tuba!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If my mention of a tuba is a surprise (it
&lt;a href=&quot;/article/remembering-john&quot;&gt;shouldn&#x27;t&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/article/vaughan-williams-tuba-concerto-programme-notes&quot;&gt;be&lt;/a&gt;),
check out this short student-film, by my buddy
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cluttercup&quot;&gt;Jane&lt;/a&gt;, which explains all:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/YlS9lpybYxo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new tuba isn&#x27;t a replacement for my current instrument (which I got when
I was sixteen years old). Rather, the instruments complement each other. What&#x27;s
the difference? If my current tuba is a professional &quot;all rounder&quot;, my new
instrument is a sort of &quot;heavy duty&quot; tuba for big orchestral pieces (most of my
current playing is orchestral).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tuba works by amplifying the buzzing sound I make with my lips
into a mouthpiece. I change notes by tensing or relaxing my lips (so the
buzzing sound gets higher or lower) which gives me a limited series of notes
that are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overtone&quot;&gt;overtones&lt;/a&gt; to the
&quot;fundamental&quot; (lowest) note produced by blowing down the length of the tube of
the instrument. I use valves to add tubing to the length of the instrument to
fill in the notes between the overtones so I can play all the notes I need
(i.e. a chromatic scale).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&#x27;s interesting is how the two instruments are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My original instrument is pitched in Eb (E flat) -- which means the
instrument&#x27;s fundamental note is the Eb more than an octave below the bass
clef (i.e. very low). My new instrument is pitched in C, so its fundamental
note is &lt;em&gt;even lower&lt;/em&gt;, thus making it an instrument more suited to lower
sounding music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The valves on each instrument are different. I have &quot;piston&quot; valves on my
original instrument. These are spring loaded and when pressed fully down add
additional lengths of tubing to the instrument. The photograph below is of the
inside of the valve so you can see the holes in the piston used to connect 
the different pipes, depending on the valve&#x27;s position (up or down).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/piston_valve.jpg&quot;
    alt=&quot;The inside of a piston valve.&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new instrument uses &quot;rotary&quot; valves. These, as the diagram below shows,
rotate to connect additional lengths of tubing (the passage of air is indicated
by the hatched area). A sort of lever is used to actuate each valve. They&#x27;re
generally much quieter and more reliable than piston valves (less moving parts
to make clanking sounds) although they can be slower to &quot;engage&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/rotary_valve.jpg&quot;
    alt=&quot;A diagramatic view of a rotary valve.&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture below shows the rotary valves on my new tuba. Notice the
levers I press with my fingers to engage the valves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/rotary_valves.jpg&quot;
    alt=&quot;Rotary valves on my new tuba.&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both tubas look &quot;tuba shaped&quot; my original tuba points to the right
(as the player is looking at the instrument) whereas my new instrument points
to the left. This simply means I have to hold them differently and there&#x27;s not
really any change in sound. You can see this difference in the picture
below (the new tuba is on the right):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/two_tubas.jpg&quot;
    alt=&quot;My two tubas.&quot;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final major difference is in the number of valves each instrument has.
My original instrument has four &quot;compensating&quot; valves which allow me to get a
full chromatic scale. The new instrument has five &quot;non-compensating&quot; valves:
the first four work like my original instrument and allow me to play a full
chromatic scale, but the fifth valve is used to help tune the very lowest
notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does the new tuba need a special extra &quot;tuning&quot; valve and what on earth
am I talking about when I say &quot;compensating&quot;..? This, dear reader, is where
maths, acoustics, logic and music come together in a spectacular fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new tuba is approximately 524.9 cm in length without any valves engaged.
This produces the note, &quot;C&quot;. The first valve adds enough pipe to lower the
pitch by a tone, giving me a &quot;Bb&quot; (B flat) which requires the total length of
tube to be 589.2 cm. Simple arithmetic tells us the total length of the tube
added by using the first valve is therefore 64.3 cm (the &quot;open&quot; length of the
instrument with the added tube should give the correct length to play a tone
lower). The second valve drops the pitch by a semitone to the note &quot;B&quot; which
requires a total length of 556.1 cm. Similarly, the third valve lowers the
pitch by one and a half tones, giving me an &quot;A&quot; which requires the total length
of tube to be 624.2 cm. Again, the simple arithmetic tells me that the length
of tube added by the second valve is 31.2 cm while the length added by the
third valve is 99.3 cm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s where it gets interesting. If I want to play the note &quot;G&quot; I need to
make the length of the instrument 700.6 cm. Given the note &quot;G&quot; is two and a
half tones below &quot;C&quot; I could take the tone provided by the first valve and
one and a half tones of the third valve and use them together. It means the
resulting length of additional pipe is 64.3 cm (the first valve) + 99.3 cm 
(the third valve) giving me a total of 163.6 cm. However, the open length of
the instrument (524.9 cm) with the additional lengths of pipe (163.6) brings
the total length to 688.5 cm, which isn&#x27;t the 700.6 cm needed to play the
note in tune!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is to use my fourth valve, which adds 175.7 cm to the length
of the instrument, thus making it in tune. However, when I need to use my
fourth valve in combination with my other three valves I still encounter the
same sort of &quot;wrong length of pipe&quot; problem I describe above. I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt;
use combinations of valves in order to get all the notes I need in the
chromatic scale. So what can I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the fifth valve on my new tuba comes into play. It has a
special tuning slide I can adjust &quot;in real time&quot; as I play, thus allowing me
to tune the fifth valve as and when I need it. It can also be tuned in such a
way that it &quot;compensates&quot; (remember that word) for the missing lengths of
tubing when I use the other valves together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leaves us with the problem of keeping my current tuba (with only four
valves) in tune. Thankfully, this instrument has &quot;compensating&quot; valves which
work in a rather ingenious manner. The schematic representation of my current
tuba is shown below. The mouthpiece is on the left with the bell on the right
and between are the four valves and associated tubing (not to scale). None of
the valves are engaged so the column of air blown through the instrument goes
directly through without any &quot;detours&quot; (as shown by the pipe filled in with
blue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/compensating_open.png&quot;
    alt=&quot;Compensating system, no valves pressed.&quot;/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I press the first and third valves down the expected two extra lengths
of tubing are added, as shown by the two loops of pipe filled with blue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/compensating_13.png&quot;
    alt=&quot;Compensating system, valves 1 and 3 pressed.&quot;/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s where it gets really clever. When the fourth valve is pressed down,
not only is the expected additional length of tube added to the length of the
instrument, but this tube is also diverted back through the other three valves
which have additional &quot;compensating&quot; tubes to bring the instrument in tune:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/static/images/compensating_134.png&quot;
    alt=&quot;Compensating system, valves 1, 3 and 4 pressed.&quot;/&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is, essentially, a logical &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; expressed as pipe-work. If
the first and fourth valves are pressed then add some new &quot;compensating&quot; length
of pipe. Clever huh..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of this system is the air does two &quot;circuits&quot; around the
instrument (once through the first three valves, and then again if the fourth
valve is pressed so the compensating pipes can come into effect). This makes
the instrument harder to blow (since there are more bends to blow through).
My new instrument feels like there is less to push against when I&#x27;m
playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, given all the technical tuba-related geekery described above I want
to end on an artistic note...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These instruments are beautiful to look at and playing them is a joy. It&#x27;s
hard to explain to folks who have never performed music what an amazing
privilege it is. I get to play beautifully designed and precision engineered
instruments as part of an orchestra, band or smaller ensemble. By playing with
my fellow musicians to an audience I&#x27;m taking part in a unique social activity.
No matter the mood or difficulty of the piece I&#x27;m playing, I love the sense of
non-verbal communication I have with my fellow musicians and collectively with
the audience. I love that I am a part of something creative, challenging,
expressive, collaborative and most definitely greater than the sum of its
parts. That the audience appreciate these efforts is a lovely positive
side effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is always &quot;joyful noise&quot;. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>