<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>What is music?</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/what-is-music</link>
        <description><h1><a href="/article/what-is-music">What is music?</a></h1><p class="published_on">Friday 4th April (8:00AM)</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/54763818?badge=0" width="712" height="400" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p><small><a href="http://vimeo.com/54763818">Understand Music</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/finallystudio">finally.</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</small></p>

<p>"What is music?" is an impossible question to answer. Everyone has
different, very personal reactions to music and, as the video suggests, you
don't need to understand music to know that you like it. What may seem like a
heavenly performance to one person is a turgid noise to another. The voice of
a certain singer may bring tears to the eyes for very different and
contrasting reasons. Attending a concert may be a semi-religious experience
for some, yet is an excuse for others to see and be seen.</p>

<p>Even generalisations don't work. For example, we may assert that music is
just a particular sort of sound; but then we'd need to explain
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_van_Beethoven">Beethoven</a>'s
composition technique. His deafness forced him to compose his later works
solely in his head - no actual sound was involved in the process despite it
being fundamentally musical.</p>

<p>In fact, some musicians disagree with the sentiment that "music" is in some
way a sub-set of "sound". Take the renegade American composer
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Ives">Charles Ives</a> who
famously asked,</p>

<blockquote>What has sound got to do with music!?
</blockquote>

<p>His point being that music is in some way the underlying "spirit" of the
composer and (especially) the performer expressed through sound rather than
the sound itself.</p>

<p>So, instead of attempting to answer an impossible questions I'll focus
my efforts elsewhere are explore the elements and concepts that are commonly
used to describe music. Naming and explaining such things is less contentious
and provides a shared vocabulary for discussing music.</p>

<p>We start by identifying who is involved in music.</p>

<h2>Listening, Performing and Composing</h2>

<p>Music is usually experienced in three different ways:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Listening to music (hearing a performance or recording)</li>
    <li> Performing music (making a composition into sound)</li>
    <li>Creating music (composing or improvising)</li>
</ul>

<p>(Actually, there is a fourth way: hearing music with your inner ear [you
hear it in your head in a similar way to silent reading]. We won't be dealing
with this sort of musical experience in this article.)</p>

<p>There is overlap between these three experiences: improvisation is both
composing and performing music in the heat of the moment and performing in a
group involves a huge amount of listening and reacting to the other members (a
musician's so-called "sense of ensemble"). In contrast, some musical
experiences fall exclusively within one realm: does a performance of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Cage">John Cage</a>'s
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4%E2%80%B233%E2%80%B3">4'33"</a> have
a performer or composer (even though both would be listed on the concert
programme)? It would certainly have at least one listener, the alleged
"performer".</p>

<p>We're all listeners because of our capacity to hear sounds that we discern
to be music. This is an important point: listening to music is not a passive
experience with you as the mere recipient of sound. It requires your
engagement so that you discern that the music is doing such and such a thing.
This may be simply having just an appreciation of the pulse of the music (you
"feel" the rhythm in exactly the same way you know when to move your body when
dancing to music). Nevertheless, there are countless examples of music that is
heard but not listened to,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elevator_music">Muzak</a> being a case
in point, and we're happy to filter it out of our attention and direct our
minds elsewhere.</p>

<p>All performers listen. They also use their bodies, instruments or other
equipment to make sound. Often, the sounds they make are pre-ordained because
they're performing a piece that is already composed. On other occasions
they're making up sounds as they go along but, crucially, such sounds still
fit into a pre-ordained structures: they're playing in a particular key or to
a certain set of pre-arranged harmonies (such as the instantly recognisable
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/12_bar_blues">12 bar blues</a>). In
any case, the performer needs to listen to what they're doing (and who they're
doing it with, remember that sense of ensemble?) to ensure the resulting
sounds meet their expectations.</p>

<p>Deaf musicians who canot hear the sounds being made are, in some sense,
still listening to the music. They literally feel the vibrations caused by the
sounds. The percussionist
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evelyn_Glennie">Evelyn Glennie</a>
plays barefoot for this very reason.</p>

<p>No matter how one "listens", all performers are involved in a tight
feedback loop that involves making sounds, listening, evaluating and adapting
as required at the moment of performance.</p>

<p>Performing also requires enough skill to make the performance any good.
Anyone who has heard a performance given by a class of recorder playing
five-year-olds will intuitively understand this. If only
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach">Johann Sebastian
Bach</a> was right when he quipped,</p>

<blockquote>It's easy to play any musical instrument: all you have to do is
touch the right key at the right time and the instrument will play itself.
</blockquote>

<p>Becoming a good performer requires deliberate practice and enough
confidence to know that you can "pull off" a performance. My tuba professor
at the <a href="http://rcm.ac.uk/">Royal College of Music</a>, the late
<a href="http://andrewhugill.com/manuals/tuba/index.html">John Jenkins</a>,
explained that a performer needed to be self-confident almost to the
point of arrogance.</p>

<p>Performers create music, but so do composers in a very different sense.
It's hard to describe what the mysterious activity of composition entails, but
it certainly contains an understanding of performance (how else is a composer
to know what works in their chosen musical medium?) and excellent listening
skills to evaluate the music they produce. It also involves a sense of style.
New types of music don't just spring out of nowhere. Often they're an
evolution of existing styles (for example,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ragtime">Ragtime</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blues">Blues</a> and other musical
styles evolved into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jazz">Jazz</a>),
or a combination of different traditions
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bhangra_%28music%29">Bhangra</a> is
a mix of Punjabi and Western popular music). In any case, being able to pin
down the specifics of what makes a certain musical style identifiable is a
vague business: there are always exceptions to the rule and the rules are
often wrong in the first place. Yet those who compose appear to
appreciate such stylistic concerns (at the risk of producing something
incomprehensible).</p>

<p>Composing ultimately involves an understanding of the nuts and bolts of
music: the various building blocks that come together to make a piece. But
what might these building blocks be?</p>

<h2>Elements of Music</h2>

<p>Pitch, rhythm, melody, harmony, dynamics, timbre, expression, form</p>

<p><small>Image credits:
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Socrates_Louvre.jpg">Socrates</a>.
&copy; 2005
<a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utilisateur:Sting">Eric Gaba</a>
(under a
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/deed.en">creative commons</a>
license).
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/8236043793/">Keep off the Grass</a>. &copy; 2012
<a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/">Mirsasha</a> (under a
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/deed.en_GB">creative commons</a> license).
</small></p>
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 April 2014 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Autonomy</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/autonomy</link>
        <description><h1><a href="/article/autonomy">Autonomy</a></h1><p class="published_on">Monday 24th March (8:00AM)</p>

<p>I believe autonomy is important. I like to think I have personal autonomy.
I also think it important as a political end to be promoted by institutions
in our wider society.</p>

<p>This article is a reflection upon autonomy.</p>

<p>The etymology of "autonomy" is derived from Greek for "autos" (self) and
"nomos" (rule or law). It was originally applied to city states where citizens
were free to live by their own laws rather than laws imposed upon them.
Unsurprisingly,
<a href="http://www.dict.org/bin/Dict?Form=Dict2&Database=*&Query=autonomy">my dictionary</a>
defines autonomy as, "the power or right of self-government; self-government,
or political independence, of a city or a state".</p>

<p>However, it is personal autonomy, as applied to individuals, that I am
interested in exploring.</p>

<p>An autonomous person is, "obedient to a law that one prescribes to
oneself" (to paraphrase Rousseau). Such a person leads their life in a manner
that is consistent with a set of beliefs, values and principles that are the
outcome of reflection and self evaluation. As Socrates famously said, "the
unexamined life is not worth living". Furthermore, an autonomous person is
not only capable of considering, deciding and acting but <em>does so in all
three cases</em>. To act without self-reflection - perhaps out of habit or
because of an unthinking obedience to received "normal" modes of behaviour -
is not autonomy.</p>

<img src="/static/images/socrates.jpg" alt="Socrates"/>

<p>For someone to possess autonomy not only should they have the capacity for
self-reflection but they should have the additional two external requirements
of freedom to act without imposition and freedom to act according to their
principles. Perhaps the most famous description of such freedoms can be found
in Isiah Berlin's essay, "Two Concepts of Liberty" (Berlin uses the words
"freedom" and "liberty" interchangeably) in which he defines <em>positive</em>
and <em>negative</em> freedom.</p>

<p>Berlin introduces these concepts by relating each to a question:</p>

<blockquote>...the negative sense, is involved in the answer to the question
"What is the area within which the subject - a person or a group of persons -
is or should be left to do or be what he is able to do or be, without
interference by other persons?" The second, ...the positive sense, is involved
in the answer to the question "What or who, is the source of control or
interference that can determine someone to do, or be, this rather than that?"
</blockquote>

<p>Let's unpack these two aspects of freedom / liberty:</p>

<p>Put simply, negative liberty is <em>freedom from coercion or
interference</em>. Berlin qualifies this by claiming that coercion implies
deliberate interference from others. As Berlin puts it,

<blockquote>If I say I am unable to jump more than ten feet in the air [...]
it would be eccentric to say that I am to that degree enslaved or coerced. You
lack political liberty or freedom only if you are prevented from attaining the
goal by human beings.
</blockquote>

<p>In the context of autonomy, negative liberty affords the opportunity for
self reflection or decision making on one's own terms. As Berlin points out,
in a wider sense one's "freedom" to act may be limited by laws of nature but
this is not our focus. Rather, we're concerned with coercion interfering with
our intent to act in such-and-such a way.</p>

<p>Alternatively, positive liberty is the <em>freedom to act in a particular
way</em>. It is the capacity to act based upon one's own choices and reasons.
Berlin insists,</p>

<blockquote>I wish to be the instrument of my own, not of other men's acts of
will. I wish to be a subject, not an object; to be moved by reasons, by
conscious purposes, which are my own, not by causes which affect me, as it
were, from outside. I wish to be somebody, not nobody; a doer - deciding, not
by external nature or by other men as if I were a thing, or an animal, or a
slave incapable of playing a human role, that is, of conceiving goals and
policies of my own and realising them.
</blockquote>

<p>Put simply, one can be free from interference (negative liberty) and free
to act (positive liberty) and in order to act autonomously one of these
freedoms is required.</p>

<p>Why only one? It's possible to act autonomously but only enjoy one of the
two sorts of liberty. For example, I have the positive freedom to
choose to drive on the wrong side of the road, and, under certain rare
circumstances may choose to do so although I ought to expect curtailment of
my negative freedoms via coercion in the form of the police. Alternatively, I
may enjoy the negative liberty to be free from coercion when applying to
one or another university but the decision concerning my offer of a place
does not rest with me (a positive freedom to attend). It's the decision of
the institutions to which I applied.</p>

<p>But are these freedoms the same as autonomy?</p>

<p>No. The will to act is missing - the capacity to take advantage of such
liberties. Consider the following, as a result of misinformation,
misunderstanding, habit or deception a person may not realise they have
liberty to act in some way or another. Perhaps they come from a town where
there are "Keep off the Grass" signs in every park and so they mistakenly
believe that this rule is the case for their current location when no such
rule is advertised or even exists. They are at liberty to walk where they will
but don't because of their ignorance.</p>

<img src="/static/images/keepoffthegrass.jpg" title="Keep off the Grass!"/>

<p>Therefore, there is a need for an open, enquiring and imaginative mind used
to engaging in reflection in order to discover and decide to take advantage
of such liberties.</p>

<p>And so we come full circle back to the capacity for self-reflection.</p>

<p>Unsurprisingly, I believe such an outlook ought to be
encouraged at school, via institutions such as professional organisations and
facilitated by the technology we invent, build and deploy.</p>

<p>Autonomy can also be paradoxical: strangely, I may act autonomously to
curtail the freedoms needed to act autonomously. For example, I may freely
choose to join the army causing me to live a necessarily un-autonomous
life.</p>

<p>Furthermore, we regularly curtail our own and each other's autonomy in
order to act autonomously: this is perhaps best encapsulated in the term "wage
slave", a situation where one is forced to work in order to earn enough to pay
for some other thing perceived to be more valuable than one's current autonomy
(such as a mortgage, family holiday abroad or merely earning enough to make
ends meet).</p>

<p>More puzzling still, many are paid to curtail other people's autonomy: I'm
often asked to design software that is purposely limited until you pay money
- and even then it is only designed to work in a specific pre-defined
manner (for example, you have to pay to join a dating website, and even then,
you're limited by not being able to contact your potential dates directly).
This is politely (and mistakenly) called "business", but an (understandably)
cynical person would prefer the term "exploitation".</p>

<p>Finally, exercising personal autonomy is how we decide and act upon life's
big questions of a political, ethical and personal nature. It is this reason,
ultimately, that explains why I believe it to be such an important attribute.
It's also why the promotion of autonomy is the stated primary aim of
<a href="/article/build-a-drogulus">the drogulus</a>.</p>

<p><small>Image credits:
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Socrates_Louvre.jpg">Socrates</a>.
&copy; 2005
<a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utilisateur:Sting">Eric Gaba</a>
(under a
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/deed.en">creative commons</a>
license).
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/8236043793/">Keep off the Grass</a>. &copy; 2012
<a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/mirsasha/">Mirsasha</a> (under a
<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/deed.en_GB">creative commons</a> license).
</small></p>
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 March 2014 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>Pachelbel's Canon</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/pachelbel-canon</link>
        <description><h1><a href="/article/pachelbel-canon">Pachelbel's Canon</a></h1><p class="published_on">Wednesday 15th January 2014 (10:30PM)</p>

<p>I've been exchanging emails with my buddy
<a href="http://www.flourish.org">Francis</a>. We've been discussing classical
music. Much of the discussion has been about discerning the "clever stuff"
that may not be immediately obvious when listening to a piece of music.</p>

<p>It's possible to listen to any sort of music and simply enjoy the
sensation of the sounds. I do this quite often. However, there's also a hidden
world of clever, sneaky and fun tricks that composers and performers use to
bring about a performance. To use a mathematical analogy, it's the difference
between just appreciating the beautiful picture of the fractal (below)
compared to having the additional understanding of the simple and rather
beautiful mathematics that bring it into existence.</p>

<p><img src="/static/images/fractal.jpg" alt="An image of a fractal"/></p>

<p>Put simply, sometimes it's fun to know exactly what's going on (in a
musical sense). Unfortunately, in the context of classical music, this usually
requires both historical and theoretical knowledge. So what do you do if you
don't have this knowledge? In the case of Francis, an obvious starting point
is to explore the classical pieces he already enjoys. When I asked him what
classical recordings he owned he replied,</p>

<blockquote>I have and quite like Faure's Pavane, and Pachelbel's Canon.
Frustratingly though when I play them now they feel like cliches. This is
partly because I know them from childhood, so there's nothing new to me.
Partly because I don't know how to engage deeper beyond them.</blockquote>

<p>So, I want to lift the curtain on Pachelbel's Canon and give you a sense of
some of the non-obvious "clever stuff" happening in the piece. I assume no
prior musical knowledge.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/JdxkVQy7QLM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Rob Paravonian's humorous rant (above) centres around the fact that the
poor cellist (playing the lowest part) plays the same sequence of eight notes
28 times. This is a special type of <em>ostinato</em> (repeated pattern)
called a <em>ground bass</em>. As Rob demonstrates, the ground bass is a
technique that's (over) used in a lot of pop music. In the baroque period (the
historical era during which Pachelbel was writing) composers used it as
an anchor within a piece so that the listener had some sort of expectation of
what was coming next. The clever bit is how the composer plays with our
expectations by setting contrasting, surprising and clever melodies over the
top of the ground bass.</p>

<p>In Pachelbel's case he starts by setting a very simple, regular step-wise
melody above the ground bass. As the piece continues each new repetition of
the ground bass has an increasingly complex setting above it until the melody
is moving quite quickly, is rhythmically more interesting (it's uneven) and
jumps around in pitch. Following this "climax" (yes, that is the correct term)
the melody gradually transforms into a slower moving, simpler and more
relaxed state that draws the piece to a close.</p>

<p>This is a sketch of the form of the piece at the macro (high)
level. But there are other levels of "resolution" that can be viewed under our
musical microscope.</p>

<p>For example, have you wondered why the piece is called "Pachelbel's Canon"
and not "Pachelbel's Ground Bass"? Well, a musical canon is a contrapuntal
technique where a single melody is played on top of itself with voices coming
in one after the other. You probably already know several canons and have
perhaps sung some at school: "Row, Row, Row Your Boat" and "Frere Jacques" are
well known examples. In any case, the way a canon is performed
is always the same: a first voice starts to sing or play the melody and, at
some regular period of time later, <em>N</em> number of voices gradually
join in one after the other and play the melody.</p>

<p>It is this "canonical" technique that Pachelbel uses. The piece is written
in four parts: the ground bass and three melody parts. However, each of the
melody parts plays <em>exactly the same melody</em> but offset by one
repetition of the ground bass. So, not only does the melody mysteriously fit
with the ground bass, but it fits with itself. Furthermore, Pachelbel has
organised things so that the macro form of the piece (the feeling of a
gradual build up to a climax followed by a relaxation to the end) emerges from
such micro level interactions between the different parts.</p>

<p>Cool huh..?</p>

<p>All of the features I describe above can be heard if you listen very
carefully. However, don't expect to hear them all at once! This is why so
much classical music deserves repeated listening because there's always
something new to spot! The following video is particularly useful because
the <a href="http://www.musanim.com/">Musanim</a> project have superimposed
a graphical version of the score that follows the performance. The ground
bass is represented by the blue blocks at the bottom of the screen and the
red, brown and yellow blocks represent each of the three melody parts.
Basically, the vertical axis is pitch (how high or low a note sounds) the
horizontal axis is time and colour represents the part being played (sometimes
the colours change if parts play the same note). If you watch and listen very
carefully you'll be able to spot the canonical relationship between each of
the melody parts.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/cweUyEDwd3o" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<p>Hang on a minute, if there are only four parts in the piece why are there
six performers..?</p>

<p>Obviously the cello is playing the ground bass. Each of the violinists is
playing one of the melody parts. The first violin is on the left, second in
the middle and the third to the right of the organ. Right of the organ? What's
an organ doing in there and what on earth is that funky guitar like thing on
the far right?</p>

<p>Well, these are the continuo group - a sort of Baroque-era rhythm section
(the instrument on the far right is, in fact, a Theorbo - a member of the lute
family of instruments). They follow the bass part (in this piece it's the
ground bass played by the cello) and improvise harmonic "filling" in much the
same way that a rhythm guitarist in a pop group or pianist in a jazz trio
do.</p>

<p>Now, watch the performance again, but this time I want you to concentrate
on what the performers are actually doing. Notice how they move a lot, swaying
from side to side and often change where they're facing. Since they're all
reading their parts they have to keep together in some way. Obviously they're
listening very carefully to each other but they're also aware of each other's
movements through the corner of their eyes. As a result they're able to get
a sense of what everyone else is doing and collectively work as an ensemble.
At certain points you'll see them glance, make eye contact with each other and
even smile. This is another means of non-verbal communication the players use
to keep their sense of ensemble (you see the third violinist do this about
halfway through the performance). Finally, at the end when they need to
coordinate the close of the performance everyone is looking at the first
violinist on the far left to get a sense of how the music is slowing down and
ultimately coming to a stop.</p>

<p>Each group works in a different way and watching an ensemble's group
dynamics is yet another aspect of classical music that allows for repeated
listening. It's fun to compare and contrast the different ways in which
performers react to and perform a piece of music</p>

<p>I hope you enjoy listening!</p>

<p><small>Image credits: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mandel_zoom_12_satellite_spirally_wheel_with_julia_islands.jpg">Fractal</a>
&copy; wikimedia.org under a Creative Commons
license.</small></p>
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 January 2014 22:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>