<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
    <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://ntoll.org/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The personal website of Nicholas H.Tollervey</description>
    <image>
        <url>http://ntoll.org/static/images/logo.png</url>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/</link>
        <title>ntoll.org ~ everything I say is false</title>
    </image>
    
    <item>
        <title>Vocation</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/vocation</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/vocation</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/vocation&quot;&gt;Vocation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Wednesday 2nd December 2015 (1:30AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do you do what you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all &quot;do&quot; different things and fulfil many roles, but our
&lt;em&gt;vocation&lt;/em&gt; is usually how we answer, &quot;what do you do?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I&#x27;m a programmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are more than just our vocation, it is but a small aspect of who we are,
what we do and why we do it. A vocation also pigeon-holes so there is a danger
of prejudice (for instance, the vast majority of programmers are not spotty,
socially awkward single men). Furthermore, our vocation defines us in terms
of our economic value (it is how we earn money).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the notion of vocation is so strong there is a danger that it
dominates how we find meaning in our lives. Everything appears to flow from our
vocation: money to pay for the things we think we need. Our life is reduced to
a struggle to &quot;do a thing to afford another thing&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2012/feb/01/top-five-regrets-of-the-dying&quot;&gt;This wonderful article from 2012&lt;/a&gt;
supplies an interesting contrast to such a world view. It lists five common
themes the dying focus on when asked, &quot;what would you have done differently?&quot;
(the same question I posed at the start but expressed in the past tense)...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I wish I&#x27;d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life
    others expected of me.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I wish I hadn&#x27;t worked so hard.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I wish I&#x27;d had the courage to express my feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I wish I had stayed in touch with my friends.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I wish that I had let myself be happier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the themes directly reference vocation nor is the resolution of
such wishes encumbered by money. For example, I can&#x27;t buy &quot;staying in touch
with my friends&quot;. It depends upon my own efforts to remain close to those I
hold dear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It suggests to me that acting without the expectation of debt or obligation
to or from others can be a source of happiness and good. Act for intrinsic
value rather than financial or material benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I&#x27;ll ask again: why do you do what you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, comments, constructive critique and ideas most welcome (with the
caveat that these are rather raw thoughts that I may revise at some later
date).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2015 01:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>What IS the meaning of life?</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/meaning-of-life</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/meaning-of-life</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/meaning-of-life&quot;&gt;What IS the meaning of life?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Thursday 19th November 2015 (1:00AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please file this under Nicholas-is-a-smart-arse. :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Bt84uBuGKNk?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, &quot;what is the meaning of life?&quot; is viewed as a difficult
question. Nothing could be further from the truth, so let&#x27;s just get
to the answer shall we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#x27;re simply asking in the wrong way. Instead of wondering what
&lt;em&gt;something is&lt;/em&gt;, we can flip the question around and ask &lt;em&gt;what its
opposite isn&#x27;t&lt;/em&gt;. Ergo, honestly listing the reasons for not killing
yourself tells you what gives meaning to your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try it for yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the answer is different for each of us and changes over time. But
that&#x27;s essentially it: asking the meaning of life is solved with a glib
philosopher&#x27;s dinner party trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didn&#x27;t I tell you to file this under Nicholas-is-a-smart-arse?!?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Wait a minute...&quot; I hear you ask, &quot;there must be more to it than that! What
about deep stuff like God?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, what about God?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an atheist and find it hard to discuss &quot;God&quot; seriously. To give you a
flavour of what I mean (and I&#x27;m certainly not trying to be disrespectful here)
when discussing religion please replace &quot;God&quot; with
&quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.venganza.org/about/open-letter/&quot;&gt;flying spaghetti
monster&lt;/a&gt;&quot; and &quot;heaven&quot; with
&quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.orwelltoday.com/orwellreligion.shtml&quot;&gt;Sugarcandy
Mountain&lt;/a&gt;&quot;. If the result starts to sound silly, then you have a sense
of how all religious discussion sounds to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I&#x27;m a smart-arse, perhaps I should top the meaning of life with
proof that there is no god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I don&#x27;t have to because the burden of proof is not my
responsibility ~ it&#x27;s religious people who are asserting something (that there
is a god).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s play another word replacement game to illustrate what I mean: where a
religious person might say &quot;God&quot; let&#x27;s say
&quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russell&#x27;s_teapot&quot;&gt;a teapot orbiting the Sun&lt;/a&gt;&quot;
instead. As a result the assertion becomes &quot;I believe there&#x27;s
a teapot orbiting the Sun&quot; to which I might reply, &quot;oh no there isn&#x27;t&quot;. The
response, &quot;OK smart-arse, prove there is no teapot orbiting the Sun&quot; shows
how bonkers and untenable such a position is. Any reasonable
person would expect the person making such assertions to be the one to prove
there is a teapot orbiting the Sun, rather than waiting for me to prove there
isn&#x27;t such celestial brewing equipment. Put simply, just because it&#x27;s possible
to assert something that is blatantly unverifiable doesn&#x27;t make it true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite example of this phenomenon is a drogulus ~ an entity whose
presence is unverifiable, because it has no physical effects. The atheist
philosopher
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A._J._Ayer&quot;&gt;A.J.Ayer&lt;/a&gt;
coined it as a way of ridiculing the belief system of his friend, the Jesuit
philosopher,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frederick_Copleston&quot;&gt;Frederick
Copleston&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1949 Ayer and Copleston took part in a radio debate about the existence of
God. The debate then went back and forth, until Ayer came up with the following
as a way of illustrating the point that Copleston&#x27;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metaphysics&quot;&gt;metaphysics&lt;/a&gt;
had no content
because there was no way of testing the truth of metaphysical assertions. He
said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I say, &#x27;There&#x27;s a &quot;drogulus&quot; over there,&#x27; and you say, &#x27;What?&#x27; and
I say, &#x27;drogulus&#x27; and you say &#x27;What&#x27;s a drogulus?&#x27; Well, I say, &#x27;I can&#x27;t
describe what a drogulus is, because it&#x27;s not the sort of thing you can see or
touch, it has no physical effects of any kind, but it&#x27;s a disembodied
being.&#x27; And you say, &#x27;Well how am I to tell if it&#x27;s there or it&#x27;s not
there?&#x27; and I say, &#x27;There&#x27;s no way of telling. Everything&#x27;s just the same
if it&#x27;s there or it&#x27;s not there. But the fact is it&#x27;s there. There&#x27;s a
drogulus there standing just behind you, spiritually behind you.&#x27; Does that
makes sense?&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the natural answer Ayer was waiting for was &quot;No, of course it
doesn&#x27;t make sense.&quot; Therefore, the implication would be that metaphysics is
like the &quot;drogulus&quot; ~ a being which cannot be seen and has no perceptible
effects. If Ayer can get to that point, he can claim that any kind of belief
in the Christian God or in metaphysical principles in general is really
contrary to our logical and scientific understanding of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what am I saying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is a complicated question - it&#x27;s not just synonymous for &quot;what is my
argument?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The examples above demonstrate that language is a source of confusion.
It&#x27;s possible to ask, &quot;what am I saying?&quot; in a more fundamental way -
synonymous with &quot;what do words mean?&quot;. Habit or familiarity appear
to lead to lazy thinking: some &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; must be true because it&#x27;s
repeated in such-and-such a way by lots of people. Yet, &lt;em&gt;when the way that
thing is expressed in language is explored it becomes obvious it&#x27;s actually
confused and a tad silly&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself, what is the &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt; of &quot;life&quot;? (Or any other word or
turn of phrase.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what&#x27;s my argument? ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If language is such a blunt tool and endless source of confusion how are we
to discuss important subjects such as how to lead a good life? How
are we to share complex and confusing ideas such as our dreams, loves and
losses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be best to merely act, observe, reflect and adjust. Know me
by what I do, how I act and the way that I change myself rather than by what I
might say (to be clear, the content of this article is covered by this
assertion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, file this under Nicholas-is-a-smart-arse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I&#x27;d love feedback, constructive critique and ideas about such
raw thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;:-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
        <title>PyCon India</title>
        <link>http://ntoll.org/article/india</link>
        <guid>http://ntoll.org/article/india</guid>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ntoll.org/article/india&quot;&gt;PyCon India&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;published_on&quot;&gt;Saturday 24th October 2015 (1:00AM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an enormous honour to be invited as a keynote speaker at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://in.pycon.org/&quot;&gt;PyCon India&lt;/a&gt;. It turned out to be one of
my most enjoyable PyCons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://python.org/&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; programming community is famous
for being a diverse and welcoming place. Apparently someone once said that
they&#x27;d came to Python for the programming language, but stayed because of the
community. That has been my experience too. Visiting PyCon India reinforced
this outlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python is free software in two ways: anyone is free to make use of it in
any way they see fit and it is given away for free. To paraphrase, it is
both free as in speech and free as in beer. Volunteering time, effort and
expertise is at the core of the Python community and every PyCon is different
since it reflects the volunteer community that organises it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 1500 attendees PyCon India is the second largest PyCon in the
world. The reason it is so big is because the organisers have managed to
foster and grow a community of amazing volunteers to run the conference. This
was brought home to me during my first evening in India: wanting to make some
friends I turned up at the conference venue to volunteer in some way. I ended
up stuffing 1500 swag bags (full of leaflets from the conference sponsors),
in what can only be described as a nerdy form of &quot;keep-fit&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It works like this: volunteers
run around in circles holding open bags while others stand in the middle
throwing &quot;swag&quot; into them. At the end of each lap yet more volunteers are on
hand to stack the bags ready for distribution to the attendees the next day.
This process starts haphazardly, but people change roles and slot
themselves in where there are bottlenecks in order to improve the efficiency
of the &quot;bag stuffing algorithm&quot;. Other techniques to speed things up included
shouting a lot, chanting and laughing at each other. This process is
beautifully illustrated in the following video of a &quot;lap&quot; that I took on my
mobile phone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Ejr6iqqCdhc?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the evening we were a well oiled machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, the first full conference day, was interesting - I was still used
to UK time so when my alarm went off at 6am (or around 1:30 am UK time) I
decided to sleep in for &quot;just another 10 minutes&quot;. Four hours later I was
woken by a phone call from reception. An Indian buddy had turned up at my
hotel to look for me and give me a lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&#x27;d come on a motorbike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d never been on a motorbike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, my first time on a motorbike was sitting on the back, hanging onto this
dude&#x27;s back pack, no helmet, dust in my eyes, zipping through Bangalore&#x27;s
morning rush-hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Is it safe?&quot; I asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Of course it is...&quot;, he replied. &quot;The traffic is so bad we never go faster than 15 mph anyway!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick appears to be not to pay attention to all the car horns, shouting
and never to look over your shoulder at what could squish you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also observed that traffic lights in Bangalore are only for decorative
purposes. I particularly enjoyed getting stuck at a junction and giving an
ancient lady in a colourful sari sat on the back of an adjacent moped a
big grin and having it returned (but without teeth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following video (taken from the relative safety of a taxi) doesn&#x27;t
even begin to convey the chaos of the traffic in Bangalore. Can you spot the
stray cow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/6KOLKBoPF9A?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course of the conference I found everyone, without exception,
to be very friendly and I was made to feel very welcome. Thank you to my new
friends in India for your wonderful warm hospitality. I hope that if you ever
make it to the UK we&#x27;ll be able to welcome you as well as you did me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday was the day of my keynote. I was addressing all 1500 delegates in
the main hall and I&#x27;d chosen to focus on education as the topic of my
presentation. I was actually really looking forward to giving the talk and
had a lot of fun whilst giving it. The live demo went well, people laughed at
my jokes, they had lots of interesting questions and it took me about an hour
and a half to field all the comments I received in the corridor afterwards.
In fact, one of the organisers told me that my keynote was a top trending item
on Twitter in India. Wow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the whole thing in the video below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Q3kXXtlviiM?rel=0&amp;amp;controls=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I love to get feedback (both good and bad). Please feel free to
&lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;drop me a line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special mention should be made of the two main organisers, Vijay Kumar and
Kracekumar Ramaraju, who put on an amazing event. I&#x27;d also like to publicly
thank my friend Kushal Das and his family and colleagues for being my guides
around Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I go back to India? Absolutely! It&#x27;s an amazing place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a privilege.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2015 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
    </item>
    
</channel>
</rss>